<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>stevenmaude.co.uk</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/</id><updated>2017-04-04T13:55:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Building a music collection on a budget</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/building-a-music-collection-on-a-budget" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-04T13:55:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-04-04T13:55:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-04-04:posts/building-a-music-collection-on-a-budget</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of months back I wrote something on trying to find inexpensive music
for DJ sets for DJ TechTools which just &lt;a href="http://djtechtools.com/2017/04/02/dj-music-for-a-budget-beatmatcher/"&gt;got posted
there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's another two tips here that I didn't think to include there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="amazon-primes-no-rush-delivery"&gt;Amazon Prime's No-Rush delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least in the UK, if you have an Amazon Prime account, and you buy things
shipped from Amazon, currently you're probably eligible to opt for a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=201910750"&gt;slower
delivery&lt;/a&gt;
with the benefit of a £1 digital credit applied to your account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This credit can be used for music purchases, and as individual MP3s on Amazon
are often just 99p or less, that usually means you can pick up a track for free
in addition to whatever you actually were ordering in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's possible to further benefit from this too. When you're planning an order
of multiple eligible items, breaking that one order up into orders of
individual items allows you to multiply the credit by the number of items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you do use the credit though since they expire after some time. It's
maybe worth keeping a want list to ensure you know exactly what to spend your
next credit on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="compilations-can-be-competitively-priced"&gt;Compilations can be competitively priced&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With compilations, you'll often find that, versus buying individual tracks,
you'll get more value for money, and can be a quick way to build up a
collection, especially if you're looking for well-known hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are, say, five tracks that you're after on a compilation, and you get
another fifty or so bundled in for a few pounds more than buying the five
individual digital tracks, that's not a bad deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you get the case where the CD version of the compilation
contains mixes, whereas the digital version may have the mixes (which
you probably don't care about too much; there are more mixes around than
I'd ever have time to listen to) and the individual tracks (which you do
want).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to sound like I'm just advertising Amazon here, as it may
be that other digital music stores offer the same kind of deals,
although I've not investigated them. But, Amazon can be particularly
competitive, again when you "arbitrage" buying MP3s via lower priced CDs
which feature
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=201377450"&gt;AutoRip&lt;/a&gt;
bundled MP3s, as I mentioned in the &lt;a href="http://djtechtools.com/2017/04/02/dj-music-for-a-budget-beatmatcher/"&gt;original DJ TechTools
post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example: at the time of writing, &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/I-Love-Garage-Various-Artists/dp/B0163D5WEQ/"&gt;this
compilation&lt;/a&gt;
is £5 for the CD &lt;strong&gt;which has MP3s provided via AutoRip&lt;/strong&gt;, versus £9.99 for
the MP3 version. Seeing Roy Davis Jr's Gabriel on there, you might think
that £5 for just that track is worth paying, but there are another 65
tracks on there too.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Surprisingly, there's very little filler on
there, and while there are a few radio edits on there, most tracks are
the full length versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bonus here is that you also get instant digital delivery on the
bundled MP3s when buying the CD version too. The only differences are
that you've paid less and get a redundant bit of plastic through the
post a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it was such ridiculously good value, I just impulse bought that
  compilation.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="DJ"></category><category term="MP3"></category><category term="music"></category></entry><entry><title>Type:Rider: A Re:view</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/typerider-a-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-29T00:31:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-03-29T00:31:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-03-29:posts/typerider-a-review</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="a-journey-through-history"&gt;A journey through history&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typography is ubiquitous and present in our daily lives, often without even
noticing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a quote from &lt;a href="http://typerider.arte.tv/"&gt;Type:Rider&lt;/a&gt;, what the
developers call a "game documentary" and what I'd call a slightly frustrating,
albeit compelling museum-style whistle stop tour through fonts and typography
across human civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the quote is spot on. Typography is everywhere, and though that's difficult
to imagine for us today — just take a look around — it wasn't always like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type:Rider goes on a journey from cave paintings, through to early writing
systems, such as cuneiform and hieroglyphics, then onwards to the spread of
printing across late medieval Europe, and the continued development of fonts,
typography, all the way to the current age where words being marked on media
has made way for being displayed on screen instead. So then, this is as much a
study of the spread of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only is it a journey through history for the player, but for the two dots
comprising a colon that the player controls. They roll along the level and can,
somewhat inexplicably, jump and wall jump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="typerider-is-no-nightsky"&gt;Type:Rider is no NightSky&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why two dots when, say, a full stop could have sufficed? Perhaps that's to
avoid accusations of being a clone of Nifflas' relaxing
&lt;a href="http://nifflas.ni2.se/?page=NightSky"&gt;NightSky&lt;/a&gt;. If anything, the extra dot is
a hindrance; it makes the clumsy platforming even clumsier, and doesn't really
add anything to the gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extra dot aside, it is reminiscent of NightSky (itself a game you should check
out) and I think the difficulty and the slightly sparse, often monochrome
foreground level layouts are why comparisons are drawn to Playdead's
&lt;a href="http://www.playdead.com/games/limbo/"&gt;Limbo&lt;/a&gt;. That, as well as the difficulty.
The difficulty is another reason that Type:Rider seems to get compared to
Trials, but this is a more loose association only. The Trials games are finely
balanced and tuned, so as to allow for mastery of very delicate, precise
controls. Type:Rider, unfortunately, is not. Quite often you'll end up bouncing
off uselessly from walls, or find your &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xfKhDiUNOG0"&gt;pitiful leaps are insufficient to jump
the chasms&lt;/a&gt; that you need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK. It's not actually that glitchy — it's definitely no &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3MWEHwvcnyM"&gt;Sonic the Hedgehog
2006&lt;/a&gt; — but the floatiness of how
the dots "jump" and move, mean that there are some sections that are
frustrating where you'll repeatedly bounce to your doom. With the addition of a
couple of cheap instant death sections which seem like they were thrown in as
attempts to add tension, it would have been just nicer to have a relaxing, easy
to progress through, game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, restarts are quick and the checkpoints frequent, so it's rare
that you find yourself repeating familiar ground. It does still break the flow
of what would be an otherwise relaxing experience, but this at least tempers
player frustration. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="but-typeriders-still-worth-a-look"&gt;But Type:Rider's still worth a look&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all a pity, because the actual atmosphere, that of something like a very
immersive museum exhibit is a pleasant one. The graphic designs of the levels,
and the integration of fonts into them, are well thought out, and thematically
cohesive in the ideas they're trying to portray and show imagination. The
historical background is provided via brief, but informative, texts that are
collected throughout the levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some peculiar issues, likely due to a quickly thrown together English
localisation. There is one notably particularly bad translation that recurs
throughout: the term &lt;em&gt;wheelbase&lt;/em&gt; peculiarly gets mentioned in the text several
times. The Steam discussion forum for the game actually answered this: it's a
&lt;a href="https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/french-english/empattement"&gt;badly proofread
translation&lt;/a&gt;:
it should be &lt;em&gt;serif&lt;/em&gt;. Likewise, there are some weird text kerning issues in the
history text too, and it's likely that these too don't occur in the French
original. But that's an oversight considering that the game is dealing with
typography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of the game means that it is limited to telling a few stories, but as
an introduction to some of the big names in history and the technological
advances made, it does a good job. It is interesting just how important the
onset of widespread dissemination of information has been, and the impact that
has had since. We take the immediacy of that for granted now — you could well
be reading this text that I wrote seconds after I published it on this site,
wherever you are in the world — but the distribution of printed works on any
useful scale wasn't even a concept until the late medieval period, just a few
hundred years ago. It's difficult to comprehend that when information is so
central to society now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also interesting where Type:Rider leaves off, which is the development of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generalized_Markup_Language"&gt;markup languages&lt;/a&gt;,
and computer bitmap and vector fonts. A really big omission, perhaps because it
was made a few years ago, back in 2013, is emoji. (However, emoji were big
enough in 2013 to make it into the &lt;a href="http://public.oed.com/the-oed-today/recent-updates-to-the-oed/previous-updates/december-2013-update/new-words-katherine-martin/"&gt;Oxford English
Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;.)
Electronic communication saw the incorporation of emoticons, constructed from
text to hint at tone where plain text may be ambiguous. That's been followed by
the widespread use of emoji, where characters visually represent concepts or
objects, and so that nicely brings us full circle: modern day communication
harking back to how writing systems first began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the idea of spending a couple of hours learning about typography is
something that sounds appealing, Type:Rider's worth spending the time with.
Just take the gameplay for what it is, which is occasionally relaxing,
sometimes frustrating, be prepared to work through the trickier sections. It's
certainly hard to dislike a work that even manages to make a valiant attempt of
painting &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2017/mar/28/how-we-made-font-comic-sans-typography"&gt;Comic Sans
MS&lt;/a&gt;
in a somewhat sympathetic light.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="game"></category><category term="review"></category></entry><entry><title>If you want my money, please state your payment processor clearly</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/if-you-want-my-money-please-state-your-payment-processor-clearly" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-06T23:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-06T23:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-03-06:posts/if-you-want-my-money-please-state-your-payment-processor-clearly</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I got a nice letter in the post informing me that my vehicle tax
was due. Wonderful news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, off I dutifully went to the appropriate &lt;a href="https://gov.uk"&gt;GOV.UK&lt;/a&gt;
site to pay the tax: it's not like it's an option if you want to keep
your car on the road legally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're not in the UK, or you are but haven't taxed a vehicle
recently, it's quite simple. They send you a paper reminder. This is
also a form that you can take into a Post Office and pay there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paying this online, you're asked for a reference number from the
reminder. There's a check made that your car has a valid &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOT_test"&gt;MOT
certificate&lt;/a&gt; (which establishes
your vehicle's roadworthiness) and then asks you for payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I'm using
&lt;a href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/taking-control-of-chromium-and-chrome"&gt;uMatrix&lt;/a&gt; in
my browser, I can spot which sites other than the one I'm directly
visiting have content which is supposed to be loaded into the current
page. The payment form didn't initially load and I noticed a blocked
site: "ephapay.net".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, I've never heard of them: let's check them out and make sure they're
someone I can trust. I didn't anticipate that the UK government's
website would be using someone dodgy, but best to check anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few searches via web search engines didn't reveal anything about this
domain. Even weirder, the WHOIS information is all hidden by a privacy
service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admin Name: PERFECT PRIVACY, LLC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely a legitimate payment processor wouldn't hide their details?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did reveal who was operating the site was right at the end of the
WHOIS information, in the name server details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Name Server: NS1.THE-LOGIC-GROUP.COM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and turns out to be benign. They're a payment processor that got
acquired by Barclaycard in 2014. And I've heard of Barclaycard&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. And
the WHOIS information for the-logic-group.com actually points to their
business address. So, it seems that at least they're a established
company (since 1988, a Companies House search will tell you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I had to dig through to establish all that. It would have been much
easier if the GOV.UK vehicle tax site just stated clearly who the
payment processor is. I almost considered just reverting to paying the
tax in person when I first encountered the mysterious site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the UK government has going for them is that road users who want to
stay legal must pay this, so one way or another, online or offline,
they'll get your cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are other sites that have similar behaviour and don't have a
captive audience. There have been several cases where I'm interested in
paying for a product or service, and hit some anonymous looking page or
iframe pointing somewhere else, where it's down to my browser showing
details of blocked requests and content that reveal who's handling
payment (yes, of course, you could also search in the source too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, common culprits of having vague payment pages are sites that
handle ticket payments for small shows, or sites that let you book a
place at running events. I'm sure there are more. And it really does
deter me: if I'm not sure if my payment details are safe, I'd rather not
bother, especially if it's something I can live without.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're designing a website, bear this in mind: for the sake of
placing a small, clear explanation of how payment works, and why the
user should trust you and your payment processor, you can remove another
stumbling block that you're putting in the way of getting more paranoid
or technically savvy users to give you money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If nothing else, you have them to thank/blame for inspiring Rowan
Atkinson's Johnny English.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="security"></category><category term="UI"></category><category term="UX"></category></entry><entry><title>Fixing horrible wireless network pings in Ubuntu (2017 edition)</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/fixing-horrible-wireless-network-pings-in-ubuntu-2017-edition" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-03T16:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-03T16:44:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-03-03:posts/fixing-horrible-wireless-network-pings-in-ubuntu-2017-edition</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I was using my laptop on battery power and I remembered that I
hadn't disabled wifi power management since I reinstalled Ubuntu in
late 2016. With power management enabled for wifi, I find I get laggy
internet on battery power, and pings are noticeably higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you suspect this is affecting you, it's easy to check:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ iwconfig 2&amp;gt; /dev/null &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; grep &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Power Management&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
Power Management:on
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the &lt;a href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/horrible-wireless-network-pings-in"&gt;method I wrote about
previously to disable wifi power
management&lt;/a&gt; no
longer works. My guess is that this is due to Ubuntu switching to
systemd in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you need to use an alternative approach as &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/jcberthon/ea8cfe278998968ba7c5a95344bc8b55"&gt;suggested in this
post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, look at your existing configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; /etc/NetworkManager/conf.d/
$ ls
default-wifi-powersave-on.conf
$ sudo cp default-wifi-powersave-on.conf wifi-powersave-off.conf
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The new .conf filename must follow any other files alphabetically, in
this case the filename must be one that's alphabetically later than
&lt;code&gt;default-wifi-powersave-on&lt;/code&gt;, so that it gets applied last, and your
modified setting overrides the default. If we named this file, e.g.
&lt;code&gt;a-wifi-powersave-off-config.conf&lt;/code&gt;, our new settings wouldn't apply
since the filename would then be ahead of
&lt;code&gt;default-wifi-powersave-on.conf&lt;/code&gt; alphabetically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, edit the new file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sudoedit wifi-powersave-off.conf
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Change what is likely a 3 in the &lt;code&gt;wifi.powersave&lt;/code&gt; line to 2. This
disables wireless power management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It likely will look like this when you've edited it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;[connection]
wifi.powersave = 2
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, restart NetworkManager and you should see that this change is now
in effect. It should also persist across reboots. You can confirm this
again with &lt;code&gt;iwconfig&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sudo systemctl restart NetworkManager
$ iwconfig 2&amp;gt; /dev/null &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; grep &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Power Management&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
Power Management:off
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="high"></category><category term="ping"></category><category term="latency"></category><category term="wireless"></category><category term="wifi"></category><category term="Ubuntu"></category></entry><entry><title>The dangers of long forgotten Bitbucket team accounts</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/the-dangers-of-long-forgotten-bitbucket-team-accounts" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-04T21:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-04T21:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-02-04:posts/the-dangers-of-long-forgotten-bitbucket-team-accounts</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month, I'd been reviewing some of the shared accounts for online
services we have at work. Often, users have an individual login for
online services. Some services don't offer that feature and there's a
single account that's shared by everyone. While digging around, I found
details for a shared Bitbucket account. If everyone has their own
Bitbucket account, then what's this one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logging in worked, and allowed me access to an account for the team
itself; there was no user, as such. Not only could this team account
access the team, but with full permissions. Furthermore, this account
had no settings of its own. If you accessed the settings page, you got
the team's settings, not that of this team account, so it wasn't
possible to change any security settings for the account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With one of these "legacy" accounts lying around, it's possible that it
is sat there with only password authentication — Bitbucket &lt;a href="https://blog.bitbucket.org/2015/09/10/two-step-verification-is-here/"&gt;introduced
two-factor
authentication&lt;/a&gt;
late, in 2015 — an unchangeable (and maybe weak, depending on your
policies) password, and with full team access.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this particularly insidious is that if you're not aware of
this account, you'll be blissfully unaware if you look at the list of
users on your team. Even if you manage the team as an administrator,
&lt;strong&gt;this team account didn't appear as an admin user&lt;/strong&gt;. I don't even think
it counts as a billed user. Someone who gains access presumably could
maintain that silently without you being able to do anything about it,
at least if they just sat there cloning your code. Mitigating that is
the audit log which would be a giveaway if anything noisy happened. By
that point though, someone malicious could still cause a lot of problems
for you by, let's say, booting out all other team members, or deleting
all your repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I had to contact support and request them to remove this
account, since there was no way I could fix this as a team
administrator. Therefore, this is definitely something worth auditing if
you think you might have such dormant accounts, even though, according
to Atlassian, this shouldn't be the case at all. They &lt;a href="https://blog.bitbucket.org/2014/01/14/important-changes-are-coming-to-teams/"&gt;earlier
stated&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting February 18, 2014, Bitbucket will remove the ability for
individuals to log into a team with a username/email and password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert your own &lt;a href="http://www.unicode.org/emoji/charts/emoji-list.html#1f937"&gt;Unicode shrug
character&lt;/a&gt;
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating new repositories failed, but, for instance, creating a
repo using my account (as a team administrator), then logging in as the
"team account" and using the team account to delete the test repo was
successful. I didn't test removing team members, but don't see why this
would have failed.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Bitbucket"></category><category term="security"></category></entry><entry><title>Switching BitLocker protection methods without re-encrypting</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/switching-bitlocker-protection-methods-without-re-encrypting" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-04T17:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-04T17:54:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-02-04:posts/switching-bitlocker-protection-methods-without-re-encrypting</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="overzealous-tpm-protection"&gt;Overzealous TPM protection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd set up BitLocker for someone using the Trusted Platform Module (TPM)
in their laptop with a PIN&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to decrypt the drive. Unfortunately, they
found that, after some time, the system tended to lock the PIN out,
unless they used a recovery key to bypass the TPM and PIN access
altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, this is some feature of the TPM in this particular
laptop where too many incorrectly entered passwords results in the TPM
locking out for some lengthy and possibly indefinite amount of time.
Perhaps even permanently. I don't think this is the case where incorrect
passwords are continually entered in a short time period, but where
incorrect attempts over a longer period are cumulatively logged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, this state doesn't seem to get reset even if you
subsequently re-enter the correct password, or unlock with another
method. (It seems reasonable that the TPM's unaware of whether
BitLocker's been unlocked or not by other means.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fixing-the-tpm"&gt;Fixing the TPM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can rectify this by &lt;a href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd851452(v=ws.11).aspx"&gt;resetting the TPM
lockout&lt;/a&gt;
but this is only a temporary fix. Again, after some number of password
failures the lockout may happen again. My conclusion in this case is
that, although disabling the TPM makes the system slightly less secure,
the greatest threat here is not an unauthorised user accessing the data,
but an authorised user being unable to access the data. Switching to
just a password unlock then seems more sensible. I wouldn't recommend
this downgrade in security otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first look, you might think that this is a chore to switch. There's
no obvious way of doing this in the BitLocker options for the drive, or
under Control Panel, and your instinct might be to decrypt the drive and
encrypt again. That can be time consuming, especially with large drives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="using-manage-bde-to-change-key-protection-methods"&gt;Using manage-bde to change key protection methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you can run the command line utility:
&lt;a href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff829848(v=ws.10).aspx"&gt;manage-bde&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since TPM plus PIN, or recovery key (or some other method of securing
your BitLocker encryption key) are key protection methods, Microsoft
terms them "protectors". Also, here we are looking at removing a TPM and
PIN protector, but you can use manage-bde to handle any BitLocker
protector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, you want to remove the existing TPM and PIN protector:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;manage-bde -protectors -delete &amp;lt;Drive&amp;gt; -tpmandpin
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You have to do this first, as it's not possible to have both TPM and PIN
protector, and a password protector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(A caution that &lt;code&gt;-delete&lt;/code&gt; without specifying &lt;code&gt;-type&lt;/code&gt; removes all
protectors and then will disable protection, so that you can still
access your drive in future. If you do that, you'll need to add new
protectors, as below, and you'll need to add new recovery protectors,
should you wish. You can do by specifying &lt;code&gt;-recoverypassword&lt;/code&gt; for a
numerical recovery code, or &lt;code&gt;-recoverykey&lt;/code&gt; for an external key in the
&lt;code&gt;-add&lt;/code&gt; command below. And then you must enable the protectors again with
&lt;code&gt;manage-bde -protectors -enable&lt;/code&gt;, including new recovery keys should you
wish to have them.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, add a new protector, e.g. a password:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;manage-bde -protectors -add &amp;lt;Drive&amp;gt; -password
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(&lt;code&gt;C:&lt;/code&gt; is the most likely &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;Drive&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; value here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll be prompted to enter, and then confirm, the new password. Now,
you'll have a password protector, which won't be subject to a TPM
lockout, as we wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can also check BitLocker status:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;manage-bde -protectors -status
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;to confirm that the drive is encrypted, and which key protectors are
active.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, password. You can configure Group Policy to allow passwords
with TPM, instead of just numerical PINs. Microsoft's documentation
always refers to this option as "TPM and PIN" regardless. This doesn't
change the BitLocker prompt: it still asks for a PIN.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="BitLocker"></category><category term="manage-bde"></category></entry><entry><title>Blocking URLs in emails from being opened in Thunderbird</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/blocking-urls-in-emails-from-being-opened-in-thunderbird" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-29T14:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-29T14:40:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-01-29:posts/blocking-urls-in-emails-from-being-opened-in-thunderbird</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'd got some unwanted spam message and wondered if it was possible to
stop accidental clicking on any URLs that are displayed in those cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out you can easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to the Edit menu &amp;gt; Preferences &amp;gt; Advanced &amp;gt; Config Editor. Skip past
the warning about changing advanced settings if it's displayed (you must
have already disabled it previously, if you don't see this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search for network.protocol-handler.external-default, right click the
option of that name that appears under Preference Name and select Toggle
to change it from the default (true) to false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you try to click on a URL now that's displayed in an email,
nothing will happen; your web browser won't open. However, you can
always copy the URL and paste into a browser yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Thunderbird"></category></entry><entry><title>The buzz (and hum) of learning a new instrument</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/the-buzz-and-hum-of-learning-a-new-instrument" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-21T18:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-21T18:41:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-01-21:posts/the-buzz-and-hum-of-learning-a-new-instrument</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Because I want to improve my skills in producing music, I've started taking
piano lessons. To start out with, I'm using a borrowed 61 key, touch sensitive
keyboard. I'd read around about this. Some people suggest you should always
learn on a piano, but my teacher suggested that's not necessary when first
starting out, at least until reaching ABRSM Grade 1 level. This has the benefit
of not having to invest a substantial amount of money into a digital piano,
should learning prove too difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing you realise when practising is that it's unlikely that anyone
else within hearing distance is going to appreciate the false starts and wrong
notes of a beginner playing piano. This is a big plus of keyboards or digital
pianos: a headphone socket means you can practise without irritating anyone
nearby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, duly plugging headphones in, I realised there was a substantial hum
(possibly ground hum) from the keyboard's output, even at zero volume,
and white noise which appears as the volume is cranked up. The same
happens in the speaker output, but is much less apparent and distracting
as it tends to get masked by ambient background noise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm usually quite fussy about unwanted noise, but I found this particularly
distracting when trying to concentrate. I would also say that you do tend to
get used to it over time and can maybe forget it's there a little, but ideally
I was looking to reduce or eliminate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="quietening-things-down"&gt;Quietening things down&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="solutions-i-considered-but-didnt-try"&gt;Solutions I considered but didn't try&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try another power supply. It's possible that this might not fix it, if
  the power supply isn't the source, so I didn't actually buy another to
  test this theory. (In this case, the keyboard can be powered by a
  substantial number of batteries, which would be an ideal test to
  diagnose whether the power supply is at fault here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Route the keyboard to a PC via MIDI to USB, play the keyboard via a
  digital audio workstation, and use a computer audio output instead of
  the keyboard's own output. This would work if you have PC audio that
  is noise-free. But, it means you then have to rely on having a PC
  around and powered on. Instead, I'd prefer to use an instrument
  directly; this way it actually keeps me away from a computer for once.
  If you're on a Windows PC, also bear in mind that you'll likely need
  decent ASIO drivers for your audio hardware, otherwise you might have
  to deal with considerable input latency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="solutions-i-used"&gt;Solutions I used&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use worse headphones. The budget Monoprice headphones I have did seem
  to reduce the noise a little compared with the Sennheiser HD25 I'd
  first tested out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add a ground loop isolator into the headphone socket on the keyboard
  and plug headphones into that. This did the trick for me. Since it's
  filtering the signal, it does also attenuate the volume, but that's a
  small price to pay for quiet. The going rate seems to be under £5 for
  cheap and cheerful generic kit, you can spend more on ones from the
  likes of Behringer, while some people even make their own DIY
  solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="keyboard"></category><category term="music"></category><category term="noise"></category></entry><entry><title>Installing pip, virtualenv and virtualenvwrapper tidily in Linux</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/installing-pip-virtualenv-and-virtualenvwrapper-tidily-in-linux" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-30T00:10:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-30T00:10:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2016-12-30:posts/installing-pip-virtualenv-and-virtualenvwrapper-tidily-in-linux</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I reinstalled my PC, I was thinking about the "cleanest" way that I
could get the Python tools I needed on there. Previously, I'd used the
pip bundled in the Ubuntu repositories, then found it was left to
languish, and was hideously out of date. (I think it is possible to
update if you've installed that way, but involves using &lt;code&gt;sudo pip
install -U&lt;/code&gt; all the time, which didn't seem sensible.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better option might be to install pip directly from the installer
that's provided by the pip developers, using pip to install virtualenv
and virtualenvwrapper, and then using the virtualenv tools to create
virtualenvs to actually install Python packages for development. This
way should create the minimum level of clutter you're adding to your
system's Python installation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, reading around, the suggestions here on &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/4324558/whats-the-proper-way-to-install-pip-virtualenv-and-distribute-for-python"&gt;doing a clean
installation&lt;/a&gt;
seemed an even better idea. You download the virtualenv package from
PyPI yourself, use Python to run the &lt;code&gt;virtualenv&lt;/code&gt; Python code directly
and use that to create a "bootstrap" virtualenv that you can then create
new virtualenvs from.  Note that these virtualenvs all include pip; no
need for extra work to get it installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is possible without doing any installation into the system's
Python at all, not even requiring any &lt;code&gt;pip install --user&lt;/code&gt; commands.
It's pretty simple to do. If you want to follow this along further and
add virtualenvwrapper too, see the Stack Overflow post for more details
(essentially, you need to get a copy of virtualenv via downloading it,
e.g. from PyPI, using curl or a web browser and then run &lt;code&gt;python
virtualenv.py $YOUR_CHOSEN_VIRTUALENV_DIRECTORY&lt;/code&gt;), then continue here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="getting-virtualenvwrapper-working"&gt;Getting virtualenvwrapper working&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though &lt;a href="https://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.io/en/latest/install.html#basic-installation"&gt;it's not recommended in the
documentation&lt;/a&gt;,
someone in the Stack Overflow comments said they'd got it working, so I
thought worth trying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I did was create a Python virtualenv purely for virtualenvwrapper
using the method in the Stack Overflow answer. I called the virtualenv
"virtualenvwrapper" and created it inside &lt;code&gt;$HOME/.virtualenvs&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I then activated this new virtualenv using &lt;code&gt;source
$HOME/.virtualenvs/virtualenvwrapper/bin/activate&lt;/code&gt; and did &lt;code&gt;pip install
virtualenvwrapper&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you modify your shell startup files as suggested in the
virtualenvwrapper documentation, you'll find you get an error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;virtualenvwrapper.sh: There was a problem running the initialization
hooks.     

If Python could not import the module virtualenvwrapper.hook_loader,
check that virtualenvwrapper has been installed for
VIRTUALENVWRAPPER_PYTHON=$VIRTUALENVWRAPPER_PYTHON and that PATH is
set properly.
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As virtualenvwrapper isn't installed in the default Python, the script
looks for it and understandably can't find it. It's a simple fix: just
activate the virtualenvwrapper virtualenv before this shell script is
sourced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you immediately deactivate the virtualenvwrapper virtualenv
again, you'll still have commands like &lt;code&gt;workon&lt;/code&gt; that function correctly
in your shell environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what I first tried was doing what the virtualenvwrapper documentation
suggests, and modifying shell startup files, but with extra activate and
deactivate steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;WORKON_HOME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.virtualenvs
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;PROJECT_HOME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.local/src 
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;source&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.virtualenvs/virtualenvwrapper/bin/activate
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;source&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.virtualenvs/virtualenvwrapper/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh
deactivate                                                          
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You will need to switch to some virtualenv first with the virtualenv
package installed, before commands that require the Python virtualenv
package to be installed will work (e.g. to create new virtualenvs). It's
simple enough to do &lt;code&gt;workon py3venv&lt;/code&gt; and then e.g. &lt;code&gt;mkvirtualenv
virtualenv_name&lt;/code&gt; when you want to create one. However, &lt;code&gt;workon&lt;/code&gt; to
switch virtualenvs should always work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="limitations-with-this-clean-solution"&gt;Limitations with this clean solution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works pretty well, but:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bootstrap environments are the ones you base your other
   virtualenvs on.  If, for some reason, you suddenly need some system
   site package installed for some particular Python package, then
   you'll need to create a new bootstrap virtualenv first, with the
   &lt;code&gt;--system-site-packages&lt;/code&gt; option. (Even if you've already got a
   "system site packages" virtualenv, if you subsequently updated the
   system packages and want a virtualenv to reflect this, you'll have to
   go back to the bootstrapping stage.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll likely need to recreate the bootstrap environments in addition
   to any actual in-use virtualenvs if you want to move to a new Python
   version. I've read in places things that suggest the Python binary is
   a symlink to the system one; on my current virtualenvs, there are
   only symlinks to the local virtualenv copy of the python binary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fixing-virtualenvwrapper-slowing-terminal-startup"&gt;Fixing virtualenvwrapper slowing terminal startup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;virtualenvwrapper does slightly delay bash starting up. On
investigation, this is principally due to virtualenvwrapper.sh itself,
not the activate/deactivate step. You can check this by running &lt;code&gt;time&lt;/code&gt;
on each of the commands, &lt;code&gt;source bin/activate&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;deactivate&lt;/code&gt; are
basically instant, whereas this script slows things down considerably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ &lt;span class="nb"&gt;time&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;source&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.virtualenvs/virtualenvwrapper/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh

real    0m0.304s
user    0m0.248s
sys     0m0.032s
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A 0.3 s delay isn't particularly long. But, for me, it makes bash feel
slightly less snappy on opening a new terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve this, you can use the &lt;a href="https://virtualenvwrapper.readthedocs.io/en/latest/install.html#lazy-loading"&gt;"lazy
loading"&lt;/a&gt;
script provided with virtualenvwrapper. For my setup, this means I would
need to hack that lazy loading script to add the activate and deactivate
command there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried this and it did work. But, it didn't seem like a good solution.
In part, it just felt hacky and, more importantly, these commands would
be removed if you upgrade virtualenvwrapper, breaking it until you again
hacked the script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, my preferred option to work around the slightly slow loading
was to create another script that I can &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; whenever wanting to
work with Python virtualenvs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ch"&gt;#!/bin/sh -e&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;WORKON_HOME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.virtualenvs
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;PROJECT_HOME&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.local/src
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;source&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.virtualenvs/venvwrapper/bin/activate
&lt;span class="nb"&gt;source&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.virtualenvs/venvwrapper/bin/virtualenvwrapper.sh
deactivate
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is less direct. You can't just directly access virtualenvs.
Insteaad, you must source this script first so that you can then
&lt;code&gt;workon&lt;/code&gt; a virtualenv to &lt;code&gt;workon&lt;/code&gt;. However, it keeps the clean install
we have made, doesn't slow bash from loading at all, and isn't a hack of
the existing virtualenvwrapper. Provided we keep it installed in the
same place, it'll work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="keeping-clean"&gt;Keeping clean&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the few drawbacks, I do like the idea of this approach overall.
You don't even need to install any Python packages, even as a user, into
Python outside of a virtualenv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind if you're intent on being particularly rigorous in keeping
your system Python clean: installing software that is built on Python
via your package manager (e.g. apt) may well end up pulling in the
package manager's version of dependencies that the software may use. A
way around this is to install whatever software you want to use in a
virtualenv instead manually, although this may be awkward if that
software uses system packages.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Linux"></category><category term="Ubuntu"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="pip"></category><category term="virtualenv"></category><category term="virtualenvwrapper"></category></entry><entry><title>The Novelist: a haunting experience</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/the-novelist-a-haunting-experience" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-12-24T19:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-24T19:59:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2016-12-24:posts/the-novelist-a-haunting-experience</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Despite "game" being in the official site's domain name, I think
recommending &lt;a href="http://www.thenovelistgame.com/"&gt;The Novelist&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;em&gt;a game&lt;/em&gt;
would be difficult. There are lots of games whose gameplay I don't get
on with which others adore, but the gameplay here seems a bit too simple
to be enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're confined to a single, small environment throughout and you carry
out the same hide and seek game for the entire one or two hours the game
lasts: hiding from the occupants, and seeking clues. It's a rudimentary
stealth game, and there are games that do this much more successfully if
that's what you're looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core gameplay itself isn't perhaps the point though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In The Novelist, a family are on a summer retreat, staying in a slightly
unusual house. You're some ghostly presence that's confined to the walls
of the house, and able to observe the family, read clues that are
scattered around and even characters' memories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're not entirely free to roam around. With the stealth gameplay
option enabled, the family can spot you, and you need to keep hiding out
of sight. As I mentioned, this didn't engage me at all — there's little
challenge — and I quickly turned it off having played through the first
couple of chapters with it enabled,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; instead opting to explore
freely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What you quickly learn is that there are ongoing struggles over the
summer: the titular novelist wants to focus heavily on writing his
novel, his partner wishes him to spend time with the family and wants to
try and get back into painting, while their son is isolated and
struggling at school. At various points over the summer, there is some
way for the novelist to make one of the family happier, albeit at the
expense of the others. As the player, you take on the role of decision
maker and see what happens following that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the fundamentals of The Novelist are based on choices alone, you
might argue that it could be equally served by text. What then does the
scenario add? Wandering around and exploring for clues adds a pacing to
the decision making process. Instead of making a snap decision, it gives
time to reflect on clues you've already discovered. You're also confined
to the small, slightly claustrophobic domestic setting the entire time;
like the ghost restricted to the house, the novelist and his family are
also trapped along certain paths by their choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Novelist could be compared to
&lt;a href="http://hcsoftware.sourceforge.net/passage/"&gt;Passage&lt;/a&gt; as they deal with
similar themes. I don't recall being as affected by Passage. Maybe
because I'm almost a decade older since I played Passage, or maybe
because you have a greater involvement in the characters' lives, a
couple of hours rather than a couple of minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decisions here certainly do feel like they have consequence. Choices you
make can be a big influence on where life takes the novelist and those
around him. Stated like that, that's an obvious conclusion to take away
from the game: you may face sometimes difficult decisions where there
are one of several mutually exclusive outcomes that you must choose
from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many games feature decisions to be made by the player, but often fail in
making the decisions feel consequential. All too often, they reduce to a
simple choice of whether the player's character will appear on Santa's
nice or naughty list.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It can also be easy to reverse these decisions
too. In some games, inflicting retrograde amnesia on every non-player
character in town is sometimes possible by, say, donating enough money
(thanks Fallout 3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly these types of difficult choices do arise in the real world.
However, one thing perhaps missing here is that many choices are the
result of more casual decisions made over longer periods of time. Do I
go out and do something different, or stay in and save money? Do I spend
more time on this hobby or that? Should I be spending more time with
friends and family, or work harder on personal projects? Over time,
where you set the balance on those choices can end up cementing into
concrete consequences. But that kind of subtlety might be more
challenging to bring out in a short game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Playing The Novelist did bring to mind this
&lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/dec/22/why-time-management-is-ruining-our-lives"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;
which I recently read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which paths will you pursue, and which will you abandon? Which
relationships will you prioritise, during your shockingly limited
lifespan, and who will you resign yourself to disappointing? What
matters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tacitly nodding in agreement to printed words is one thing. Experiencing
that through role playing a section of someone else's life in a heavily
time compressed form is another. That's what The Novelist does so well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other reason for turning it off was to minimise my time in the
game. First person games sometimes induce nausea in me, and this was no
exception. Often, increasing the field of view helps, but unfortunately
there's no option to do so here. It points to the game's strength, and
perhaps its brevity, that I stuck with it.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, it's Christmas Eve, so there's got to be some concession to
that here.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="game"></category><category term="review"></category></entry></feed>