<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>stevenmaude.co.uk</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/</id><updated>2018-05-20T17:24:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Solve your problem with sloppy Python</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/solve-your-problem-with-sloppy-python" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-20T17:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-20T17:24:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2018-05-20:posts/solve-your-problem-with-sloppy-python</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="pycon-2018-a-quick-note"&gt;PyCon 2018: A quick note&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As PyCon 2018 happened last week, I've been watching a few talks. It's
sometimes difficult to keep up with changes to technology if you're not
paying constant attention. These kinds of talks are a useful way of
trying to catch up a little. With that in mind, I'm writing up summaries
of a few talks here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="solve-your-problem-with-sloppy-python"&gt;Solve your problem with sloppy Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talk is available to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jd8ulMb6_ls"&gt;watch
here&lt;/a&gt;, and an easy watch.
This was a pragmatic and enjoyable talk that would be easy for beginners
in Python to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a nice contrast from other programming talks too. Often,
presenters, quite reasonably, focus on telling or teaching an audience
what they believe to be best practice on a topic. Concentrating on a
more practical side made for a light and refreshing approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="code-being-discussed-is-for-personal-automation"&gt;Code being discussed is for personal automation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing code to solve your problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not writing code in a professional context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These are throwaway scripts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You're the only person writing it and likely to see it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="rules"&gt;Rules&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fail early and noisily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use Python instead of shell scripts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have fun!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id="guidelines"&gt;Guidelines&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use latest Python version to take advantage of new features.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Try automating even more, push as far as you can go, but may have some
  human intervention too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These projects are an excuse to try or learn new libraries/technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter if the code's hacky; you may not bother with tests.
Quick and dirty code to get a job done. A couple of examples of this
from the renaming files problem in the talk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; to generate a list of filenames in Python; add triple
  quotes around string, &lt;code&gt;strip()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;split()&lt;/code&gt; on newlines gives a
  list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using exceptions lists in renaming files (e.g. to add apostrophes to
  words), run through each check for each filename. Most won't trigger,
  so you're doing lots of unnecessary checks, and could refine that, but
  performance unlikely to be an issue for these kinds of tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cutting corners is OK in this context, if it gets the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="example-uses"&gt;Example uses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renaming files. A general tip for file renaming tasks — in this case,
  downloaded radio shows — back these up via creating hard links with
  the same filenames in a backup directory. That way you can always
  revert to the original names, without having to backup the files.
  Could use Python's &lt;code&gt;os.link()&lt;/code&gt; but also possible via a simple shell
  loop: &lt;code&gt;mkdir backup &amp;amp;&amp;amp; for a in * ; do ln $a backup/$a ; done&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provisioning new machines, e.g. running &lt;code&gt;apt install&lt;/code&gt; and configuring
  programs, e.g. copying license keys.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tidying audio files, creating playlists etc.; possibly with human
  intervention here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ripping CDs, using simple metadata format that can be parsed easily.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="a-final-note"&gt;A final note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes Python was used to call out to the shell. &lt;code&gt;subprocess.run(s,
  check=True, shell=True)&lt;/code&gt; is better than &lt;code&gt;os.system()&lt;/code&gt; because
  &lt;code&gt;os.system()&lt;/code&gt; does not fail noisily, but &lt;code&gt;subprocess.run()&lt;/code&gt; does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="a-thought"&gt;A thought&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that didn't get asked in the Q&amp;amp;A at the end: how should you
estimate whether the automation is actually costing you time? xkcd
has covered this well in these &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/1205/"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/1319/"&gt;comics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cases, it can be reasonably predicted that, if the process is
either time consuming or will be repeated often, it's worthwhile to
spend the time to write code as a solution to the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, the "Rogue's Gallery" radio show renaming given as the main example
presumably took a few minutes to write, find the exceptions (by hand)
and verify (probably also by hand) the code is doing what it should.
There are only actually a few shows to rename, and these themselves
could be done by hand, as a one-off task.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="PyCon"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>Upgrading Raspbian and rc.local failures</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/upgrading-raspbian-and-rclocal-failures" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-10T20:13:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-10T20:13:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-12-10:posts/upgrading-raspbian-and-rclocal-failures</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="a-raspberry-pi-as-a-wireless-bridge-for-old-hardware"&gt;A Raspberry Pi as a wireless bridge for old hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is something I did a couple of months back, but figure it's worth
documenting, to maybe help anyone with a similar problem search for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One use for my Raspberry Pi is as a wireless bridge, and this is mainly
for a now ancient Xbox 360. Yes, the one without built-in wifi, it just
has an Ethernet port for networking; not much good when your router is
nowhere near a TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, and as is often customary when solving technology problems,
I used &lt;a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/64353/32125"&gt;instructions that I cobbled
together&lt;/a&gt; from various
places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd been slack on upgrading my Raspberry Pi's Raspbian. It was working
perfectly fine for what it was doing, so there was no immediate need to
touch it. Because of this, it has languished on a distribution based on
the now aging Debian Wheezy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More recently, with the &lt;a href="https://www.ncsc.gov.uk/krack"&gt;recent WPA2
exploit&lt;/a&gt; in October, and the then lack of
any as-yet patch even for Debian Wheezy (which has since been patched,
not sure about Raspbian itself), I thought I should finally upgrade, so
the Pi was patched against this and any other future security issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't particularly want to go to the trouble of doing a fresh
install, so I tried an in-place operating system upgrade, deciding that
the worst that could happen is the upgrade fails and I'd have to do a
fresh install anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-upgrade-process"&gt;The upgrade process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually upgraded in two stages. First from Wheezy to Jessie, and then
I figured if that went OK, I could try upgrading again, from Jessie to
Stretch too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upgrading the distribution actually worked well. With my Raspbian Wheezy
install, I upgraded to Jessie as described on the &lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/forums/viewtopic.php?f=66&amp;amp;t=121880"&gt;Raspberry Pi
forum&lt;/a&gt;.
Everything seemed to work, including the Xbox's internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I was feeling brave, I decided to upgrade again. However, I didn't
feel so brave that I would do that without first backing up the working
system, so I &lt;a href="https://raspberrypi.stackexchange.com/a/312/12370"&gt;backed up the SD card with
&lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to a gzipped
image in case something went wrong and I could recover a working system
quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I upgraded from Jessie to Stretch. This is the same process as for
Wheezy to Jessie, just with &lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/blog/raspbian-stretch/"&gt;different repository sources
used&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, the upgrade worked fine, the Pi booted up, and I could
connect to it wirelessly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="a-stretch-too-far"&gt;A stretch too far&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, the Xbox's internet connection no longer worked. Checking the Pi, I
spotted what looked like error messages appearing at boot time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first problem is checking the boot log messages that quickly
disappear from the screen. Since Debian now uses systemd, you need &lt;code&gt;sudo
systemctl&lt;/code&gt; to review those messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I spotted there is that there was an error that indicated that
commands I had in &lt;code&gt;rc.local&lt;/code&gt; were not running correctly. As mentioned,
in my &lt;a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/64353/32125"&gt;description of my Xbox and Pi
configuration&lt;/a&gt;, I was
using &lt;code&gt;rc.local&lt;/code&gt; to run the commands on boot that ensured the bridge
worked, instead of having to run anything by hand every boot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That seemed strange. More so when running the script by hand caused it
to work as normal, which allowed the Xbox to once again connect to the
internet as it did on Raspbian Jessie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did this script fail on boot via &lt;code&gt;rc.local&lt;/code&gt;? As &lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/forums/viewtopic.php?f=66&amp;amp;t=122207"&gt;mentioned on the
Raspberry Pi
forums&lt;/a&gt;,
the difference presumably is that the Pi's networking isn't configured
at the time of the script trying to run. Trying to then change this
configuration when it's not ready will then fail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there are no guarantees about when &lt;code&gt;rc.local&lt;/code&gt; is run. If you have
dependencies on other things, the moral of this longish story is that
you should create a systemd service and have systemd launch it after
everything else; this fixed the problem and everything finally was
working again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="configuration"&gt;Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For reference, here's what I have configured:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;wireless_bridge.sh&lt;/code&gt; is saved in &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/sbin&lt;/code&gt;, with 755 file
permissions, root as owner and group, and contains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ch"&gt;#!/bin/sh -e&lt;/span&gt;
/usr/sbin/ifplugd eth0 --kill
/sbin/sysctl -w net.ipv4.ip_forward&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
/sbin/ifconfig eth0 &lt;span class="m"&gt;192&lt;/span&gt;.168.1.1
/sbin/iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o wlan0 -s &lt;span class="m"&gt;192&lt;/span&gt;.168.1.0/24 -j MASQUERADE
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;wireless-bridge.service&lt;/code&gt; is saved in &lt;code&gt;/etc/systemd/system&lt;/code&gt;, with 644
file permissions, root as owner and group, and contains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;[Unit]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;Description&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;Wireless Bridge Service&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;After&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;multi-user.target&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;[Service]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;Type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;idle&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;ExecStart&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;/usr/local/sbin/wireless_bridge.sh&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;[Install]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;WantedBy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;multi-user.target&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You could possibly change &lt;code&gt;multi-user.target&lt;/code&gt; to one of systemd's
&lt;a href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/systemd/NetworkTarget/"&gt;network
targets&lt;/a&gt;,
but I didn't bother testing this out, as the configuration above just
seemed to work (with, I suppose, the possible cost of the bridged
connection not being available until slightly later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have the Xbox network settings as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IP address: 192.168.1.2&lt;br /&gt;
Subnet mask: 255.255.255.0&lt;br /&gt;
Gateway: 192.168.1.1  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the primary DNS server set to my router's IP address.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Raspberry Pi"></category><category term="Raspbian"></category><category term="Linux"></category></entry><entry><title>A digital piano buyers' guide for learners</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/a-digital-piano-buyers-guide-for-learners" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-10-22T17:10:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-22T17:10:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-10-22:posts/a-digital-piano-buyers-guide-for-learners</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I've &lt;a href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/do-you-even-liszt-five-months-of-learning-piano"&gt;documented earlier
here&lt;/a&gt;, I've been
taking piano lessons since the start of this year. There I also
mentioned I'd been using a keyboard to learn. Since then, I've switched
to a second-hand digital piano for practising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I discovered is that a keyboard with velocity sensitive keys (i.e.
capable of producing different key volumes depending on how you play) is
fine when starting out. Any music you play at first will be simple, but
needing to play notes at varying volumes is likely something you'll be
doing almost from the start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're planning on trying out piano lessons, if you have such a
keyboard already or can borrow one for a few months, that's a sensible
initial step.  Don't let not having a piano right now put you off
starting learning now: it's a substantial commitment to get one. It's
probably sensible to ensure that you're likely to stick with learning
first, before plunging in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, a few months on, once you've made a little progress, the
inadequacies of using a keyboard as a substitute for a piano soon become
apparent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One big problem is that the feel of hitting the keys is much different,
which is difficult to get used to when playing on a real grand piano for
lessons. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another is that, like the keyboard I used, many keyboards only have 61
keys, not the 88 that standard pianos have. This can be confusing, and
can hamper you relatively early on. Even on the simple pieces I was
learning, there were occasional cases where you'd just have to miss or
mime playing a note out, because it didn't exist on the keyboard. The
difference in the number of keys also made orienting myself difficult
when sat at the real piano for lessons, and I'd get "surprised" by the
presence of the extra keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point, it felt like that the keyboard was hindering my progress,
and a natural juncture to replace it in my practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-a-digital-piano"&gt;Why a digital piano?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're not too aware of digital pianos, and I wasn't before I started
looking into this, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_piano"&gt;Wikipedia is a good starting
point&lt;/a&gt;. There, we learn,
digital pianos are really high-end keyboards that are designed to be
good facsimiles of real pianos, in both sound and feel of how it plays.
(I'd add that sometimes, though not always, they are designed to mimic
the look of a real piano too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That explains why you might want a digital piano over a keyboard. But
why not just get a traditional acoustic piano? Especially when looking
around, you can likely find pianos on offer for the literal giveaway
price of £0, providing you can collect. Reading on, the Wikipedia entry
explains good reasons for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acoustic pianos weigh a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;. It's a considerable task to get one of
  these to where you live, especially without damage to the instrument.
  Likewise, if you need to move for whatever reason, you face this
  problem again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, acoustic pianos can take up a lot of room. Some digital
  pianos can do too (you can even get digital grand pianos, for reasons
  that aren't that clear to me), but there are digital pianos available
  that are just the keyboard, and are relatively easy to move. For
  example, Yamaha's current low end keyboard-like models weigh a little
  bit more than 10 kg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acoustic pianos will also need tuning. That's an ongoing cost and one
  that's also fairly pricey. Digital pianos could also require repair
  too, although not likely with the regular frequency that an acoustic
  would need tuning (pardon the pun).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One downside with digital pianos is that you're somewhat reliant on
having local availability of technicians who specialise on those
models, and the parts being available to repair the piano; reasons
why you might want to opt for a well-known brand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost all (or maybe even all) modern digital pianos, and even lots of
  older ones, will have some means to use it as a MIDI keyboard. A
  digital piano in a given price range likely has fewer voices (i.e.
  types of sound it can play, e.g. piano, organ, strings) than a
  comparably priced keyboard, but you can always hook it up to a
  computer and use it to control whatever instruments you have available
  there in a digital audio workstation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digital pianos have headphone outputs, so that you can practice
  quietly. This is not usually an option on acoustic pianos. I say
  usually, because you can get hybrid acoustic-digital pianos that allow
  switching between acoustic and digital modes, though these are very
  expensive and still suffer from the problems of tuning, size and
  weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hybrids aside, the downsides with digital pianos are that the feel and
sound is a simulation of a real piano. Even with today's technology,
they're never going to be quite as authentic as the real thing. But
especially when still a beginner, a decent digital piano is probably
more than sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-to-look-for"&gt;What to look for&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's daunting spending a considerable amount on a piano, if you still
feel like you don't know what makes for a good instrument. From reading
around, there are some general considerations you can think about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;size and cabinet; as I mentioned above, digital pianos come in
  different sizes. If you're pushed for space, then you might have to go
  for one of the keyboard-like pianos. There are also cosmetic choices
  to make; if a piano comes built-in to a cabinet, do you like the
  appearance and colour of it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pedals; acoustic pianos usually have three pedals. I think most
  electric pianos usually have three too, though lower end models might
  only have two. Three, then, really is &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YZoYEr6NdmE"&gt;the magic
  number&lt;/a&gt;, so you may want
  to go for a model with the pedals you'd expect on a acoustic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;voices; this is maybe less important. The main thing for learning here
  is that the piano sounds realistic. Having other sounds to use is a
  nice bonus, but not essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;polyphony; this is the number of notes that can &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; simultaneously
  without earlier played notes that are still sounding just being
  dropped. Current low end models may have 64 note polyphony, whereas
  better models will have 128, 192 or even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not quite as simple as the number of notes you &lt;em&gt;play&lt;/em&gt;
simultaneously, since, for example, using multiple voices (e.g.
piano and strings) at once, or using the sustain pedal to prolong
the sound of non-held notes will eat into this note "budget". More
is better, especially if using multiple voices simultaneously. But
given that 64 note polyphony seemed to be a satisfactory standard in
the past, anything above that is likely very good for a beginner
piano.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;headphone noise; after I had an experience with a keyboard's headphone
  output being &lt;a href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/the-buzz-and-hum-of-learning-a-new-instrument"&gt;distractingly
  noisy&lt;/a&gt;,
  I knew I should check this on any piano I bought.  Just remember to
  take the pair of headphones you use with you when looking at a piano
  to test this. Trying to concentrate with a distracting buzz in your
  ears isn't a great feature to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the feel and action of the keyboard; I can appreciate that higher end
  pianos aim to more realistically replicate the feel of a real piano.
  For instance, the weights of the keys, and the texture. And if you've
  experience of several pianos, this is probably easy to discern. For
  me, having played on one acoustic piano, this was far less easy for me
  to know what was good and bad. More expensive digital pianos tend to
  use different hardware than cheaper variants, whether you can tell
  much of a difference as a beginner is difficult for me to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;branding; common brands are those you might expect, the likes of
  Roland, Korg and Yamaha. There are also no-name branded pianos
  available, but I suspect the quality of these can vary wildly. I'm not
  always one to go for big name brands, but I think in cases like this,
  where there's likely much expertise gone into the research and
  development, it's probably easy to cut corners and end up that might
  look the part, but is in fact considerably inferior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="and-with-used-pianos"&gt;And with used pianos?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My teacher's advice was to stick to a low budget and pick up a used
model (given that it would be almost certainly an improvement on the
keyboard I was using), rather than a brand new, but low end model. When
I was looking at the market, digital pianos seemed relatively mature.
The manufacturers continue to churn out regular updates to their product
lines, but, much like mobile phones now, it doesn't seem that there are
any real technological revolutions that have happened over the past
couple of years. Buying used seems like a good way to get more for your
money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When buying used, the condition of the instrument is important. Spares
may be few and far between and expensive if anything does break. That's
another reason not to maybe spend a huge amount on old kit: the repair
costs may also be very expensive or repair may rely on you getting hold
of a second broken model for spares. (This also is another reason why
no-name digital pianos may not be a good investment, if there are no
parts available or indeed anyone who knows how to repair those models.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bearing all that in mind, the most I wanted to spend was the cost of the
current low end Casio and Yamaha electric pianos, and I didn't really
want something more than about a decade old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="buying-a-used-piano"&gt;Buying a used piano&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, after a week or two of searching on eBay and Gumtree — if
you're in the US, Craigslist is probably a good substitute for Gumtree —
I managed to find a Yamaha Clavinova that seemed ideal. It was within
driving distance to collect, seemed reasonably priced, was in my budget,
and claimed to be in good condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When looking around, I found that used digital pianos were generally
claimed to be well cared for. My hunch is this is because these are
reasonably expensive bits of kit new and therefore buyers want to look
after them. Another reason is that a lot of sellers are getting rid of
them because the piano is no longer in use, either because they have
bought a newer instrument or have given up learning. Not in use means
not becoming worn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was much the case for the piano I ended up buying. The seller never
really took to it, was looking to replace it with a synthesizer and so
it looked almost brand new. There was plastic wrapping still on the
pedals, hardly a visible scratch on the cabinet, all the manuals were
present, and even a catalogue of various Clavinova models that the
original purchaser had been given while they were originally deciding
which one to buy. All a good portent for the piano being treated well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="some-other-tips-on-buying-used"&gt;Some other tips on buying used&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you try as much as possible before handing over cash. Do all
  of the buttons work? Does every key plays smoothly? As mentioned
  above, I took my own headphones to test the headphone output too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't be afraid to haggle a little. Prices of pianos vary a lot as
  there are lots of different models and often relatively few sellers
  around (although major cities will tend to have more). Unless someone
  has expressly stated the asking price is the final price, even if the
  asking price is reasonably sensible, I don't think there's any harm in
  offering something like 10-15% below to give them room to
  counter-offer, and maybe give you a small discount. Since pianos are
  big, and sellers may well want to get rid of them quickly, if they
  sense a possible sale, they may well be happy to negotiate a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you're clear on what's included for the price. Sometimes
  sellers will sell piano stools or stands separately from the piano
  itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going to a manufacturer's website and getting hold of a PDF copy of the
  manual, if available, is a good way of answering questions you may
  have prior to purchase (e.g. is the MIDI via USB? does the piano need
  drivers for connecting to a PC? are they available?) or finding
  detailed specifications. You can usually find these in the support
  section of a manufacturer's site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if you're intending to ever use your piano as a MIDI
  keyboard, make sure that drivers are available for the piano for your
  operating system from the manufacturer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't be too set on going for a particular model or brand. The market
  depends on what's available in your area, so I'd just stick with a
  budget and features you're not willing to compromise on. Most sellers
  want you to arrange collection, which likely means you travelling
  there to collect in person (unless you pay someone to move it, which
  will probably cost you a fair bit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="three-months-on"&gt;Three months on&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I went with the first Clavinova I looked at, and have been
very happy with it since. While a little unusual to switch from the
previous keyboard initially, it didn't take that long to adjust. Since
then, it has made a noticeable difference in my confidence going into
piano lessons and being sat at an acoustic grand piano. It now feels
much more a natural transition to go from playing at home to playing in
lessons.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="piano"></category></entry><entry><title>Full of heart: an Undertale review</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/full-of-heart-an-undertale-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-20T15:47:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-20T15:47:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-08-20:posts/full-of-heart-an-undertale-review</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="playing-undertale-fills-you-with-determination"&gt;Playing Undertale fills you with determination&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undertale's almost two years old. Yet I only bothered to play it this
year. If you have a PS4 and never got it on PC, it was released this
week. While the PC version will have been much cheaper while on sale,
and runs on just about any hardware, if you really must play it on a
console, now you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why didn't I bother sooner? Hype is one reason. When it's that vocal —
and with Undertale, it's near deafening — I always tend to do as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%27t_Believe_the_Hype"&gt;Public
Enemy
instructed&lt;/a&gt;.
The other is its resemblance to 16-bit Japanese RPGs (JRPGs). While I
appreciate those games are much loved, I've never really shared that
affection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I did actually get round to Undertale on PC, it happened to be on
sale. I figured it was cheap enough to see if they hype was warranted
and I wanted an escapist diversion from real world events. It seemed as
good a game to try out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without spoiling too much, you're a human that finds yourself fallen
down a mountain, and lost somewhere in the underground world of
monsters. The rest of the game sees you journeying through to try and
find some route home. Mostly this is done by exploration, although there
are a few puzzles dotted along the way that need solving before you can
progress, and monsters that you can fight. So much, so familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's a wonderful game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those aspects of JRPGs that I never got on with are kept to a minimum.
There's a minimum of backtracking. The random battles, a staple of that
genre, that prevent you from walking more than a couple of footsteps —
because &lt;em&gt;swoosh swoosh swoosh&lt;/em&gt; TWO SLIGHTLY SURLY ENEMIES IN MATCHING
OUTFITS APPEAR, and &lt;em&gt;cue battle music&lt;/em&gt; — are thankfully omitted too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you actually battle, the system is novel: a mixture of strategy and
shmup bullet dodging. Battles can even be avoided, and these options are
left open to the player to decide. Both in and out of battle mode, the
dialogue is predominantly witty and charming, and avoiding lazy
territory, instead of prolonged and awkwardly translated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing that the game does well is, without any spoilers, is
continually confronting you and challenging your expectations of the
situations you're placed in, at times akin to what something like The
Stanley Parable does in trying to break the fourth wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without playing and without spoiling it, it's hard to convey that
without being anything other than handwavingly effusive. Characters and
combatants that only appear briefly don't just feel like they've been
arbitrarily placed there, but like they have a real back story, even if
that's not ever entirely revealed. And while the game has this rich
assortment of characters, it also has character itself, full of soul and
heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="fantastic-mr-fox"&gt;Fantastic Mr. Fox&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undertale's singular cohesion is likely because it was largely the
product of one person's imagination, Toby Fox. And while its graphics
are simple, but functional, it is a polished game, backed by an
incredibly &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SxNcKXjfaQo"&gt;strong
soundtrack&lt;/a&gt; also composed
by the developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been fairly lucky that the few games that I've played through in
recent years have been particularly good choices for one reason or
another. Undertale's another, and one of the more memorable. It
genuinely feels like an experience that would only work as a game, not a
book or film. True, you could describe a similar journey with similar
characters in print or on screen. But it's the act of playing through
and having to make decisions on how you play through that's intrinsic to
how it works and how it makes you feel; that's very different to a more
passive experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where many otherwise good games fail is extending their gameplay through
repetition and tedium, churning out more of the same. Undertale avoids
this, keeping the core game short and sweet, but giving you the
opportunity to play through in a very different play style. I'll
definitely look forward to revisiting that world in a few months.
(That's a really strong compliment from me. I have so little time to
play games these days that there are very few that I'd ever return to
once I've played through.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undertale is the perfect game for a Sunday afternoon where rain is
beating down your windows, a dull Tuesday where you're miserably plagued
with cold, or maybe even a snowy Thursday where you have the luxury of
being snowed in, unable to get to school or work, and are just warming
up with hot chocolate after already having been out to play in the snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's that kind of game.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="game"></category><category term="review"></category></entry><entry><title>Flipping out over swimming turns</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/flipping-out-over-swimming-turns" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-29T12:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-07-29T12:18:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-07-29:posts/flipping-out-over-swimming-turns</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Note that I actually learned how to flip (or tumble) turn a while ago,
drafted this back then and only just got round to posting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="turn-down-for-what"&gt;Turn down for what?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been swimming for probably the best part of twenty years. That is
&lt;em&gt;regularly&lt;/em&gt; over a period of twenty years, not constantly; an hour
usually is enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I didn't gain confidence in the water until much later than I
should have done, I've never had anything much in the way of serious
coaching. I've swum for fitness and, apart from swimming lessons for the
absolute basics, have made pretty much any improvements to my swimming
by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though swimming feels quite natural to me now, this lack of training and
racing means I never had any real incentive to learn how to properly
tumble turn. It always looked really daunting when I saw others doing
them. But I more recently thought that I wanted to have a go at learning
them, and eventually got there. My turns are far from perfect, but the
fact that I have the co-ordination to flip myself over is impressive
enough to me, to be honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's particularly nice is that flip turns are a more fluid way of
turning, than grabbing the side with your hands and pushing off. It
means you can maintain more speed, and just feels smoother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind, I'm hardly a good swimmer. And I'm definitely not a
swimming coach either. But, since I taught myself and can remember it
reasonably well, I thought it was worth documenting how I learned. It
took me a while to figure all this out myself. It's the learning
experience of someone who taught themselves very recently as an adult,
rather than coaches who have a lot more knowledge and experience than
me, but may have less of a memory of how they first learned the skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="turning"&gt;Turning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of videos, such as &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FDM-WuklAqc"&gt;this
tutorial&lt;/a&gt; but, when I was
learning, I found that videos tended to go over the mechanics of the
turn itself, not so much how you go about learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you watch that video, you'll see that for a front crawl flip turn,
all that's really involved is something like a forward roll, albeit in
the water. As you approach the wall, you flip yourself over forwards,
push off the wall with your feet and swim off in the other direction.
Notice that if you just roll over forwards, your body will flip from
face down to face up. So you also have to rotate yourself back to face
down as you push off from the wall. And ideally all this is in a smooth
motion. Simple, eh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many things, once you grasp it, it's easy. But it's difficult to
pick up at first. You're coordinating your body in a way which you may
not have before, along with thinking about keeping on swimming,
breathing and without injuring yourself. Putting all that together is
surprisingly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-do-you-have-to-worry-about"&gt;What do you have to worry about?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="hitting-the-wall"&gt;Hitting the wall&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, this hasn't happened to me yet, not even while learning,
but misjudging your position may lead to unexpected bumps. And the worry
of doing that is an impediment to learning, because you may be
overcautious and hold back too much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, you can actually get quite close, probably about an arm's
length without too much worry. The best way I found to build confidence
is to try from too far out and then progressively get closer to decide
the right distance to turn without colliding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, pools have markers on the floor for swimmers to judge the
distance. If yours doesn't then just find your own marker. Maybe that's
by counting tiles from the side or just by remembering how far in front
you need to be at the point where you should turn. You may not need
these guides once when you're more comfortable with how many strokes you
are from turning, or when your instincts improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a bit of fine tuning with the ideal distance: if you're too
close, you may end up hitting some part of your body against the wall or
at least take measures to awkwardly prevent yourself from colliding.
While if you're too far, you'll either miss the wall completely, or have
to stretch your legs out to reach the wall and get a weak push off as
your legs can't spring you off the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A counterintuitive thing that helped me was sometimes trying this with
breaststroke, &lt;em&gt;not frontcrawl&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This means you're approaching more
slowly, so less worried about hitting the wall. It's also easier to keep
the wall in sight, instead of while you're rotating in frontcrawl.
Related to this, I incorrectly assumed that you need to be going fast to
keep your momentum moving through the turn. Even going slowly, you can
still flip over without too much trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="rolling"&gt;Rolling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the video guides I watched on YouTube also seemed to suggest
flipping yourself over in the water, not even being near the wall, just
from standing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also stops any possibility of your forehead becoming closely
acquainted with the swimming pool wall, but I actually found this quite
difficult when I was learning to turn (though easier now I can actually
turn). This is also useful since you can actually use the same motion to
flip direction even without a wall which can be handy if you're in a
busy lane and want to avoid overtaking a cluster of slower swimmers in
front.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most useful exercise for me was doing forward rolls. If you haven't
done forward rolls in a while (and why would you?), doing a few of those
on dry land as practice helped me get the idea of the required motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="breathing"&gt;Breathing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having water rushing up your nose is not a pleasant feeling that's not
dissimilar to spraying carbonated drinks up there. (It always reminds me
of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irn-Bru"&gt;Irn-Bru&lt;/a&gt;; that drink seemed
to be notorious for sending jets of eye-watering bubbles up my nose.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, it's irritating and distracting, and unfortunately may well
happen almost every time you attempt to do a flip turn. Breathing out
through your nose slightly while flipping stops this, but knowing
exactly when you start needing to breathe out takes some practice,
especially when you're possibly slightly disorientated from flipping. At
the same time, you don't want to breathe out unnecessarily and leave
yourself gasping for breath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, you probably overcompensate and breathe out too much. All
that's need is a gentle and brief air flow while you're turning,
possibly far less than you imagine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(When I first drafted this post, even after a good few months of turning
like this, I was still occasionally getting caught out, and it takes a
few seconds to have the awkward fizzy feeling dissipate. A considerable
time later, this isn't the case now; it's relatively rare that I get the
breathing wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="practice"&gt;Practice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice isn't anything unique to this, but it's probably the most
important thing. You're learning several new physical skills and having
to employ them all seamlessly to get the result you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I spent a few minutes of several swim sessions over several
weeks to start getting a feel for turning. This was a little
demoralising at times, especially as failing means you're often getting
nowhere, metaphorically and literally (I'd often end up stuck at the
side of the pool, bursting up for air, to get the water out of my nose.)
What you have to remember is that getting things horribly wrong is a key
part of learning physical skills. Eventually, you condition yourself to
not do the Wrong Things, and you slowly improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slowly, the motion that was needed to get myself round started to become
apparent. After that, I spent a couple of sessions where I was focusing
pretty much exclusively working on this only, swimming from end to end,
but not particularly exercising hard and just concentrating on the turns
themselves. Even then, I kept getting worried that I'd forget what I'd
learned, so I ensured that I attempted to turn on just about every
length I was swimming for a while after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be frustrating at first, but when it does click, then you'll be
able to turn every time you want to, rather than making a mess of it.
After that, you can spend a lot more time refining aspects of it,
optimising where you start turning from, trying to push off to get the
most distance from the wall, and timing your breathing so you can stay
underwater without it being uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite me finding it tricky to learn, I'd say it's well worth the
effort, even if you're swimming just for fitness. Tumble turns give you
another way of mixing up your training, can help constant lengths flow
together more seamlessly, and aid you maintaining your speed when
swimming in shorter length pools. If you need any more convincing, just
compare flip turning swimmers to those not when you're at the pool;
you'll see it makes for a considerable drop in lap times once you get it
right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're racing breaststroke, then you don't actually flip turn,
  but touch the wall with both hands, and then push back off the
  wall with your feet, but using breaststroke is still a nice way
  to learn.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="swimming"></category></entry><entry><title>Rinse FM's SoundCloud account takedown</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/rinse-fms-soundcloud-account-takedown" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-18T21:56:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-07-18T21:56:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-07-15:posts/rinse-fms-soundcloud-account-takedown</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="admonition article-edit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit 2017-07-18: SoundCloud have now restored &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/geeneus/status/887050524067061760"&gt;Rinse FM's
account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the points below still stand in relation to hosting
content under online accounts that have the potential for
copyright takedowns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="and-its-shutdown"&gt;And it's shutdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many dance music lovers, the taking down of Rinse FM's SoundCloud
profile yesterday was a sad event. Along with their account, a huge
archive of shows they hosted on SoundCloud have all gone due to
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/geeneus/status/885984092449366021"&gt;copyright
infringement&lt;/a&gt;
complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's difficult to overstate Rinse's influence in dance music. The
station was heavily instrumental in pushing grime, and later dubstep in
the UK, and contributing to the massive spread of these genres outside
of these shores. While much of the UK radio broadcast frequency space is
pumped full of the same cloying pop music being endlessly
recirculated,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Rinse FM is a refreshing breath of fresh air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rinse FM started life as a pirate station, &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2012/sep/30/rinse-fm-former-pirate-station-18-birthday"&gt;broadcasting illicitly via
aerials perched on tower block
rooftops&lt;/a&gt;,
but more recently acquired a legal license. Peculiar then that they are
now legitimate under the traditional broadcasting regulations, but don't
have the same freedoms when distributing those same broadcasts via the
internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately Rinse has an established physical presence as an FM station
and a fanbase built long before the internet became popular for
distributing music. Rinse also has a sizable following on other social
networks, allowing them to communicate what's going on, and, probably as
important, a web site that lets them continue to put out their shows
uninterrupted, via live streaming and podcasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without seeing their SoundCloud playback statistics or their web
analytics before and after this change, it's difficult to know how much
of an impact that has on the number of people listening to Rinse FM
online. But, given the news of SoundCloud's redundancies this week, it
may well be that &lt;em&gt;everyone's&lt;/em&gt; profiles are &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/07/12/soundshroud/"&gt;getting deleted from
SoundCloud sometime
soon&lt;/a&gt; like it or not.
Perhaps any impact on Rinse's future prospects may well be minimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, such an account deletion could be disastrous for the progress of a
smaller project, say a independent producer, or a niche podcast, who are
maybe start to make waves. All of a sudden their content evaporates
(easy to replace somewhere else) together with all of their following on
that site (perhaps more difficult to rebuild).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-can-we-take-away-from-this-takedown"&gt;What can we take away from this takedown?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="it-seems-a-backwards-step-for-the-music-industry"&gt;It seems a backwards step for the music industry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at &lt;a href="http://rinse.fm/podcasts/"&gt;the podcast&lt;/a&gt; page and, in any
given week, you'll see a diverse range of artists hosting shows, and
invariably a top line up. Today, you have a house legend, Masters At
Work's Kenny Dope, on only a couple of hours after alternative
electronic producer, &lt;a href="https://forestswords.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Forest
Swords&lt;/a&gt;. Whether old hands or not,
the hosts are often influential taste makers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of that, Rinse's audience no doubt overlaps with who the music
industry are targeting: young and early adopters of new music. Why then
does someone, somewhere presumably think it's a smart move to hinder
that?  These listeners likely form the dedicated audience that same
industry is crying out for: those that will go out and track down music,
share it with their friends, go to shows to see acts playing out, or
even become the next big DJs or producers of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another thing: many of Rinse's shows are in a mix format. That's
because mixes are a natural way of presenting modern dance music. Maybe
I'm naive as to the machinations of the music industry, but both as a
listener, and as a (mediocre) DJ, it's difficult to see the logic behind
&lt;a href="http://djtechtools.com/2017/06/15/drake-hate-dj-mixes-soundcloud-copyright-strikes-vs-dj-mixes/"&gt;taking down DJ mixes at
all&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as creative expression and entertainment in their own right,
mixes can act as promotional tools. The featuring of tracks in mixes may
well encourage listeners to buy the tracks, or at least to head over to
a streaming service to hear it uninterrupted. Keep in mind that a track
in a mix isn't usually a substitute for hearing the track end-to-end:
they're different contexts. And DJs listening in may well decide to
shell out for the full track to play in their own sets. When there's so
much music, past and present competing for attention today, you'd think
that &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; that might nudge listeners to a given label's artists
would be welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="where-to-host-projects"&gt;Where to host projects?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you're starting with a project that you're serious about and you
want it to reach the audience you're aiming for, what do you do? What
this situation tells me is that it's vital to be cultivating a following
in multiple places. That way you're not back to square one should your
profile on a single site be taken down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I have an idea for a music-related project I'm intending to
put together. To keep things simple starting out, I'd considered just
having the project exist as a SoundCloud account, instead of creating a
blog to go with it. After this week with the Rinse FM takedown, coupled
with the possibility of SoundCloud disappearing, my thinking has shifted
entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owners of accounts on online services, as I've written before,&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; have
little real ownership of what happens with those accounts. If the site's
owners or moderators don't like what you're doing for whatever reason,
you're gone. Someone might complain about what you're doing on the
service, just as happened to Rinse FM, and likewise you're gone. For
what I'm planning, it's very unlikely that copyright claims would be an
issue, but the potential of having your account taken down for some
other reason, and perhaps outside your control, still stands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, radio stations like Rinse and DJs could try their luck on
Mixcloud or other alternative sites, but there's nothing to say that the
same copyright issues might occur there in future, even if those sites
are relatively permissive now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's difficult. The big services are those where the users are. Creators
are often tied to publishing using those services if they want to get
people interested, as those services are where people are browsing,
searching and listening. But, over-reliance on a particular service
means that if it fails you, either destroying your account on a whim, or
because the site itself is shutdown, the knock-on impact for getting
visibility (or audibility) for creative projects can be a big blow.
Hedging your bets seems the only viable solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong. I'm very much not against pop music. The
  "same" in that sentence is an important qualifier of why I
  dislike those stations so, so much. It's the lack of individuality
  and the repetition that gets me. If you flick through the
  commercial pop stations, could you tell them apart?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When there's so much music that I know I'll never have enough time
  to discover and hear, it's such a pity that show producers and
  station bosses are often so unadventurous.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look &lt;a href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/what-happens-when-github-decides-youre-not-a-human"&gt;what happened to my GitHub account last year&lt;/a&gt;,
  for example.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="radio"></category><category term="Rinse FM"></category><category term="SoundCloud"></category></entry><entry><title>Do you even Liszt? Five months of learning piano</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/do-you-even-liszt-five-months-of-learning-piano" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-11T14:06:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-11T14:06:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-06-11:posts/do-you-even-liszt-five-months-of-learning-piano</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="why-learn-now"&gt;Why learn now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other posts on my blog highlight the small theme of me very, very slowly
trying to get better at making music. When you're a novice, it's natural
to ask what's the best way to improve? Some common advice I've found on
music production forums goes like this: focus on develop piano playing
skills first, and less on learning software or production itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that's for two big reasons. An analogy is that being unable to
touch type would be a hindrance for writing and coding. You can still do
these things regardless, but the lack of being able to express yourself
quickly does slow your progress. Likewise with music, yes, you can
painstakingly draw notes in software,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but being able to play a
melody or chord progression means that you can transcribe something in
your head much more quickly and directly, as well as improvise
effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to play also gives you hard fought experience of both picking
up music theory as you learn and seeing it constantly applied. When
playing pieces of music that "work" while seeing how they are made, it's
surprising sometimes just how some melodies can be pleasing, whether in
spite of, or indeed, because of their simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that motivation in mind, I've been taking piano lessons since the
start of this year. And as I've just this week played a very small part
in a concert, albeit a very simple accompaniment, it seemed as good a
point as any to document how I've found this as an adult learner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tuition-or-self-taught"&gt;Tuition or self-taught?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lessons can be expensive for what is a relatively short time with a
teacher, so why would you bother paying? You're doing most of the
learning by yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very true, but lessons have a lot to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes a commitment to sit down and learn something for the next week,
which is very important. Aside from the odd day when I've been ill or
away, I've usually managed to get in at least a daily half-hour practice
session. Having a scheduled lesson with a teacher really does act as a
promise to ensure you keep time aside for practice. At times, I'd have
the idea in my head that I'd not yet got enough done for the next
lesson. That's usually enough motivation for me to sit down and work on
piano. You have a deadline to meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teachers can provide guidance of specific pointers, on technique, on how
to play tricky sections, or on explaining notation. Particularly with
piano, at least to me, it doesn't always seem obvious whether what I'm
doing is "correct" or most efficient. If I was learning in isolation,
things I find difficult could well contribute to me giving up. Knowing I
can go and get advice at the next lesson is a really positive and
powerful resource to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having someone capable of competently observing and listening to you
play, assessing that and pointing out things you're doing wrong (even
when you think you've mastered something) is also a boon. Likewise, this
means you should be encouraged with reasonably good habits, e.g. posture
and finger positioning, instead of getting by for now, and struggling
later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A teacher can also tell you when you've got the most out of learning a
piece. You could spend a long time playing something to near perfection,
but is that practice time most usefully spent doing that? Importantly,
it's not just having that feedback from someone else, but one who has
taught others and knows what's reasonable to expect too. It also, again,
takes this decision out of your hands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removing some of the decision making of learning is another benefit.
Instead of having to figure out what books to get and which pieces to
try next — is this too difficult? too easy? — they can set tasks for
you. Again, a teacher should know what works well for other learners,
and it means you don't have to concern yourself with that at all. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, for me, lessons work best with a two-way involvement. As time
is short, I've found a good strategy is going in with a clear idea of
things I've been struggling with or don't quite understand, to discuss
and work on in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disregarding all those benefits, could you teach yourself? It's not
impossible. There are musicians that have successfully done just that.
But, it requires a lot of discipline and the persistence to battle
through the tricky skills you'll need to learn. The only downside I can
think of taking lessons is their financial cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="starter-books"&gt;Starter books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first book I was using was The Classic Piano Course Book 1 by Carol
Barratt. Beginning from basics, it introduces new ideas throughout every
couple of pages, moving briskly, without being overwhelming. Progress
feels regular and positive. Certainly, except towards the last third or
so of the book, with a little practice each day, it was possible to get
most of the simple pieces to a decent standard in a week or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to tuition versus being self-taught, you could use it for
self-teaching as it is mostly self-explanatory, although at times it's a
light on details. For instance, it provides an exercise on hand
extending and contracting, which, in the absence of helpful pictures, I
had to check with my teacher that I'd understood it correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From completing about three-quarters of that book, I've moved on to 2017
&amp;amp; 2018 ABRSM Grade 1 assessment pieces. Not necessarily with a view to
taking the exams, but to get to that standard. These are challenging,
probably taking me maybe a couple of weeks to be able to play through
from start to finish at all (i.e. stumbling through them with hands
together), with another week or two to refine them. Even then, I'm aware
of shortcomings that I could still improve on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Popular books, such as these, are a good choice. You'll easily find
competent performances on YouTube as a useful reference for what the
music you're playing should sound like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-is-learning"&gt;How is learning?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually enjoy practice. It can be frustrating, particularly when you
first start out on something and struggle, which can be demoralising.
What you have to do is retain the faith that you'll improve just like
you have on previous pieces when you first encountered them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you're a bit more comfortable that most new things you play could
be the most difficult that you have tackled, the process starts to feel
less daunting. Once you begin to get to grips with a piece, playing
becomes a lot more fun to work on as it comes together, and you make
fewer mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picking out the correct notes, adding the correct rhythm, introducing
dynamics and accents, and pedalling all feel almost like separate layers
of complexity. This can feel overwhelming at times, although focusing on
tackling a subset of these and adding the others on later does help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coordinating two hands is definitely a tricky aspect of piano. It takes
considerable practice to be able to play two different things with your
hands independently. That's very different from guitar (where I have a
little past experience),&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; where left and right hand perform very
different tasks, and it's easier to isolate their movements. That said,
as much as I find certain aspects of piano tricky, I found barre chords
on guitar a real barrier (sorry) to cross.&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Piano feels difficult
generally, but I've not yet encountered any single thing that is a
comparable obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole, learning piano been an enjoyable and rewarding experience.
To go from almost no experience to being able to stumble through Grade 1
pieces, which sound pleasant (if played well), and really feel like
you're playing piano, has been an interesting journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now feeling a bit more confident when I'm attempting to make music.
Knowing that my hands are likely in the correct position, or being able
to noodle around on the keyboard with a more decisive feeling of what
I'm doing as being musical, are some of the early benefits I've gained
from studying piano. Recalling little melodies or chord progressions
also seems a simpler task, since I'm more familiar with keyboard layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a late starter, there's no way I'm going to be ever as good as if I'd
begun when much younger. I think it's important to keep your possible
achievements realistic, so as not to stretch too far and give up in
frustration. Nonetheless, for what I really want to do, create
music,&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the skills being developed are valuable, and, importantly,
I've found learning piano enjoyable enough in itself to continue with
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some take this to
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_MIDI"&gt;extremes&lt;/a&gt; too, treating a
musical score as a canvas that must be filled and painting in an
&lt;em&gt;inhuman&lt;/em&gt; number of notes.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One notable thing from learning guitar is that I only ever read
treble clef, but not bass clef (although I did see it and struggle
through with it a while back in a &lt;a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/edinburgh-music-theory"&gt;Coursera music theory
course&lt;/a&gt;). Because
of that, I'm much less comfortable reading the bass clef. The best way I
can describe this feeling is: imagine the confusion if you were reading
a book where a mischievous publisher had turned every second line upside
down.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've not picked up a guitar, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barre_chord"&gt;barre
chords&lt;/a&gt; are difficult because
they require clamping some or all of the strings down at one fret
position, usually with the index finger. Here, you need to strengthen
and toughen up your finger to do this, as well as placing it correctly
so the strings ring cleanly, instead of with an unsatisfying dull thunk.
It can be tricky.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's certainly worthwhile and enjoyable to play other people's
music well. But I think there's something about the possibility of being
able to create something as an individual. There's no-one else that is
you, or can ever be you. Therefore it is possible to create something
that's really your own and couldn't be made by anyone else, even if
your technical prowess is a hindrance. And sometimes that lack of
competency, to a degree, can be a key part of what marks out what you
create as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outsider_music"&gt;distinct and
unique&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="learning"></category><category term="music"></category><category term="piano"></category></entry><entry><title>Looking at Ableton's Learning Music</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/looking-at-abletons-learning-music" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-21T20:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-05-21T20:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-05-21:posts/looking-at-abletons-learning-music</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Previously I &lt;a href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/book-and-talk-review-making-music-74-creative-strategies-for-electronic-music-producers"&gt;looked at Ableton's book of ideas for music
producers&lt;/a&gt; that came out
a while back, geared to people with some experience of making music
already. That did well in summarising suggestions for creativity into
short, easily digestible chapters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ableton have now followed on by developing a free tutorial site that
actually takes a step back. It's instead aimed at complete beginners who
might be interested in creating music which, in the spirit of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Does_exactly_what_it_says_on_the_tin"&gt;Ronseal&lt;/a&gt;,
Ableton have called it &lt;a href="https://learningmusic.ableton.com/"&gt;Learning
Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the previously published book, this resource is accessible for
free. Is it worth your time to work through?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-does-the-site-work"&gt;How does the site work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always &lt;a href="https://learningmusic.ableton.com/"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;
yourself, but, briefly, each page is a mixture of a small amount of
explanatory text with usually some interactive tool that mimics some
aspect of a digital audio workstation (DAW) (particularly Ableton Live).
Sometimes, there are music videos where some feature of that music is
then broken down on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where this DAW-lite interactivity works well is that it's stripped down
to the minimum framework of triggering samples or placing notes. Looking
at a lot of modern audio software, it's easy to be overwhelmed by
options, even as a seasoned user. This paring down was a sensible
decision so as not to deter the interested who might have little
experience of music theory, or digital music making. (And no doubt made
the site simpler to build too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This functionality also provides an opportunity to practice and try
altering the examples, if someone doesn't yet have a digital audio
workstation installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These interactive tools often nicely assist the user, making it easy to
make something sounding pleasing. This can be by, for example,
restricting the permitted notes to ones within a scale, or, as on the
&lt;a href="https://learningmusic.ableton.com/index.html"&gt;first page&lt;/a&gt;, by carefully
creating patterns that the user can trigger and overlay each other
without any danger of the sounds clashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the look and feel of the interactive sequencer widgets is
obviously influenced by Ableton Live, and could segue nicely into trying
out the Ableton Live demo, the ideas — much like the book — transcend
any particular piece of software. Like the book, even if you've no
interest in Ableton itself, and intend to use some other software (or
hardware) for making music, that shouldn't put you off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial does allow you to export sketches you make in the Learning
Music web app to Ableton Live, should you wish — a nice touch — albeit
one that's geared towards steering users towards Live (which is fair
enough).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other main feature of this tutorial is that context of the musical
ideas is given by reference to contemporary music, often well-known
electronic music. Some aspect of each is broken down. This can be quite
revealing if you haven't thought of music that way before: isolating one
part (percussion, bassline, chords, melodies, structure) and briefly
exploring what makes those aspects effective. It's nice that's it's
example led; it gives the reader something to quickly grab onto, and
provides possible inspirations too. Active listening in this way was
pushed throughout the earlier Making Music book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the creators of the site's material could have gone slightly
further. Maybe deconstructing one simple track throughout the course of
the tutorial would work well in addition to analysing different pieces
of music (which admittedly does help avoid boredom). Referring back to a
single piece of music and considering a different aspect each time might
provide two things: a sense of familiarity as the learner progresses
through the material, and a sense of achievement that they understand
how most of the main aspects of a particular track are put together,
once they've completed the tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="and-does-the-site-work"&gt;And does the site work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of material, if you've ever covered some basic music theory or
have reasonable proficiency on an instrument, then you'll probably have
encountered plenty of what is taught, and you won't get that much out of
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there were still a few things I learned about, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the Indonesian &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pelog"&gt;Pelog&lt;/a&gt; scale;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the opening notes of the melody from Kraftwerk's &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LTZyXlLhvxs"&gt;Tour de
  France&lt;/a&gt; are apparently
  taken from Paul Hindemith's &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vXb63qlNg5c"&gt;Heiter
  Bewegt&lt;/a&gt; from Sonata for
  Flute and Piano. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tutorials, then, only skirt the surface of each topic. Read the
wrong way, this might sound like a criticism. It's not. In teaching
aimed to give a survey of a topic, it's actually a positive: crucially,
it's just enough to get the main point across to the target audience,
make them aware of the ideas, and prompt the curious to go and learn
more elsewhere, without being so detailed as to feel like hard work. So,
for me, the site succeeds in its aims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're a relative newcomer to music theory or composition, have got a
spare hour or two and want to learn a little about creating music, or if
you just want to see breakdowns of how parts of some pieces of music
work — music that you may well have already heard and loved — it's more
than worth your time to work through the material Ableton are offering.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Ableton"></category><category term="music"></category><category term="music theory"></category></entry><entry><title>Trying to trim down static GTFS feeds</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/trying-to-trim-down-static-gtfs-feeds" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-29T22:24:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-29T22:24:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-05-05:posts/trying-to-trim-down-static-gtfs-feeds</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="whats-a-gtfs-feed"&gt;What's a GTFS feed?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I've been attempting to reduce the size of a static GTFS feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, GTFS is the &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/"&gt;General Transit Feed
Specification&lt;/a&gt;, a format
for public transport providers to distribute details of their services.
For example, a bus operator might want to share which routes they run
on, and the times at which they arrive at certain stops. It's not
restricted to buses. You might find GTFS feeds published for trains,
underground services, ferries and &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/reference/routes-file"&gt;even
gondolas&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "static" distinguishes those feeds from realtime&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; feeds. Static
feeds are just zip files that contain a number of text files in a
comma-separated values (CSV) format, with a .txt filename extension.
These CSVs detail regular timetables that should remain valid for some
reasonable length of time, i.e. they change infrequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realtime feeds (GTFS-RT) report, for example, live trip updates (e.g.
when a bus gets behind the published ideal schedule) or vehicle
locations. Realtime feeds are in Google's Protocol Buffers format, not
CSV. It's useful to be aware of the difference, but, beyond that, I
won't discuss GTFS-RT feeds further in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-problem"&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleagues on a project were attempt to load the data we'd found for a
particular country, and they were finding it far too large to be usable.
GTFS files come zipped, and the total unzipped content of this file
wasn't far off a gigabyte, and the import into their software was taking
too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were only interested in one geographic region, so maybe most
content can be filtered out either by location, or by transport agency.
Here's a rundown of what I found with the existing tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="onebusaway-gtfs-transformer"&gt;onebusaway GTFS transformer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, on seeing the &lt;a href="http://developer.onebusaway.org/modules/onebusaway-gtfs-modules/1.3.3/onebusaway-gtfs-transformer-cli.html"&gt;onebusaway GTFS
transformer&lt;/a&gt;,
it seemed like a dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a Java program that lets you simply specify the agencies to retain
from the feed in a simple JSON format, and it's fairly comprehensive in
how you can do that. So, hey, let's write a simple transform JSON that
keeps the bus and train agency for the region of interest, and drop the
rest. Exactly what's needed, and a job well done, so now I can relax, and
take a well-earned rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, &lt;em&gt;opens eyes to the smell of a burning PC&lt;/em&gt;, it's time to wake up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation does provide a warning that this transformation may be
memory and CPU hungry with large GTFS feeds, and that's what I found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the transformer seemed to choke on this large GTFS file.
It ran for a long time (hours, across multiple CPUs), got stuck spinning
its wheels on the huge stop_times.txt file (millions of lines) and never
managed to escape that mud. As well as that, out of memory errors were a
problem. In the software's defence, the free memory on the instance I
was running on was fairly limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've simpler GTFS feeds to work with, it may do the trick, but, for
large ones, you'll need a beefy PC to possibly get anywhere with it.
That said, there's little status output while it's running, meaning it
was unclear whether the transformer was ever doing any useful work or
just getting stuck in some loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="gtfstidy"&gt;gtfstidy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, &lt;a href="https://github.com/patrickbr/gtfstidy/"&gt;gtfstidy&lt;/a&gt;. It can reduce
the size of static GTFS feeds by removing redundant content, simplifying
identifiers and doing clever things to optimise shape data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's written in Go, although there are no builds provided, so you'll
have to have Go to install or compile it yourself, which is easy enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, it took a long time to process; here, about five hours on my
2013 Core i5 laptop. Then, gtfstidy crashed right at the end of
processing the data &lt;a href="https://github.com/patrickbr/gtfstidy/issues/1"&gt;because as I later discovered, it expected the
output directory to
exist&lt;/a&gt; and just failed
to write the output otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then it took &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; few hours after I created said output
directory to run again and actually get the cleaned feed data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, gtfstidy reduced the total size of the GTFS files by about
150 MB, which is a considerable saving. My initial idea was maybe it
might clean the data up enough to make running the onebusaway
transformer a little bit quicker, but it didn't seem worth bothering
trying that again, as the data files overall were still large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition article-edit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit 2017-12-29: The author of gtfstidy emailed me to say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;gtfstidy actually comes with a very handy option which I use
extensively for filtering. If you run gtfstidy with &lt;code&gt;-DO&lt;/code&gt;, it will
delete any entity which makes any problems during validation and
also delete any entity which is not referenced anywhere. This
cascades through the feed. This means that, if you want to only
keep data for certain agencies, for example, you can just delete
all agencies you don't want to keep from the agency.txt file.
&lt;code&gt;gtfstidy -DO&lt;/code&gt; will now remove any route that references one of the
agencies you have deleted, and any trip that references one of
these routes, and any stop_time that references one of these
trips, and so on. If any orphan stops, or orphan shapes, or orphan
fare rules etc remain after this, the &lt;code&gt;-O&lt;/code&gt; option will delete them
too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works for any of the GTFS files. If you just want to keep trips
for certain stops, delete every other stop from stops.txt. If you
just want to keep data for some routes, delete all the other routes.
After &lt;code&gt;gtfstidy -DO&lt;/code&gt;, you will have a new error-free, filtered subset
of the original feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="gtfssplit"&gt;gtfssplit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href="https://github.com/samuelmr/gtfssplit"&gt;gtfssplit&lt;/a&gt; is a PHP
tool that breaks apart a static GTFS feed into trips, shapes and stops.
Unlike the other two projects, this one hasn't been touched for a
while.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This took a fair time to run, although you can see it's at least doing
something some of the time, because, contrary to the relatively shy and
subdued onebusaway transformer, it displays a lot of warnings while
running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once these files are all on disk, maybe it's possible to write code to
recombine these back together into a GTFS feed, filtering out for
agencies that you're not interested in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I observed is that the dates.txt files that the gtfssplit documentation
refers to in the output (that should be for a given service, i.e. to
tell you which dates the service applies) didn't seem to be present, so
it might be possible that it's losing data somewhere. Maybe that's
because the feed I was looking at has a &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/reference/calendar_dates-file"&gt;calendar_dates.txt and no
calendar.txt
file&lt;/a&gt;,
and this case isn't handled. (It's valid, just not the recommended way
of putting together a feed.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I'm not sure, and didn't spend any more time investigating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="journeys-end"&gt;Journey's end?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's as far I got to, which is a little anticlimactic. That is, I
haven't found a good existing solution for solving this for large feeds,
outside of the prospect of attempting to write code to do this myself.
However, the fact that all the existing software runs slowly, doesn't
exactly instil me with much hope of doing a better job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big difference is that what's actually needed here to solve the
problem is something relatively simple by comparison. The core issue is
that the stop_times.txt is too large. Maybe it's possible to filter that
down based on working through the various files, which is a much more
specific kind of tool than the generic transformer. Perhaps this could
work along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep rows from routes.txt that match the relatively few transport
   &lt;code&gt;agency_id&lt;/code&gt;s of interest giving a set of &lt;code&gt;route_id&lt;/code&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep rows from trips.txt that match those &lt;code&gt;route_id&lt;/code&gt;s from 1 in
   trips.txt, so now these give &lt;code&gt;trip_id&lt;/code&gt;s of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep rows in stop_times.txt if they match a &lt;code&gt;trip_id&lt;/code&gt; retained from
   2, meaning most of the rows disappear, assuming the agencies that are
   of interest make up only a small proportion of the total rows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could go further and then fix up the other files too to purge
anything that's now no longer relevant: for example, cleaning agency.txt
to remove agencies that are no longer present. But perhaps gtfstidy
might be enough to tidy up the remaining files and allow us to construct
a clean and valid feed from the files we've mangled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also ways of wrangling GTFS feeds into SQL databases — haven't
linked any as I haven't tried any and can't vouch for them, but they're
easy to find by searching "GTFS to SQL" — so importing and writing
queries to do this filtering, then exporting the result as CSV might be
an alternative option instead of coding something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all speculation for now; I haven't attempted any of this yet. If
I do and it's useful, I'll share what I learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition article-edit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit 2017-12-29: The approach I actually used to solve this problem
is on &lt;a href="https://github.com/sensiblecodeio/diet-gtfs"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; albeit
scrappy. It's possible to specify a latitude and longitude range,
which you can then filter out stops in stops.txt, and then remove
any then-irrelevant content in the other files, and rebuild the
feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I seem to recall this generated a feed with no serious problems
when verified by a GTFS feed validator; you could always try
sending the output of this through something like gtfstidy, of
course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would be nice is if feed providers offered feeds in smaller
regional chunks. Often, transport companies are providing GTFS feeds at
an agency level, so these should be relatively small. I suspect that the
sources of countrywide feeds are usually efforts of communities or
companies to compile the data, which is sometimes originally in a format
other than GTFS, into a standard feed. So it feels ungrateful to comment
that it would be nicer if they broke these feeds into smaller chunks for
data consumers to import into software without further work because
they're providing a free service and their efforts are appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, those making efforts to share this data may find more
users for their data if it's ready for import into other software
without needing fast PCs with lots of RAM, or without consumers having
to find ways to divide up the provided feed. For instance, applications
like OpenTripPlanner can, at time of writing, &lt;a href="https://github.com/opentripplanner/OpenTripPlanner/issues/2063"&gt;still struggle with large
GTFS
files&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The single word "realtime" is how the specification writes it.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't always the case, but looking at the activity of an open
  source project can be a portent of how useful it might be, if
  there are several competing bits of software that do the same
  thing and you're trying to narrow down to a few candidates to try
  out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How popular a project is, e.g. the number of GitHub stars, might
  be one indicator, although all projects will start out at zero on
  this, so it could well be a good project you've stumbled across
  that's just relatively new, or in a particular niche that means it
  will never become extremely popular. If there are multiple
  competing projects, you can compare them relatively, as opposed to
  comparing their number of stars to &lt;a href="https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap"&gt;something like
  Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The age of the last commit is another. If a project has not been
  touched in a very long time, it could be so good that it hasn't
  needed any maintenance, or just be abandoned because it no longer
  works, or it never did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A project with comprehensive documentation, particularly if the
  documentation is good and still valid is another positive sign.
  Especially if you can get a software package or program to install
  and runs an example as described in the docs. There have been
  times I've found that this isn't the case; not a good start and
  I'm likely to give up at this point, if there are alternatives to
  still try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren't definite rules. And if projects are open source, then
  the only cost in trying them out is time, but these are some of
  the rules of thumb that I'd use when looking out for software I'm
  unfamiliar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking for recommendations from others is another valuable
  resource that might speed up your search, instead of solely
  relying on your own judgement and web searching skills too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This footnote definitely turned out much longer than planned.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="GTFS"></category><category term="open data"></category><category term="transit"></category><category term="public transport"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning LaTeX: why and how</title><link href="https://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/learning-latex-why-and-how" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-01T15:02:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-05-01T15:02:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-05-01:posts/learning-latex-why-and-how</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="sharelatex"&gt;ShareLaTeX&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I saw &lt;a href="https://www.sharelatex.com/learn/Learn_LaTeX_in_30_minutes"&gt;this
documentation&lt;/a&gt;
from ShareLaTeX linked on Hacker News and, as I haven't used LaTeX in a
while, thought I'd quickly skim through to see what I remembered. And I
started reminiscing about LaTeX which I'd been using semi-regularly
around a decade ago, eventually writing a circa 300 page thesis with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've never encountered it before, LaTeX is a free software project
that is described by the &lt;a href="https://www.latex-project.org"&gt;project's site&lt;/a&gt;
as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a high-quality typesetting system; it includes features designed for
the production of technical and scientific documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's nothing to stop you using it for other types of documents too;
those are just the areas where it's traditionally used, particularly in
academic circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to ShareLaTeX. First, the ShareLaTeX documentation looks pretty
good if you need something to get you started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't used ShareLaTeX recently although I think I tried it out a few
years back and it seemed fine enough. It's a web app that lets you
prepare LaTeX documents and, if you pay, collaborate on them. One big
advantage I can see of using a web app for LaTeX beginners is that it
removes one of the barriers of starting with LaTeX: installing
everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="installing-latex-on-windows"&gt;Installing LaTeX on Windows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've not had cause to use LaTeX much recently, so haven't tried
installing on Ubuntu; a lot of my writing is done via Markdown, whether
technical documentation or words like the ones you're reading now on my
blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Windows, it used to be reasonably simple to get a working system with
&lt;a href="http://www.texniccenter.org"&gt;TeXnicCenter&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://miktex.org"&gt;MikTeX&lt;/a&gt;, but you'd still have to get a PDF viewer,
like &lt;a href="https://www.sumatrapdfreader.org"&gt;SumatraPDF&lt;/a&gt; integrated into that
for previewing. This &lt;a href="https://tex.stackexchange.com/questions/116981/how-to-configure-texniccenter-2-0-with-sumatra-2013-2016-version"&gt;Stack Exchange
answer&lt;/a&gt;
may help with integrating the PDF preview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though that's still three different bits of software you have to get
working together, so not a trivial task by any means. From memory,
install MikTeX first, as TeXnicCenter can detect it during install and
configure its own settings to use your MikTeX installation without you
needing to set things up by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="starting-out"&gt;Starting out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ShareLaTeX documentation just starts out with creating a basic
document and has you working through following their example. That's
fine to see things piece by piece. Beyond that the single suggestion I'd
have for a new user to learn effectively is to take a completed document
you have written, representative of what you'd like to create using
LaTeX, and then &lt;strong&gt;struggle through recreating that existing document in
LaTeX&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it may well be a struggle, but this has a few benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's presumably a finished work, so you don't have any time pressure
  for completion. With a deadline to meet, as soon as you encounter
  issues with LaTeX, you'll likely fall back to whatever word processor
  or document creator you're comfortable with to get the job done, and
  then give up on learning LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a document similar to that you'd usually be writing, you'll
  encounter many of the issues in LaTeX that you'd hit doing so, and can
  solve these without the aforementioned time pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, it was graphics and, especially, table layouts
that caused the most problems, but you may have particular
typography requirements that require some package to be installed,
or some subtle override of the LaTeX defaults to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding these solutions is not always quick, but I imagine there are
more forum posts, &lt;a href="https://tex.stackexchange.com/"&gt;Stack Exchange&lt;/a&gt;
questions and blog posts around than there were when I started, so
it's likely someone's encountered and asked about the same issue
you're dealing with. The LaTeX Community forum was also a good
source of helpful solutions from knowledgable people even in its
early days ten years ago, and &lt;a href="http://latex.org/forum/"&gt;still lives on
today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A completed document gives you a reference for getting started in
  future.  You can use it as the basis for a new document, instead of
  starting from nothing, or you can just refer back to it and copy and
  paste appropriate bits of formatting markup you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="latex-versus-word"&gt;LaTeX versus Word&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="latex-installation"&gt;LaTeX installation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I saw it when learning back in 2007ish, LaTeX was more difficult to
get started with than the likes of conventional word processors: the
installation isn't trivial, and you need several things other than your
desired text in a LaTeX document before you can get that text to
display. In a word processor, you can just start typing. So there's some
level of competence you need just to make &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; old document, let alone
the one you actually want to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="word-woes"&gt;Word woes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Word is easy to get started with, but Word had, and maybe still has, its
own problems: again, going back to 2007, to when Word 2003 was still
popular, referencing support was limited, that you'd use external tools
for (e.g. EndNote or &lt;a href="https://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;).  I'm not sure
how Word looks with respect to that now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, Word seemed to struggle and be sluggish with large documents
with lots of images, which was always fun. Again, maybe that's improved
in recent versions? When editing LaTeX, you're only editing the source
markup in whatever text editor you choose to use, and this source, even
for a lengthy document, will be relatively small; images for LaTeX are
stored entirely separately from the source. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue with Word is ensuring formatting styles are correctly and
consistently applied to text. You can create styles, but you then have
to apply them by hand, selecting the text. Sometimes you may delete
spacing between words and suddenly you have to reapply a styling, as the
text has changed to the style of its neighbours. In LaTeX, anything to
do with formatting is specified explicitly in the markup, making it easy
to see that the correct styling is applied to the text.  Furthermore,
the LaTeX defaults are usually decent, not always perfect, but decent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-good-and-bad-of-latex"&gt;The good and bad of LaTeX&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This explicitness and strictness of LaTeX is good and bad. It means that
you know what is intended for your text, but it also means that it's
possible for you to break your document sufficiently such that it cannot
be rendered correctly, or sometimes even at all, by LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've done programming and are used to finding and correcting your
inevitable mistakes, this isn't unusual. But the idea of having written
a document that you can't then display in the intended output format may
be an intimidating concept to new users. Likewise, the error messages
can be numerous and formal, and not much help to novice users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tricks known to programmers like a regular edit-compile cycle to ensure
you find issues as you create them, or commenting out markup to isolate
the specific parts of markup that are the cause of difficult to
understand problems are useful skills. (These ways of working are
perhaps a result of the creators of LaTeX — and TeX, which LaTeX is
built on — being computer scientists.) However, these concepts may not
be immediately obvious by users with little experience of coding who
just want to get on with writing, and don't want tools getting in the
way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, working just with the LaTeX source and focusing on
the text alone seems much more productive to me. You can concentrate on
content first, and fix up the presentation at the end. Otherwise, I find
that working alongside the printed document layout presents me with the
continuous distraction of making things look "right", fixing incorrect
formatting or alignments, even though the content in question could be
modified or removed entirely during later editing. This time might be
better spent just writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking of layout, in my opinion, a LaTeX document using defaults will
be much more pleasant to read than a Word document using defaults. To
some extent, in both cases, this can somewhat depend on templates that
you may choose to create your document, but a default LaTeX document has
more of the look of a professionally typeset book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, many useful additions to LaTeX come in the form of a huge range
of additional packages you can install to add new commands and features.
Again, this is a mixed blessing. First, you need to be aware that they
even exist — &lt;a href="https://tex.stackexchange.com/questions/553/what-packages-do-people-load-by-default-in-latex"&gt;lists like
this&lt;/a&gt;
can help: there may be a package perfect for what you're trying to do,
but you just haven't discovered it yet. Another hassle is that you can
have incompatibility issues between certain packages, or they may
require to be loaded in a certain order. Fixing problems like these is
time, again, spent on tools, not on writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do need to be careful of package updates. Mostly these should be
benign, but in one case I experienced, a package update suddenly broke
my document, and I had to spend time discovering the problem and
reverting the package version.  (My memory's hazy, but I think this was
complicated by MikTeX only having the latest package versions, so in the
end I think that I had to download from elsewhere and install by hand.)
This may be an issue for compiling documents if you return to them much
later in the future: if any of the packages have broken their backwards
compatibility, you may be stuck. There's also no easy way that I was
aware of to pin package versions, like you might in a &lt;a href="https://packaging.python.org/requirements/"&gt;Python
setup.py&lt;/a&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="do-you-still-need-to-learn-latex-these-days"&gt;Do you still need to learn LaTeX these days?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I learned LaTeX, software like &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/"&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt; has
appeared and made it simple to write in other formats — for instance,
Markdown, reStructuredText, or HTML — and convert that to LaTeX.
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; in particular is very
simple, and easy to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For relatively straightforward documents, that's an alternative to give
you the benefit of nicely typeset output, without having to bother
writing LaTeX directly. This can give you a handy subset of LaTeX in
potentially a simpler markup, especially with Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, LaTeX remains flexible and powerful and, especially for
creating more complicated documents, it still retains popularity more
than thirty years after its first development. Furthermore, it's also
released under an open source license (the LaTeX Project Public License)
so these professional-level tools are available to everyone at no cost.
If you have the likes of long reports or a thesis to write, it's
certainly still worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="LaTeX"></category><category term="document preparation"></category><category term="word processor"></category></entry></feed>