<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>stevenmaude.co.uk</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/</id><updated>2015-07-18T23:54:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Thinking of using a static site generator for your blog?</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/thinking-of-using-a-static-site-generator-for-your-blog" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-18T23:54:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-07-18:posts/thinking-of-using-a-static-site-generator-for-your-blog</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I first thought about moving from Blogger to Pelican, it was
because I'd had more than enough of Blogger's drawbacks. What hadn't
crossed my mind, because I had no experience of using them, were the
problems that static site generators could have. At the time, my hunch
was that it wasn't possible for them to be worse than Blogger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, that was the case. But, they are not entirely perfect
and, going through this migration, I better understood what
what the good and the bad of static site generators are. If you're
thinking of making a similar migration, these points might give you an
idea of what you might deal with in shifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I'm familiar with Pelican and Blogger, most of the points apply
generally so could still be informative for you if you're considering a
move from, say, Wordpress to Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Converting and writing content (Markdown)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on what you used to create a blog previously, and how much
    content you had on your old blog, it may be time consuming to move
    content. Even armed with a &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican/pull/1390"&gt;fork of Pelican&lt;/a&gt; where
    someone helpful had added Blogger conversion, the output
    wasn't perfect and still had plenty of residual cruft that had to be
    fixed up by hand.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown's quick to write with, but only gives you a small subset of
    HTML and so doesn't handle every eventuality. There are dialects of
    Markdown which expand this with more layout options that may be
    available in your blog software of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Pelican at least, it's possible to use
&lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; via a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/liob/pandoc_reader"&gt;plugin&lt;/a&gt;. Pandoc is one of
the more versatile Markdown converters, but does introduces another
dependency. Pelican also offers reStructuredText support which has
support for more formatting options than vanilla Markdown, but just
isn't as nimble to write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I opted to occasionally allow fall back to raw HTML in
posts, mainly for handling images. This isn't ideal, but is a decent
compromise that's at least compatible with different Markdown
implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All my content is in fairly plain Markdown which I love writing in.
    It also means that I'm far less locked into Pelican than I was ever
    tied into Blogger. Should I wish to switch to another static site
    generator, only the metadata and Python-Markdown specific tweaks may
    need adjusting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adding content to the site and hosting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My git repositories are structured in a way that I like: blog HTML,
    the theme I use, my Pelican configuration, my Markdown posts, and
    the post images are all separate. However, for making small
    adjustments to posts, this is a nuisance: you need to edit the post
    and remember to push that, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; generate the HTML, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; move
    that into the HTML repository and finally push that to GitHub. I
    usually do this via branches too, which is more work too (though
    this is my choice). Improving this workflow is on my to-do list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My blog's not trapped within Google's servers. Certainly, I'm wary
    of how much Google's hands are present in much of what I do on the
    web, whether through hardware devices I use, their search tools or
    through websites that use features like Google Analytics and Fonts
    (including mine). At least the blog's now hosted elsewhere and
    Analytics and Fonts that the site's using could, in the worst case,
    be removed entirely, or replaced with alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the blog's not really dependent on the whims of any service
    owner at all. If GitHub stop hosting, I can take the HTML and host
    it elsewhere. With Blogger, you're at Google's mercy: if they ever
    decided to drop Blogger, then you'd be forced to switch to a new
    blog platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the content is tracked within a git repository. This means it's
    version controlled, and there's no easy way to obliterate posts.
    With Blogger, at least once, I foolishly attempted to edit multiple
    posts in separate browser tabs and subsequently lost the content of
    one of them. Luckily, I had a window open with the web version of
    the post to recover it. But, having only a single canonical copy of
    posts stored in Google's servers was clearly not a good thing.
    (Wordpress is better in that it's possible to store multiple
    revisions of posts.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have much more control of the post URLs; Blogger posts always
    have the year and date in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blog hosting using my own domain name on GitHub is free of charge.
    This is also free on Blogger. If you use wordpress.com, you'll need
    to pay; if you're using your own Wordpress installation, using your
    own domain is free, but it's likely you'll need to pay for hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Appearance and viewer experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With Pelican (probably much less so for Jekyll), there's not a huge
    range of themes. If you're fussy like me, you may need to spend some
    time tweaking, or creating your own. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My site now functions without the viewer needing JavaScript. With
    Blogger, you used to only see half the page content. If JavaScript
    is disabled now, the only issue is that the mobile menu doesn't
    open, which is far less of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no awful separate mobile version of the site. On Blogger,
    the template I used had an unfriendly feature where swiping would
    navigate away from the page to the previous or next article. This
    could be triggered quite unintentionally by trying to pinch to zoom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often my posts are on programming. Having code snippets that look
    nice without me having to do anything is a great bonus. In Blogger,
    you'd need a JavaScript plugin for syntax highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Running the generator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static site generators are not for the impatient. For Pelican, being
    comfortable with Python is a big help, though not essential.
    Pelican — and I imagine this applies to Jekyll too — isn't difficult
    to get a basic blog up and running, but to get the result you want
    may take you considerable work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a very large number of posts, the time it takes to build
    your site may become an issue. With 61 posts and 1 page, my site
    takes 2 to 3 seconds on my Core i5 PC. If the site starts taking
    minutes to build, that may become a chore. This would be
    particularly frustrating if editing posts and wanting to quickly
    preview how the changes look since, with Pelican, the entire site is
    rebuilt when running the development server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican is nice to use, and I had very few problems in doing so.
    Most of my effort was spent on converting content and amending the
    theme to my liking. Though the community's relatively small, it does
    seem like there are more blog posts and activity compared with when
    I first looked into it last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican, and many other static site generators, are &lt;a href="http://opensource.org/"&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt; software. This means they are free
    to use, and free to modify (and share those modifications). The
    implication is that, as long as there are developers interested in
    it, it's likely that it will continue to be supported and developed.
    Even in the unlikely event that everyone else abandons it and you're
    the only user, you can still continue modifying it. (This also
    applies to Wordpress' source too incidentally.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Living with a static site&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When worrying about the limitations that static sites may have, think
about the actual minimum you need on a web site to share and present
written ideas and thoughts you have. It's really not very much; do you
&lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need everything that Wordpress offers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I'm pleased with the result. When I'd started thinking about
moving, I'd got fed up of using clunky old Blogger, which feels
distinctly unloved by Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to write directly in the format (Markdown) that the blog
actually uses is a real convenience. (Note that Wordpress offers this
option too.) Along with that, the blog looking fresher than it did is a
bonus. These features, more than perhaps anything else, actually makes
me want to add new content to my blog, which is more than I could say
that Blogger ever did for my inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see exactly how much work in the early commits
&lt;a href="https://github.com/StevenMaude/blog-content/commits/master"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Blogger"></category><category term="Pelican"></category><category term="Wordpress"></category><category term="static site"></category></entry><entry><title>Restoring a tag cloud dispersed by Pelican 3.6.0</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/restoring-a-tag-cloud-dispersed-by-pelican-360" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-12T11:51:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-07-12:posts/restoring-a-tag-cloud-dispersed-by-pelican-360</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;The case of the disappearing tag cloud&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can probably tell — if not from the posts mentioning Pelican,
then the giveaway is the footer of each page — my site is currently
built using &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noticing there was a new version this week, I eagerly updated and then
tried building my site. No errors, I thought, so everything must be
fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, on loading the site, the tag cloud had vanished&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next twenty minutes or so, I slowly figured out the cause: the
Pelican code that creates this had been moved out to a separate plugin.
(If only I'd checked the &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.0/faq.html#my-tag-cloud-is-missing-broken-since-i-upgraded-pelican"&gt;Pelican
docs&lt;/a&gt;
first, I would have saved the time...) From there, it's a simple fix.
Install the plugin, add it to your &lt;code&gt;PLUGINS&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;/code&gt; and the
tag cloud will be restored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installing Pelican plugins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One small frustration is that the official plugin
&lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-plugins"&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; is, if maybe
not monolithic, a substantial size. The appeal of a central repository
does make some sense. It provides a single location for developers to
add functionality to Pelican and means users can issue one command to
get access to everything at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my hunch is that users probably only want a few of the numerous
plugins: seventy at the time of writing. Also, when a plugin is updated
by its author, they additionally have to put a pull request into the
plugins repository to keep the submodule or files stored there in sync,
which is extra work for everyone involved too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My tag cloud plugin fork&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution for installing the plugin would be to write a simple shell
script that does the cloning and just keeps the tag plugin. Instead, I
felt that it would be both simpler and more sensible — rather than
retrieving many plugins that I don't need — to install the plugin via
the existing &lt;code&gt;requirements.txt&lt;/code&gt; in my blog configuration. (The other
plugin I use, &lt;a href="https://github.com/Nitron/pelican-alias/"&gt;pelican-alias&lt;/a&gt;,
is installed this way in my setup.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I made the plugin  &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; installable (available
&lt;a href="https://github.com/StevenMaude/pelican-tag-cloud"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and added that
to my requirements for what seems like a neater solution. The only
downside is that I have to ensure that this plugin is updated when the
original code is. For this plugin however, I suspect that updates would
be irregular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the site's not changed since I wrote this, then it's the one
that shows up in the upper right sidebar.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Pelican"></category><category term="tag cloud"></category><category term="plugin"></category></entry><entry><title>Blogger versus Wordpress revisited</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/blogger-versus-wordpress-revisited" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-06T14:46:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-06-06:posts/blogger-versus-wordpress-revisited</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you look back, the &lt;a href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/blogger-versus-wordpress"&gt;first post&lt;/a&gt;
on this blog was agonising over what blogging system to use. At the
time, my reasoning for choosing Blogger was that it was quick to get
started with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that was true. Provided you already have a Google account, you can
make a blog in a few clicks. There's a simple interface for entering
posts: you can enter raw HTML or use something that looks more like a
word processor. Even if you know very little about how the web works, it
makes publishing straightforward. It's cost-free to use too, even if
you're using your own domain name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the limitations of Blogger soon became apparent:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default templates available look dated. (Though you could well
  modify them or install one from elsewhere). Furthermore, for the
  default template I used, which was fairly plain, it wasn't even
  possible to read the site properly without JavaScript: half of the
  page content would not be displayed. Code snippets, which I've often
  used in posts, are also hard to read because there's no syntax
  highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mobile template for Blogger interprets swiping left or right
  across the screen as meaning that you want to move to a different
  article. This is frustrating enough even when you know about it as
  it's easy to trigger unintentionally. It's more confusing for someone
  visiting your site for the first time. As mobile internet browsing
  increases, the needs of viewers on those devices becomes more
  important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I found writing posts on Blogger to be clumsy. The WYSIWYG
  editor is quite limited. If you want anything outside of the fairly
  limited feature set (for example, footnotes, or more control over
  images), you need to edit the HTML directly. The HTML that the editor
  creates seems to get polluted with unnecessary tags quite often,
  especially if you're switching fonts (e.g. between code and non-code
  sections).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also accidentally lost work due to having two copies
of the post creator open, with one overwriting the contents of the
other unintentionally on save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To work around this, towards the end of my Blogger use, I was
writing posts in Markdown&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; completely separately, converting them
from Markdown to HTML, then pasting the HTML into Blogger, fixing
up things and adding images. Writing posts in Markdown was
convenient, the subsequent wrangling of the HTML output to Blogger
was not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current, published form of the blog posts is that which is
  stored in Google's servers. Keeping a local copy and
  tracking any changes made in posts was a chore, so I never bothered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogger isn't software available for you to run on your own computer,
  so you're at
  Google's mercy. If Google change something that you find particularly
  detrimental, or if they ever decided to drop it completely, you'll be
  forced elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what are the alternatives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main off the shelf solutions seem to be Wordpress or static site
generators. Wordpress is &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; popular for building blogs, and
actually resolves many of my Blogger complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One big plus is that it's open source (see &lt;a href="https://wordpress.org"&gt;wordpress.org&lt;/a&gt;).
This means you can run it anywhere you like, though you'll have to pay
to host it somewhere. Alternatively, you can host your blog at
&lt;a href="https://wordpress.com"&gt;wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt; for free, albeit with possible
ads and without the use of your own domain name. Resolving these
problems is simple: just give them money!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wordpress is also a step up from Blogger in terms of customisability,
with a much larger user community around it. Because of this, there's
far more in the way of themes and plugins to tweak your blog how you
want it. Researching just now, I discovered 
&lt;a href="https://en.support.wordpress.com/markdown/"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is supported
for writing posts, which is great. And some previous history of your
posts are saved (25 revisions at the time of writing), with the
ability to &lt;a href="https://en.support.wordpress.com/posts/post-revisions/"&gt;revert and compare
them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, having used Wordpress at work, there were still three big reasons
why Wordpress didn't seem a suitable replacement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost of hosting.&lt;/strong&gt; This isn't particularly high, but my blog is just
  a side project, so I'd rather keep the costs minimal. Blogger is
  free: any other possible solution is competing with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wordpress uses PHP, which I know nothing about.&lt;/strong&gt; It's unlikely, but
  if I ever did want to do any low-level customisation, I'd need to
  learn it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wordpress seems too heavy-handed for what I need&lt;/strong&gt;: a simple way of
  presenting text-based articles on the web. This is reflected both in
  its frequent security updates (though an &lt;a href="https://codex.wordpress.org/Configuring_Automatic_Background_Updates"&gt;automatic update option&lt;/a&gt;
  is available) and its byzantine menus which ordinarily see me
  clicking every option exhaustively until I find the setting I want to
  change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not to say Wordpress is a bad option — lots of sites do use it
— just that it wasn't the right option for me. For my use case, which is
sharing things I've written, static site generators seemed a better fit.
I'll describe the advantages of those in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown is a simple way to mark up plain text with your intended
  formatting using annotations that you might already be accustomed
  to. For example, to indicate bold text you would type
  &lt;code&gt;**important point**&lt;/code&gt; to give the output &lt;strong&gt;important point&lt;/strong&gt;. Its
  original use was to create HTML simply, but it can also be
  converted into many other formats using tools like
  &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/"&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Blogger"></category><category term="Wordpress"></category></entry><entry><title>Hiding draft articles in Pelican</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/hiding-draft-articles-in-pelican" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-01T13:53:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-05-31:posts/hiding-draft-articles-in-pelican</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;What I thought I'd get done in a week, actually took about four
months. But I'm finally free of Blogger and have moved to
&lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt; for creating my blog. I'll be
writing more about how I migrated soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I approached the end of that lengthy migration, I found myself
writing new draft articles that I wanted to ensure didn't actually make
their way into my publication directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Writing blog posts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way that I usually approach writing blog posts is that, as
I reach the end of writing them, I'll start reading in the final display
format, i.e. as a web page. This helps spot any mistakes that
I might miss from my eyes glazing over at a text editor, and helps me
spot formatting problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, you might be working on multiple articles at once, so you want to
publish while you still have draft articles in your &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a few ways to prevent posts from being accidentally published,
without needing to do file juggling of your drafts in and out of the
&lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Marking as draft and &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any articles we stick in the &lt;code&gt;content&lt;/code&gt; directory will end up in our
&lt;code&gt;output&lt;/code&gt; directory, right? Not if we do like
&lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/latest/content.html"&gt;the documentation says&lt;/a&gt;
and add &lt;code&gt;Status: draft&lt;/code&gt; to the metadata.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building your site will then place draft articles in a &lt;code&gt;drafts&lt;/code&gt;
directory, and the articles therein aren't linked from anywhere. This
might be useful if you want to share a link with someone to get feedback
on a post before you officially publish it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file in your &lt;code&gt;output&lt;/code&gt; directory is also an option
if you're using &lt;code&gt;git&lt;/code&gt; to push new versions of your blog for publication.
Add &lt;code&gt;drafts/&lt;/code&gt; to your &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; and you'd have to make a deliberate
effort to add them for publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stopping Pelican from seeing the draft posts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other option is to just prevent Pelican from seeing draft posts
completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This does mean that they won't appear in your local preview of your
site, not even as an unlinked page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Using Pelican's &lt;code&gt;IGNORE_FILES&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting "draft" in the filename of any drafts is another option. Then,
you can use the &lt;code&gt;IGNORE_FILES&lt;/code&gt; setting in &lt;code&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;/code&gt; to
specifically ignore the drafts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that if you specify a setting in your Pelican configuration files,
the defaults get overridden. This means that you'll need to copy over
the existing settings from the defaults too. Otherwise, you'll
unintentionally change your configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, the &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/latest/settings.html"&gt;default&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;code&gt;IGNORE_FILES&lt;/code&gt; setting is &lt;code&gt;IGNORE_FILES = ['.#*']&lt;/code&gt; so we'll need to
add &lt;code&gt;IGNORE_FILES = ['.#*', '*draft*']&lt;/code&gt; to our Pelican settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Hiding the files completely (in Ubuntu, at least)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Linux, I thought that preceding the filename with a dot would hide
posts from Pelican, but it doesn't seem to. However, sticking a tilde on
the end of the filename does seem to prevent Pelican from seeing the
post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One side-effect is that if you use a text editor that creates backup
files with a tilde on the end, your backup files will actually have
&lt;strong&gt;another&lt;/strong&gt; tilde on the end (e.g. &lt;code&gt;my_draft_post.md~~&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Maybe marking files as hidden in Windows would have the same effect?
Haven't tried this.)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="draft"></category><category term="article"></category><category term="Pelican"></category></entry><entry><title>Taking control of Chromium (and Chrome) with µblock and HTTP Switchboard</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/taking-control-of-chromium-and-chrome" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-18T12:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2014-09-28:posts/taking-control-of-chromium-and-chrome</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="admonition article-edit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit 2015-05-18: The Chromium bug is fixed which should fix the µMatrix
UI sluggishness, and µMatrix is finally available as a Firefox addon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition article-edit"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edit 2015-01-09: HTTP Switchboard development is discontinued and has been
replaced with &lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uMatrix"&gt;µMatrix&lt;/a&gt;. The
interface is largely unchanged. One problem at the time of writing is a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock/issues/419"&gt;Chromium bug&lt;/a&gt; which I
think is the cause of the UI being really laggy to appear. Hopefully,
this should be fixed soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After tinkering around with Adblock's filters to block some ads, I
remembered that I'd read about an alternative to Adblock for
Chromium-based browsers called &lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/httpswitchboard"&gt;HTTP
Switchboard&lt;/a&gt; a few months ago
and figured I should actually give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons that HTTP Switchboard was notable is that it promised
to be much more CPU and memory friendly than &lt;a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/nnethercote/2014/05/14/adblock-pluss-effect-on-firefoxs-memory-usage/"&gt;Adblock Plus&lt;/a&gt;
currently is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the adblocking part of HTTP Switchboard has now been separated
out into another project, µblock. Both are still useful. I'll explain
why below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why are you blocking content at all?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many content-driven websites use advertising as their business model. My
feeling is that, while sites are welcome to try and send content to my
browser, I should have the freedom to choose what my browser actually
loads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no contract I've signed that states I must load and display the
page as the site owner intends. (What if I'm using a text browser like
links?) And there's no obligation on my part to make their business
model sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you still think this seems selfish. Well, to some extent it is.
But, my privacy and computer security are more important to me than the
financial success or failure of an external organisation. That I put my
priorities in this order is kind of obvious though, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why shouldn't sites and advertisers worry so much?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even with "despicable" users like me, there are two reasons I can think
of as to why advertisers and sites dependent on them shouldn't feel so
glum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Adblocking users have made an active choice to block ads. Those
    users have done you a favour in removing themselves from your
    viewership as you don't waste time targeting them; why chase
    "customers" running in the opposite direction from you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Browsing is increasingly done from mobile browsers. How many users
    are going to bother to root their devices or install alternative
    browsers just for adblocking?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But why worry about where displayed web content originates from?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Privacy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One contentious issue with ads and cookies is privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="http://www.economist.com/news/special-report/21615871-everything-people-do-online-avidly-followed-advertisers-and-third-party"&gt;this Economist
article&lt;/a&gt;
highlights,
the depth of what advertisers collect about your browsing habits is
extensive, and it's handled and passed around by many organisations.
Unless you're all for being advertised at, this isn't for your benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe advertisers are really all benign and just interested in deciding
who's best to try to sell to. Perhaps just as the executive in that
article quoted claims, it really is just that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"We are not trolling for personal information. We are trying to figure
out if you are a high-value customer and are in the market for a car."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, the sheer amount of information being collected is worrying,
especially when, as a user, I've no idea of what's actually being
tracked and what the intended end use is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Malware&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as that, web advertising has been a conduit for the deployment
of malware previously and will no doubt continue to be. (It's a nice way
of distributing it to users who are visiting, what to them, might seem
like a trustworthy site. If they can get the malicious ad past the
company providing the advertising, they don't need to go to the trouble
of hacking the site directly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There have been
&lt;a href="http://arstechnica.com/security/2014/09/google-stops-malicious-advertising-campaign-that-could-have-reached-millions/"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;
or &lt;a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-switch/wp/2014/01/04/thousands-of-visitors-to-yahoo-com-hit-with-malware-attack-researchers-say/"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;
high-profile incidents this year too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of potentially malicious content, it's not only just ad
providers that I'm concerned with, but allowing large numbers of
arbitrary sites to run their scripts on your machine unchecked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the recent &lt;a href="http://www.zdnet.com/was-jquery-hacked-7000034009/"&gt;JQuery
compromise&lt;/a&gt;, for
instance. Fortunately, only the site itself was affected and &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; the
hosted libraries that many sites. It's not inconceivable that an
attacker may well deliberately go after to poison hosted libraries. It's
just way too big a jackpot for malware distributors to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if such an attack might be spotted quite quickly, how many users
could be affected in the interim? (I'm not even sure what the solution
is here; often JQuery's needed for sites to function as intended...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Minimising the number of third-party sites that you allow content to
load from can't be a bad thing. (There's some risk wherever you go, but
in some cases, I've seen sites loading in content from more sites than I
can count on both hands.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Controlling what your browser displays&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what can you do? There are browser extensions for Firefox and Chrome
that give you more control over what your browser loads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lots of sites are perfectly readable without them storing tracking
information about you, without arbitrary JavaScript running. For those
that don't, it's quite simple to whitelist them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The downside of this is that it can be a chore. In Firefox, I need a
slew of extensions to do this: which sites are allowed to run scripts
(NoScript), which cross-site requests are allowed (RequestPolicy), and
which sites can store cookies (CookieMonster).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing each one in turn, allowing permissions for cookies, scripts and
third-party scripts, can be tedious. I've run NoScript for a long time,
but these days with sites often hosting content and scripts somewhere
other than on the domain you're visiting, it's much more work than it
was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTTP Switchboard was a big, all encompassing project for Chromium-based
browsers that had features comparable to Adblock Plus, and the Firefox
extensions, NoScript, RequestPolicy. Recently, the &lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/httpswitchboard/issues/378"&gt;adblocking,
pattern-based filtering&lt;/a&gt;
has been split out into another project,
&lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/ublock"&gt;µblock&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;µblock&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By virtue of what HTTP Switchboard aims to do — give you full control of
what is allowed by your browser — this makes its user interface slightly
more complex, which I'll soon get onto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="article-image" src="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/images/2014/ublock.png" alt="The µblock enable/disable icon." width="174"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stripping out this sophistication seems like a smart move, since
µblock's incredibly easy to use. Really, it requires the same amount of
setup as Adblock Plus does: not much at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes with the most popular Adblock Plus filters accessible on
install, and you can easily choose which of those filter lists are
applied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disabling µblock for a site is also straightforward. Click the red µ
icon next to the address bar and then click the power icon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does the same job as Adblock Plus, but with lower CPU and memory
usage. If you've ditched an ad blocker for this reason, it's worth
looking at. Even if you're still happy using Adblock Plus (or one of its
forks), µblock is definitely worth spending the couple of minutes to try
it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;HTTP Switchboard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On to HTTP Switchboard, which allows fine grained control of the types
and locations of content that Chromium-based browser can access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that with the current version of HTTP Switchboard, there's a little
&lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/httpswitchboard/issues/378"&gt;initial setup&lt;/a&gt; to
disable the adblocking filtering that µBlock covers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HTTP Switchboard's interface can feel initially overwhelming; more so
than perhaps the likes of NoScript, RequestPolicy and CookieMonster that
I use which all have similar menus to allow or deny permission for a
site to run scripts or store cookies. These have a text explanation of
what the option does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="article-figure"&gt;
  &lt;img src="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/images/2014/Firefox_menus.png" alt="Examples of NoScript, CookieMonster and RequestPolicy permission menus."&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;From left to right, examples of NoScript, CookieMonster and RequestPolicy permission menus when accessing Google Books.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this menu format is, though it's explicit and clear,
it's cumbersome when you're dealing with several extensions. For each
extension, you need to repeat the process of whitelisting every site
that you're allowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you've actually used HTTP Switchboard for a few minutes, its
simplicity clicks. HTTP Switchboard opts for a table-like interface.
Each site is represented as a row, and each type of content is shown as
a column.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="article-figure"&gt;
  &lt;img src="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/images/2014/HTTP_Switchboard.png" alt="Example of HTTP Switchboard's table interface."&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Example of HTTP Switchboard's interface when accessing Google Books.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lets the user approve different permissions for different sites
quickly. Just read down the list of sites, click on those you want to
whitelist completely, and for those you don't you can allow specific
features only (e.g. loading images only). Likewise, if you want to
enable one type of content for all sites, just click the appropriate
column. If you want to save the permissions in future, click the padlock
icon, and you're done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It helps a lot that you can see &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the sites that are trying to
load content or save cookies in one glance, rather than consulting
separate menus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an autoreload option that refreshes the page when you change
permissions, so once you've approved everything needed, the page should
then work as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of the box, (I think) HTTP Switchboard was configured to allow most
requests through, apart from those blacklisted by filters. What
initially confused me was at what level the filters apply. (Do they
apply to this site? To this domain? globally?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'd recommend is, like the extension developer, is to
&lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/httpswitchboard/wiki/How-to-use-HTTP-Switchboard:-Two-opposing-views"&gt;block everything&lt;/a&gt;
by default and then whitelist only what you want to allow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an option in the HTTP Switchboard settings under "more security"
to create a new site-specific scope for every site you visit which is
really useful. This creates a set of rules for each site you visit.
Furthermore, the drop down (click the blue top-left box with the site
name in) lets you select where the rule applies (to the site, to the
domain or globally).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lets you block content from, say, a site like twitter.com when
you're visiting a third-party site, but allow it when you're directly
visiting Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also has some nice bonus privacy features, like removing HTTP
referers when visiting non-whitelisted sites and a user-agent
randomiser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing that's missing for me is guidance on what the sites
likely are. If you're happy to spend a few seconds researching, it's not
hard to figure this out. It might save a bit of time if there was a
database of sites telling you "hey, you might need this, it's a content
delivery network" or "this is tracking how you're using the site; you
probably don't need it for the site to function properly". Yes, I can
search, but it's a bit clunky to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are really great browser extensions, and credit to Raymond Hill
for an awesome job on them. Every time I'm managing permissions with
multiple extensions in Firefox now, I sigh a little. (Firefox's awesome
bar is far more useful to me than Chrome/ium's omnibox though, so I tend
to stick with Firefox.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Longer term, I'd really hope that a Firefox add-on developer &lt;a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock/issues/27"&gt;picks up
the baton to port these&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(As a postscript, I should point out that as well as adblocking and
control over requests, &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/https-everywhere"&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/a&gt;
is another useful privacy-enhancing extension for Firefox and Chromium
browsers. Where HTTPS browsing is available on sites but not always used,
HTTPS Everywhere enables it for you.)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="ad"></category><category term="µblock"></category><category term="HTTP Switchboard"></category><category term="blocking"></category><category term="privacy"></category><category term="adblock"></category></entry><entry><title>Updating and rooting Moto G</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/updating-and-rooting-moto-g" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-08-25T18:34:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2014-08-25:posts/updating-and-rooting-moto-g</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;My Moto G has been nagging me to upgrade firmware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I did today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I was persuaded by the Motorola system updater. Not because it's a
lovely looking bit of software, but because it makes nagging an art with
its focus-stealing prompt. If you go for the "no" option, your phone
kindly reminds you again in an hour &lt;strong&gt;every hour&lt;/strong&gt;, just in case you've
forgotten. This is regardless of what you're doing at the time, even if
you're say using Google Maps for driving navigation which is quite
hideous. Even the option to postpone the reminder for a week or a month
would be nice. A rubbish, rubbish, rubbish user experience.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A simple upgrade is as easy as pressing "upgrade". Because my phone was
rooted and encrypted, the upgrade was likely to fail, so I had to
restore it to stock firmware first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I wanted to then reroot it so that I could use
&lt;a href="https://github.com/M66B/XPrivacy"&gt;XPrivacy&lt;/a&gt;. This lets you restrict the
permissions that apps have. Google did have App Ops in Android which did
a similar thing (without quite as much granularity, I believe) but
promptly removed it. It would have been good of them to leave it in: it
would have removed one reason I have for rooting. Android apps are just
far more intrusive in their permissions than they usually need to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, I don't want Twitter's app to access my contacts, thanks; I'm more
than capable of finding people on Twitter directly. No, there's no
reason for Soundhound to know where I am. No, even if my phone &lt;strong&gt;had&lt;/strong&gt;
NFC, I don't want F-Droid to be able to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The assessment
&lt;a href="http://www.cnet.com/news/why-android-wont-be-getting-app-ops-anytime-soon/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
is that one big reason for the removal of App Ops is due to it breaking
apps. I disagree with that though. Using XPrivacy, I restrict almost
every app and haven't had any trouble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can understand that if app permission controls were enabled by
default, there's the possibility that it could cause problems for users
that don't understand the implications of allowing/denying permissions,
but if it was something like the developer options where you have to
deliberately enable it, then they wouldn't even know it was present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here are the reference notes I made while upgrading for (the
inevitable) next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preliminary setup with Ubuntu&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(or your choice of a Linux that has &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;fastboot&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install (to a live USB, or use an existing install on your laptop)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable third party repositories in "Software and Updates".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do &lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get update&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install android-tools-adb android-tools-fastboot&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Backup data from phone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copy off any photos, documents or other files you want to save.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to backup your call logs and text messages, Call Logs Backup
and Restore, and SMS Backup and Restore work pretty well for me. That
said, they do request internet permissions which I block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Restore stock firmware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stock firmwares are available
&lt;a href="http://sbf.droid-developers.org/phone.php?device=14"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://forum.xda-developers.com/showthread.php?t=2542219"&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt; was a
useful reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boot into the bootloader using power on and volume down key (or enable
USB debugging mode when the phone's on normally and do
&lt;code&gt;adb reboot-bootloader&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo fastboot flash partition gpt.bin
sudo fastboot flash motoboot motoboot.img
sudo fastboot flash logo logo.bin
sudo fastboot flash boot boot.img
sudo fastboot flash recovery recovery.img
sudo fastboot flash system system.img_sparsechunk1
sudo fastboot flash system system.img_sparsechunk2
sudo fastboot flash system system.img_sparsechunk3
sudo fastboot flash modem NON-HLOS.bin
sudo fastboot erase modemst1
sudo fastboot erase modemst2
sudo fastboot flash fsg fsg.mbn
sudo fastboot erase cache
sudo fastboot erase userdata
sudo fastboot reboot
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(sparsechunk files may have numbers 0, 1, 2 - just flash them in
ascending order.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Upgrade&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boot into stock and install update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To avoid heartache&lt;/strong&gt;, make sure you check for system updates
&lt;strong&gt;after&lt;/strong&gt; you update, and install any further updates before
proceeding. Repeat until no update is found. Otherwise, like me, you may
discover after rooting again that there are still updates remaining
after the first one. In that case, you'll have to restore to stock again
:( (I was on 4.4.2, but there was a minor update that didn't change the
version before the latest 4.4.4 update.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Unlock bootloader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Only needed if not previously unlocked; while restoring stock
firmware and upgrading, this didn't get relocked. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need a bootloader unlock code from Motorola's
&lt;a href="https://motorola-global-portal.custhelp.com/app/standalone/bootloader/unlock-your-device-a"&gt;site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;fastboot oem unlock
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Boot into fastboot mode: Enable developer mode again in settings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;adb reboot bootloader
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Optional: get a copy of the original Motorola logo and do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo fastboot flash logo original_logo.bin
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;to remove the annoying "bootloader is unlocked" warning at boot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href="http://wiki.cyanogenmod.org/w/Template:Unlock_Bootloader"&gt;CyanogenMod's
site&lt;/a&gt; for more
details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Install custom recovery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get custom recovery; &lt;a href="http://teamw.in/project/twrp2/233"&gt;I used TWRP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get a recent fastboot .img; at the time of writing, 2.7.1.1 was the
latest, but didn't work. 2.7.1.0 worked fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install through bootloader using fastboot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo fastboot flash recovery modified_recovery.img
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Root the phone by installing SuperSU&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boot from bootloader into TWRP recovery. Reboot system, say yes to
install SuperSU.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boot up, run SuperSU installer; go to Play Store and choose &lt;strong&gt;update&lt;/strong&gt;
(&lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; open).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will probably prompt to install a new binary; the normal install
should work fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Install XPrivacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install XPrivacy installer. Follow each of the several instruction steps
that are shown when you run it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Encrypt and change password again&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a screen lock PIN or password, then fully charge battery and
encrypt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change the password using &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.nick.cryptfs.passwdmanager&amp;amp;hl=en"&gt;Cryptfs
Password&lt;/a&gt;
so that you can have a separate screen unlock code and encryption passphrase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This is another good reason to root your phone. Without this, your
encryption password is identical to your screen unlock code. Unless you
want to have either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a weak password, or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a huge password that you have to enter every time you unlock your phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you'll need to change it using CryptFS which requires root access.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Disable all the slow animations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make Android snappier, disable the animations by enabling the
developer options. Go in Settings &gt; About phone, scroll to the bottom
and keep pressing build number until it tells you the developer options
are active. Now, in Settings &gt; Developer options, you can set "Window
animation scale", "Transition animation scale" and "Animator duration
scale" all to off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Restore data, account, messages, call logs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reinstall SMS Backup and Restore, Call Log Backup and Restore, and
restore the backups you made. Reinstall any other apps you want,
including &lt;a href="https://f-droid.org/"&gt;F-Droid&lt;/a&gt; if you want AdAway and that's
everything finally done. No more nagging for updates!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Moto"></category><category term="firmware"></category><category term="upgrade"></category><category term="Android"></category><category term="system"></category><category term="root"></category></entry><entry><title>My wifi's connected, but there's no internet...? (Intel Centrino versus Ubuntu)</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/my-wifis-connected-but-theres-no" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-29T23:15:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2014-07-29:posts/my-wifis-connected-but-theres-no</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Intel Outside (of my own office)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I've never had too much of a problem with on my Ubuntu 12.04
LTS install is networking. There's been the odd time when it's refused
to connect to the network, despite everything else being fine. This has
always been fixed with a reboot, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem I experienced today was a lot more serious. I'd travelled to
another office to work and tried to connect to their wifi. I knew the
network should have been OK as no-one else seemed to be having an issue,
and I'd entered the WPA password correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I saw was that the wifi showed as connected, but I couldn't connect
to anything. Occasionally, I could try and ping a server, and when I
bothered to wait long enough to see anything, what I saw was connection
timeouts, horrible packet loss, and ping times of several &lt;strong&gt;seconds&lt;/strong&gt;.
(Pings are normally measured in milliseconds; I was seeing results of
&lt;strong&gt;thousands&lt;/strong&gt; of milliseconds.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd never seen this problem before. It quickly became apparent that this
was specific to my hardware and my Ubuntu install. When I booted into
Windows, it connected immediately without any problem, and a colleague
was using a later version of Ubuntu on different hardware without a
problem at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's certainly difficult to try to fix such a vague problem. Running
searches like "wifi not connecting on Ubuntu" inevitably brings up much
noise relating to every wireless problem out there and not anything much
of relevance, but I didn't have a lot more to go on. Having to do lots
of searching and skimming through web pages using a phone to search
isn't ideal either, but it did eventually lead me to the right answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fun with &lt;code&gt;iwlwifi&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What worked was searching for issues relating to the wifi driver
(&lt;code&gt;iwlwifi&lt;/code&gt;). A common theme that came up was &lt;code&gt;11n_disable=1&lt;/code&gt; which is a
modprobe option that disables the wireless N feature of the Intel
wireless adapter. (&lt;code&gt;lshw -C network&lt;/code&gt; states the model is "Centrino
Wireless-N 2230".)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By running the commands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo rmmod iwldvm
sudo rmmod iwlwifi
sudo modprobe iwlwifi &lt;span class="nv"&gt;11n_disable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;1
sudo modprobe iwldvm
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got normal wireless access back (minus wireless N speeds, but the
choice between fast, but no wifi and slow wifi is not a difficult one to
make).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;rmmod&lt;/code&gt; commands remove the modules from the kernel, while
&lt;code&gt;modprobe&lt;/code&gt; adds them. We need to readd the wifi module with wireless N
disabled. (The offending module is &lt;code&gt;iwlwifi&lt;/code&gt; but I couldn't &lt;code&gt;rmmod&lt;/code&gt; it
until I'd removed &lt;code&gt;iwldvm&lt;/code&gt; as trying to do so showed that &lt;code&gt;iwldvm&lt;/code&gt; was
using &lt;code&gt;iwlwifi&lt;/code&gt;. There is a force option for &lt;code&gt;rmmod&lt;/code&gt; but it didn't seem
sensible to use it when there was an alternative.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making this fix stick&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want this fix to apply every time you boot, you can just create a
new &lt;code&gt;.conf&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;/etc/modprobe.d/wireless-n-fix-iwlwifi.conf&lt;/code&gt;, adding just this line to
the file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;options iwlwifi &lt;span class="nv"&gt;11n_disable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Thanks to this &lt;a href="http://askubuntu.com/questions/119578/how-to-fix-slow-wireless-on-machines-with-intel-wireless-cards"&gt;nice
summary&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can choose any valid filename you like, provided it ends in &lt;code&gt;.conf&lt;/code&gt;;
you'll also need to edit this using &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; and your favourite text
editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why hadn't I seen this problem before?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What seems to be the issue is that I think that the office was using a
wireless N router, and there's some kind of issue with this for the
Intel Centrino wireless network adapter on my laptop under Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowhere else I've been with this laptop seems to be using wireless N, so
that explains why it was an issue for the first time today. It's pretty
poor that this seems to have been a &lt;a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu/+source/linux/+bug/1034740"&gt;long-running
problem&lt;/a&gt; and
yet it's still present... but at least there's a workaround.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="connection"></category><category term="Centrino"></category><category term="wifi"></category><category term="Ubuntu"></category><category term="Intel"></category><category term="fix"></category></entry><entry><title>Arduous lessons in Python: why main() is useful</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/arduous-lessons-in-python-why-main-is" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-07-05T11:42:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2014-07-05:posts/arduous-lessons-in-python-why-main-is</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="article-image" src="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/images/2014/python_logo.png" alt="The Python logo."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ordinary afternoon and I'd wanted to work on some code locally on my
machine. I knew the tests previously ran without any issue. So, after
I'd cloned the repository locally, I ran &lt;code&gt;nosetests&lt;/code&gt; to make sure
everything was OK with my setup before I started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I expected is the tests to run pretty quickly as before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened instead is that Python started hogging a CPU and I saw a
lonely blinking cursor where I expected my test results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something was happening, but none of the tests were seemingly running.
That is, I wasn't seeing any pass/fail indicators, which was strange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What actually happened&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something was running that evidently wasn't what I intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On inspection, one of the import statements in the test code had a
structure somewhat like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;some_function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;some&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;things&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;another_function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;some&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;other&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;things&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;really_long_winded_scraping_function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;lots&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;things&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;really_long_winded_scraping_function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind that when you import a module, the statements are actually
executed. If you've just got function and class definitions in there,
then this means that they get defined, but they aren't executed until
you call them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if functions are called in the module's flow of execution, then
they'll be called when you import it too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when this module was being imported by the test module, the
&lt;code&gt;really_long_winded_scraping_function()&lt;/code&gt; was being called. So, yes,
eventually, the tests would have run, but they'd run &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the code in
the &lt;code&gt;import&lt;/code&gt; had finished, which would have taken &lt;strong&gt;hours&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fixing the problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally, I routinely use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;__name__&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;__main__&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;in Python code that I start writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/2/tutorial/modules.html"&gt;official
documentation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Within a module, the module’s name (as a string) is available as the
value of the global variable &lt;code&gt;__name__&lt;/code&gt;."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it also does is assigns &lt;code&gt;'__main__'&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;__name__&lt;/code&gt; if the module is
being executed directly. This gives you a way to specify different
behaviour depending on whether the module itself is run or just
imported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're importing the module to reuse the code elsewhere, you can then
just access the relevant functions and classes that you need, rather
than running code that actually starts doing things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, for some reason, we'd just quickly thrown some functions
together, then found that the function that actually initiates all of
the scraping wasn't being called. So, we'd just quickly added a call to
what was our at the bottom of the module, set the code going to do the
scraping and not run the tests again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was fine, until I forgot about this and came to run the tests again
later! It's a good case for running your tests regularly; the reason it
took me so long was that we hadn't run the tests since getting the main
code working. If we had, I think I'd have been more likely to spot the
connection between our fix to the code and the tests taking an age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This isn't a test specific problem. You'd notice it whenever you
imported the code into another module. It just happened to be that the
tests were the only other module that we'd imported the code into.)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="foolishness"></category><category term="name"></category><category term="main"></category><category term="Python"></category><category term="fix"></category></entry><entry><title>Chatting about data science careers</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/chatting-about-data-science-careers" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-06-22T21:47:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2014-06-22:posts/chatting-about-data-science-careers</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Visiting Cambridge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="article-image" src="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/images/2014/Cambridge_1.jpg" alt="A photo of a street in Cambridge" width=300&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visited Cambridge this week. Though I know Oxford fairly well, somehow
I'd manage to avoid ever travelling to Cambridge before, so being in a
lovely city and surrounded by things new to me (though mostly far older
than me) was a pleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what was I even doing there anyway? The university careers service
was holding an event for postdoctoral researchers to find out more about
paths outside of university. I'd been invited to talk about data
science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day started with brief talks from the careers staff and one of the
guests. In a short session, they divulged several ideas that I'd taken
far longer to collect either from reading around, the careers programme
I attended last year, or by a slow realisation during my career
searching process last year.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a brief session where I and the other nine invited speakers
introduced themselves to everyone, the rest of the day was spent talking
with small groups of postdocs. Much discussion seemed to centre around
what my work involves, and how I eventually found my job.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of event seems a great way for people to get inspired about
what kind of careers they could consider a move into, especially if
they're at a crossroads where all the exits are hazy. I think they can
also provide a helpful confidence boost at a time when anxiety and
indecision can easily take hold. If you're chatting with someone who's
been in your shoes recently and managed to make a successful career
move, why shouldn't you believe that you can replicate it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A positive for me was that a few of the people I spoke to were already
looking into data science as a career. And I'm also hoping that I
managed to encourage those who, on speaking to them, seemed like they
definitely had relevant skills, but they weren't entirely sure whether
it was an option for them to explore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PhDs moving from research to industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were two thoughts that I took away from the event. First, contrary
to my preconceptions, it seemed that from the experiences of some of the
other speakers that a long stay in university research wasn't perhaps as
detrimental as I expected. In other words, you're not "trapped" at
university if you have spent several years as a postdoc. (Though if
you've already made up your mind to leave, it was mentioned that it's
advisable to plan your exit as soon as possible.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other idea that I heard a couple of times is that there seems to be
a disconnect between employers looking for well qualified PhDs and the
candidates themselves. The jobs are there. The candidates are there.
But, for whatever reason, they're missing each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="article-image" src="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/images/2014/Cambridge_2.jpg" alt="Another photo taken in Cambridge."&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From my experience as a researcher, I'd suggest a part of the problem is
that PhDs and postdocs may be simply unaware of the range of
opportunities available to them. For data science at least, there are
several organisations whose specific goal is to help transition science
PhDs into employment. This is fine, but that's covers one discipline and
small groups of fortunate researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it's also a problem of communicating across this gap. Researchers
are perhaps underequipped to successively sell themselves to employers,
and maybe industry employers are not making it clear when PhDs with
strong analytical backgrounds are exactly who they're looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I'm sure the researchers attending took away some good
ideas. It was definitely a productive and fun day out, and gave me the
unusual opportunity to take a bit of time out to reflect on where I am
in my career move. Thanks to Anne Forde of Cambridge University's
Careers Service and Kim Nilsson of &lt;a href="http://s2ds.org/"&gt;S2DS&lt;/a&gt; for inviting
me to participate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A great idea that was highlighted is to just look through postings on
sites which are advertising jobs (maybe Nature Jobs, New Scientist if
you've a science background and want to stay in science, and further
afield otherwise) and investigate lots of jobs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, another point that was emphasised, which is really important, is
&lt;em&gt;don't dismiss yourself&lt;/em&gt; as being unsuitable for a job based on the
title alone. You may find that you're already more than capable of
meeting the candidate requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More specifically, small bits of wisdom such as
these. Figuring out what you like in your current work, what your
strengths are and what your priorities in work are. Having these things
clear in your mind really does help you filter prospective jobs or
workplaces to those that you're more likely to be interested in. It's
easy for the panic of "I need a job" to settle in, and to then focus on
applying for vacancies, rather than going the perhaps necessary process
of self-discovery instead.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One good question that came up a couple of times
and I didn't have an instinctive answer for was: how do the longer term
careers of data scientists progress? My excuse was that I'd just started
out in my career and data science is still relatively new. Kim also
mentioned that she saw lots of opportunities to specialise and find a
niche.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it shouldn't have surprised me so much.
Checking over my own notes from last year, those were the main questions
I was asking the data scientists that I chatted to in informational
interviews.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="data"></category><category term="careers"></category><category term="university"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="science"></category><category term="Cambridge"></category></entry><entry><title>52 weeks, 52 posts</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/52-weeks-52-posts" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-10T17:52:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2014-05-10:posts/52-weeks-52-posts</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A year ago, I started writing this blog. I didn't really have any
expectations of what I wanted to get out of it, but I think it's been
successful despite my lack of lofty ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, I hadn't written any blog back then. So it's a little strange
that in the past year, I've had blog posts on another two other blogs
aside from this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been quite a busy year too, so I've been sporadic in posting.
Saying 52 posts in 52 weeks might sound well disciplined, but you can
see that there have been weeks when I've not found time to write
anything. (Which is a little lazy of me.) Other times I've been more
inspired and written in bursts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, the fact I've still returned to it even after several weeks
away is certainly auspicious. What I think I've got out of it is that
I'm much more conscientious about scribbling notes down for my own
reference, which I seldom did before having a blog. This has proven to
be a useful reference. If I can't quite remember how I did something,
but know it's on here, I can find it quickly. If I do write up things on
here, it's because it was a problem that I didn't see an obvious answer
to and took more than a cursory internet search or investigation on my
own part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as that more practical side, it's been a good excuse to work on
my writing (a muscle that I don't often flex at work).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about the coming year then? In this next year, two resolutions that
I'd like to keep are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to try and maintain at least some kind of regularity to posting
    (even if my posts are clustered together sometimes) and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;migrate this blog to Pelican or something similar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For what it's worth, I started looking into the second. It's just a
matter of ensuring I put the slight effort into seeing it through.
Deciding what to do about comments, and actually going about exporting
my existing content to Markdown or RestructuredText are the obstacles at
the moment. Really though, it's a question of &lt;strong&gt;just doing it&lt;/strong&gt; rather
than procrastinating and getting distracted writing blog posts about how
I'm going to do things.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="self-indulgence"></category><category term="musings"></category></entry></feed>