<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>stevenmaude.co.uk</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/</id><updated>2016-04-20T20:30:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Taking web page screenshots smartly with Firefox's Developer Tools</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/taking-web-page-screenshots-smartly-with-firefoxs-developer-tools" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-20T20:30:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2016-04-20:posts/taking-web-page-screenshots-smartly-with-firefoxs-developer-tools</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Snap happy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firefox has a buried feature in its Developer Tools, which is potentially
useful even if you're not a developer. If you've never used the Developer
Tools, just press F12 and you'll see the tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should see a cog icon towards the upper right of the pane that's just
displayed. The cog is on the same row as the Inspector, Console etc. buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clicking this displays a page of options that you can use to customise the
Developer Tools. By ticking "Take a fullpage screenshot" under "Available
Toolbox Buttons", you should see a camera icon appear near the cog icon you
previously clicked. Selecting this gives you a screenshot of the page where you
opened the Developer Tools. The resulting PNG file can be found in your Firefox
Downloads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a really handy feature. It means that you can take an image of a
scrollable page that's &lt;strong&gt;larger&lt;/strong&gt; than your current window. No need for
screenshotting parts of the page then joining them together by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Solving bigger problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if you want to enlarge the visible area beyond the size of your
current window, and then take a screenshot?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why would this be even useful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say that you want a screenshot of a web page displaying a map, where the
map expands to fill your browser window. And let's say that you want the
screenshot to cover a larger area than fits into the largest browser window you
can have on your desktop. Just expanding the window isn't going to give you the
size that you need.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can you do this? If you hover over the toolbox icons in the Developer Tools
panel, near to the cog, you should be able to find the Responsive Design mode.
(It's a very small, dotted rectangle inside a larger, thicker rectangle.) Click
this. Your display will change to have a border and extra options appear. The
selected resolution is shown above the display. Clicking on the resolution
dropdown menu, you can directly type the resolution you want this preview
display to have and press Enter to have it take effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that's left is to take a screenshot again using the "Take a fullpage
screenshot" option in the Developer Tools toolbox. (Note that Responsive
Design mode has its own screenshot tool, near to the resolution menu,
but this only takes an image of the page visible within the display
window you've just set, i.e.  it's not necessarily the full page if
there would still be scroll bars at that actual display resolution
you've selected.)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Firefox"></category><category term="screenshot"></category></entry><entry><title>Managing a Bitbucket user's permissions when they've left your team</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/managing-a-bitbucket-users-permissions-when-theyve-left-your-team" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-16T01:54:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2016-04-16:posts/managing-a-bitbucket-users-permissions-when-theyve-left-your-team</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Kicking the Bitbucket&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I noticed this week is that users who'd left a Bitbucket team&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
that I'm currently a member of were still billed as having admin access
to several repositories. But, this wasn't by virtue of being a team
member, as we'd removed them.  Instead, this was via their own user
accounts. This seems like the intended behaviour. It's documented
&lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/site/master/issues/5148/repos-transferred-to-a-team-retain-creator#comment-22446820"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:
a user gets admin access to the repository when they create it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tested this by just creating a new repository that was owned by the
team. Checking the access management settings showed that the team was
the owner of the repository, but I had separate admin permissions for
the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've got the required permissions yourself, you can go and clean up
user access on a repository basis, via that same repository access
management settings. A short look around — though short does mean very
short, admittedly — for suitable bits of the API that would let me purge
old users without having to manually click through each repository
didn't reveal anything. Click, click, click seemed the only way to fix
it. And if you have a lot of repositories, that's a lot of clicking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stop it (and tidy up)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking now at this late hour, it seems that I was looking in entirely
the wrong place previously. A much, much quicker route to cleaning up is
to browse to your team's page and select "Manage team". From there, look
at "Plan details". There you can see exactly who has access to your
team's repositories and what access type they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might be "group". That is, because they're part of a user group in
your team — groups are another aspect of access management, you can be
in the team, but maybe you're in a group that maybe doesn't have access
to any team repositories at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A user's access type can also be "repository", i.e. they have access
because their user account has explicitly set permissions on that
repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clicking "View access" shows you which team repositories they can
access. Next to "View access", there's a cross icon that you can click
to remove &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; the user's permissions from your team. In just one
click. What happens if you do that for a user that's still on the team?
I can't answer that; maybe it boots them out of the team too? (I wasn't
about to try it.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A potentially money saving tip&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's sensible to keep access permissions to your repositories to a
minimum to ensure that only users who need access have it. Of course, it
may be that you have equally sensible reasons to retain access for
ex-team members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it's also worth considering how Bitbucket counts users in your
team's plan. The definition of users on the Bitbucket plan details page
is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of users (including you) with any level of access to one or
more of your private repos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is whether they are a formal team member or not&lt;/strong&gt;. (Team members
without repository access don't count here.) So, this spring cleaning
might allow you to switch to a cheaper Bitbucket plan for your team too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organisation in GitHub parlance.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Bitbucket"></category></entry><entry><title>The case of a Windows 7 update, Secure Boot and a suspect motherboard</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/the-case-of-a-windows-7-update-secure-boot-and-a-suspect-motherboard" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-12T00:33:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2016-04-12:posts/the-case-of-a-windows-7-update-secure-boot-and-a-suspect-motherboard</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Because, obviously, I have nothing I'd rather do than try to fathom how Secure
Boot works on a Monday evening, I'm writing this up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you're experiencing this problem right now. Maybe you're not, but you're
intrigued as to how I go about diagnosing computer problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A stubborn PC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I maintain a PC that has Windows 7 installed (due to be upgraded to Windows 10)
and, yesterday evening, installed several optional updates.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Nothing unusual
there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A day later, an owner of the machine restarted it. Except, well, the PC
refused.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead it said this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The system found unauthorized changes on the firmware, operating system or
UEFI drivers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmm. That's certainly not good since it's related to &lt;a href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-GB/library/hh824987.aspx"&gt;Secure
Boot&lt;/a&gt;'s check of
boot integrity. Warily, I disabled Secure Boot in the BIOS to get the machine
to boot Windows, and checked the System Event Log.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking around the log, it turns out that the last time that the machine had
previously successfully started was just before I installed the updates, which
is consistent with what had happened. As the PC was fine until that point, it
ruled out anything malicious, and pointed to the update as being a likely
candidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having looked through the list of recently installed updates, most of them
seemed fairly routine, except &lt;a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-gb/kb/3133977"&gt;the KB3133977 update for a Bitlocker
issue&lt;/a&gt;. What stood out were the
changes to Windows Boot Manager files &lt;code&gt;Bootmgr.efi&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Bootmgfw.efi&lt;/code&gt;, which
also suggested the update was at fault.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;ASUSpect?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searching around led me to several recent links, as I mentioned in comments on
this &lt;a href="https://superuser.com/questions/1054790/system-found-unauthorized-changes-on-the-firmware"&gt;SuperUser
question&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In those posts, Windows users were reporting the same issue: the BIOS
complaining that there was an unauthorised change. This being a relatively new
issue isn't surprising as the update was only released on March 14th, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ASUS being the motherboard manufacturer seems to be common to those
experiencing the problem. It seems to affect different models; here it's a
H87-PRO. Even then it's unclear what the root cause is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;maybe ASUS motherboards are the only ones that allow you to enable Secure
Boot with Windows 7?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;maybe there's something unusual with the signing process of this update that
only affected ASUS motherboards?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or maybe it's just a coincidence? (But, it's odd that it's a common link in
several cases. You'd think if users with other motherboards would have been
affected, they'd have mentioned it too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As linked above, Microsoft's site suggests Secure Boot is supported on Windows
8 and up, and I can't find any documentation to suggest Secure Boot should work
on Windows 7. It's possible that this is just behaviour out of specification
that didn't cause any problem until now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(It's a while ago since I installed the PC, but I guess that I originally must
have tried turning on Secure Boot during installation and, since the PC booted
without a problem, left it enabled.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other posts I'd read indicated that removing KB3133977 didn't solve this.
Perhaps there are EFI changes that don't get reverted when you uninstall the
update? Who knows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, restoring a previous system backup fixes the issue. You could then
leave everything as is, but have to make sure that you don't install this
update (hiding it would work). This is inconvenient then, but fine provided you
have regular backups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, but the update might actually fix a problem you're experiencing with
Bitlocker. In which case, you're going to have to install it regardless then,
aren't you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another solution is to disable Secure Boot in the BIOS. That's not a perfect
solution though, especially if you're booting other operating systems that work
with Secure Boot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's always possible, but unlikely, that Microsoft could reissue the update and
enabling the Secure Boot option might be possible again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of that explains completely what happened, but that's at least enough to
hopefully stop you panicking and make your Windows install accessible, if
you've been affected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What fun will today's later batch of updates brings, I wonder?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One more thing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I wondered what happens if you disable Secure Boot, then do an
in-place upgrade of Windows in this situation, where we can't enable Secure
Boot? Can you later enable it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hunch is that you should be able to, provided your operating system was
installed when your BIOS was in UEFI mode. With the ASUS motherboard I was
looking at, if you were doing an in-place upgrade in this particularly strange
case, I think you'd need to clear the Secure Boot keys to disable Secure Boot
while allowing UEFI (otherwise you wouldn't be able to boot Windows 7).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the upgrade's complete, I'd then expect I could go back to the BIOS and
install the default Secure Boot keys, which should let you set Secure Boot
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously, I had recommended updates set to automatically install, but
unfortunately it's now necessary to make sure you don't &lt;a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windowsexperience/2015/10/29/making-it-easier-to-upgrade-to-windows-10/"&gt;inadvertently install
Windows 10&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Windows"></category><category term="Secure Boot"></category></entry><entry><title>Firefox keyword searches, and how to fix adding them</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/firefox-keyword-searches-and-how-to-fix-adding-them" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-04-03T17:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2016-04-03:posts/firefox-keyword-searches-and-how-to-fix-adding-them</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What are keyword searches?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keyword searches, or quick searches, are really handy when browsing. If
you think of something that you want to search for, they remove the
extra step of first navigating to the site and selecting the search box. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you can just directly enter your query into your address bar,
preceded by some keyword. For instance, if I look up "Ubuntu" on
&lt;a href="https://duckduckgo.com"&gt;DuckDuckGo&lt;/a&gt;, I can just hit Ctrl+L to access
the address bar, type &lt;code&gt;d Ubuntu&lt;/code&gt; and hit enter, to directly access the
page of search results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How keyword searches save time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might not seem like a big time saving, but when you consider that
you have to repeat the same process for every site you search on, it
soon adds up. It's a feature you can use not only with traditional
search engines, but with most sites that have a search box. One example
is YouTube, I'll often — maybe &lt;strong&gt;too&lt;/strong&gt; often — type &lt;code&gt;yt Yet another timewasting
distraction&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating and using custom keyword searches in Firefox&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is really simple to do. You're really just adding a bookmark, but
one that refers to whatever URL the search box will send you to, not the
page itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right click a search box on a webpage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select "Add a Keyword for this Search..."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the dialogue that opens, enter a keyword and the search URL is
   then added to your bookmarks with a placeholder for a query.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you next type that keyword followed by a search query into the
   address bar, the bookmark gets loaded with your query automatically inserted
   into the URL.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These keyword searches are normal bookmarks; you can edit them like any
other bookmark. The only difference is that they contain the &lt;code&gt;%s&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Printf_format_string"&gt;placeholder&lt;/a&gt; in the
URL. When you carry out a keyword search, the term following the keyword
replaces the &lt;code&gt;%s&lt;/code&gt; in the bookmark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're browsing through your bookmarks in the Library, you'll only
see "Name", "Location" and "Tags", but if you click "More", you'll see
(and can change) the keyword you've set too. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This all works because, as you've probably noticed, using a search
option on a site usually sends you to a URL that contains the search
term. Hopefully you can see that if you construct the URL without even
visiting the site first, that this should still work. That said, this
assumes that the site uses GET requests where the query is contained in
the URL itself.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But my keyword searches aren't being added?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I find them so useful, I sorely missed it when recently, for whatever
reason, Firefox decided that it wouldn't add them any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bookmark would get created, but the keyword I added didn't get
saved. Even if I manually edited the bookmark, I could enter a keyword
but on navigating away to another bookmark and back again, the keyword
would be lost again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple fix was just to exit Firefox, locate &lt;code&gt;places.sqlite&lt;/code&gt; inside
the Firefox profile directory,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; rename &lt;code&gt;places.sqlite&lt;/code&gt;, and let the
file be rebuilt on the next restart (as documented in &lt;a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/cant-add-change-or-save-bookmarks"&gt;Mozilla's support
pages&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation states that you lose history, but any bookmarks are
rebuilt from a backup. Once you're happy everything's OK, you can delete
the old &lt;code&gt;places.sqlite&lt;/code&gt;. After that, new keyword searches were added
without a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its location depends on &lt;a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/profiles-where-firefox-stores-user-data"&gt;your operating system&lt;/a&gt;.
For me, on Linux, it was in the hidden &lt;code&gt;~/.mozilla/firefox&lt;/code&gt;. On
Windows, it'll be in &lt;code&gt;%APPDATA%\Mozilla\Firefox\Profiles\&lt;/code&gt;. Make sure
that you're in the correct profile directory, if you have multiple
Firefox profiles.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Firefox"></category><category term="keyword search"></category><category term="quick search"></category></entry><entry><title>Answers to some Windows 10 activation questions</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/answers-to-some-windows-10-activation-questions" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-12T22:23:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2016-01-12:posts/answers-to-some-windows-10-activation-questions</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With a Windows 10 1511 Threshold 2 ISO that I downloaded (using the
&lt;a href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/getting-an-official-windows-10-disk-image"&gt;source I've previously
described&lt;/a&gt;),
I was recently testing out Windows 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Threshold 2 release was the first major release of Windows 10 since
launch and was made available in November 2015. Previously, the route to
claiming the free Windows 10 upgrade from an existing version of Windows
was to do an in-place upgrade from a current install. The Threshold 2
release changes this so that you can enter a Windows 7 or 8 product key
on a clean install of Windows 10 and successfully activate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I still had a lot of questions about how the activation process
worked and, probably because Threshold 2 is still fairly new, I couldn't
find much to tell me how this was actually going to work out. Here's
what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What happens if you clean install Windows 10 on a PC with an embedded Windows licence?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, Windows licences for mass produced consumer systems are
usually included in the BIOS itself, rather than printed on a sticker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the Windows 10 install does is automatically installs and activates
the corresponding Windows 10 version if your hardware has an embedded
licence. (Pro if your laptop had a Win 7 Pro/Ultimate or Win 8 Pro
licence, or Home if you had a Win 7/8 Home licence.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that this is still counted as part of the free upgrade
entitlement rather than offered in perpetuity, so won't be an option
once Microsoft's free upgrade offer expires in July 2016. You'll
probably have to pay for an upgrade then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Can you use a Windows 8/8.1 Pro Pack key to claim a Windows 10 Pro upgrade?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. You can go to "change product key" and try entering your key, but
you'll probably see the error &lt;code&gt;0xc004f210&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because you're on Home, not Pro, so the key's not valid for that
version of Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What works instead is to use the &lt;a href="https://answers.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/forum/windows_10-windows_install/windows-10-pro-becomes-home-after-reinstallation/f1d7d4e5-cdf6-4fd7-b0e7-f87084b73df8"&gt;generic Pro
key&lt;/a&gt;
which will then install the Pro upgrade. Your Windows install will then
show as not being activated as it only had a Home licence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, entering that Pro Pack key should activate without any problem, I
think, provided that it was previously used on the same hardware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clarifying this with how this worked for me might help explain this
process if it's still somewhat unclear. My laptop had a Windows 8 Home
licence which got upgraded to Windows 10 Home automatically on install.
Then, I changed the product key to the generic Pro key. Following the
Pro upgrade, the Windows 8 Pro Pack key that I'd previously used on the
same laptop activated Windows 10 Pro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Can you clean install Windows 10 Pro on a laptop which has an embedded Home licence?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've activated Windows 10, you get a digital entitlement. Any
product key you first used to activate is no longer needed: in future,
the Windows activation servers just check your hardware and see that you
have a valid licence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue here is that — &lt;strong&gt;even if your hardware has a entitlement for
the Pro version&lt;/strong&gt; — if the hardware has a key for a Home version, that
will be recognised on install and you'll end up with a Home version
install.  You'd then have to enter the generic Pro key and hopefully
your PC should activate without a problem then, since it should have the
digital entitlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is inconvenient: it does mean you don't get a clean Pro install,
but one that's upgraded from Home to Pro (though in practice there's
probably little difference between these two routes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't tested this, but as far as I can tell, the solution is to
&lt;a href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/hh824952.aspx"&gt;modify the installer disk
image&lt;/a&gt; with a
text file that contains a product key. If you use the generic Pro key,
you should get the Pro version installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, you could enter your Windows 7/8 product key as described
above or, if reinstalling, the digital entitlement should allow you to
activate without entering any product key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First impressions of Windows 10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I've noticed that the start menu is an improvement on Windows 8,
but not as good as the one in Windows 7, the default theme is awful to
look at compared with Windows 7's Aero — it's far too white and bright,
with very little contrast in Explorer and Control Panel windows — and
that there are lots of telemetry tracking and unwanted bundled software
(e.g. OneDrive) to remove. There is a &lt;a href="https://technet.microsoft.com/en-us/library/mt577208%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"&gt;Microsoft guide on how to do
so&lt;/a&gt;.
Set aside some time. It's a lengthy read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Activation confusion aside, Windows 10 installed without a problem. The
installation process has been streamlined to require very little
interaction beyond picking install language. Another pleasant surprise
was that every piece of built-in laptop hardware had drivers installed
automatically which saves a lot of delving into badly designed
manufacturer websites to retrieve them. Even on Windows 7, a clean
install would usually result in a lot of small pieces of hardware having
missing drivers. And, in the brief testing I've done running Traktor,
Windows 10 seemed stable enough.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Windows"></category><category term="activation"></category></entry><entry><title>Using Garmin Forerunner watches with Linux</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/using-garmin-forerunner-watches-with-linux" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-30T23:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-12-30:posts/using-garmin-forerunner-watches-with-linux</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm now the owner of a Garmin GPS watch. When I was looking at GPS
watches, I couldn't find a huge amount of information on using them with
Linux. This post concerns the Forerunner 15 (FR15) particularly, but
think may well apply to several others in that range that function as
USB storage devices, with the usual "your mileage may vary" caveats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Can you use it with Linux?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, to some extent. Though you won't be able to use all the fancy
display features on Garmin's site. That said, I'm not bothered about
that and would actually prefer to keep my data offline, especially with
the number of website data breaches there have been recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FR15 shows up as a normal USB storage device so you can copy over
.FIT files from the watch directly and work with them on your computer.
My run data was stored in &lt;code&gt;GARMIN/ACTIVITY&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that, when researching this, you may read older posts about the
unofficial Garmin Communication web browser plugin that was capable of
uploading data to Garmin's servers.  This no longer functions and &lt;a href="https://github.com/adiesner/GarminPlugin/issues/14"&gt;this
GitHub issue&lt;/a&gt;
suggests it won't be fixed anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Installing GPSBabel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next job is to get the FIT files into a format that's more widely
usable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.gpsbabel.org/"&gt;GPSBabel&lt;/a&gt; is a application for Windows, OS X
and Linux that lets you convert between GPS data formats, including
converting Garmin's FIT (Flexible and Interoperable Data Transfer)
format into .GPX (GPS Exchange Format) which is well supported by
various free, open source applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Support for FIT was added to GPSBabel in versions 1.4.3 and later,
judging from the &lt;a href="https://www.gpsbabel.org/changes.html"&gt;GPSBabel
changelog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your distribution's repositories have an older version, you'll need
to compile it from source. In Ubuntu, it was reasonably straightforward
to clone it from &lt;a href="https://github.com/gpsbabel/gpsbabel"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and then
do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;./configure --prefix&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$HOME&lt;/span&gt;/.local
make
make install
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;prefix&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt; allows you to &lt;a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/42569"&gt;install to a local
directory&lt;/a&gt; and avoids the need
for &lt;code&gt;sudo&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;make install&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only hiccup was that the &lt;code&gt;configure&lt;/code&gt; step gave the error message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;configure: error: Qt4 or Qt5 is required, but neither was found&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/16607003/qmake-could-not-find-a-qt-installation-of"&gt;The fix&lt;/a&gt;
was to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo apt-get install qtcreator
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;which was probably overkill as it installed a lot of packages, but
compiling then worked. (I then removed &lt;code&gt;qtcreator&lt;/code&gt; via &lt;code&gt;apt-get
remove&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Converting Garmin's FIT data to GPX&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example use of GPSBabel is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;gpsbabel -i garmin_fit -f input.FIT -o gpx -F output.gpx
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This gives you a GPX file which can be loaded into far more software. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a quick test, I loaded the output GPX file into
&lt;a href="https://apps.ubuntu.com/cat/applications/viking/"&gt;Viking&lt;/a&gt; which seems a
little bit limited, but at least let me visualise speed against time,
and see where I've been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are web apps out there that will save you this hassle and do the
conversion for you, but, again, I'd rather keep my location data to
myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Some of the high-end watches also have the ability to send the data to
Garmin via Bluetooth to mobile apps that collect the data, so that's
another way you could avoid the requirement for Windows or OS X.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Upgrading the watch's firmware&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My watch came with the latest firmware installed and the watch has been
out a while, so I doubt there are any major issues remaining. But, there
may still be further updates as it's still a supported product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official update method is via Garmin's Windows or OS X software. If
you search their site, you can find that updates exist, but you're told
to use Garmin Express to install them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it is possible to find download URLs for firmware updates, if
you look in the HTML source. For instance, the &lt;a href="http://download.garmin.com/software/Forerunner15_270.rgn"&gt;current FR15
firmware&lt;/a&gt; is
available via direct download using any client you like, albeit via
insecure http. (I haven't tested the official software, it may well use
the same links.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't needed this information yet, but there are &lt;a href="https://forums.garmin.com/archive/index.php/t-103787.html"&gt;more details
regarding a different
model&lt;/a&gt; on the
Garmin forums, but may well be relevant here. As a post there states,
you may need to remove 60 bytes of an extraneous header using &lt;code&gt;tail&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To verify that an original file needs this header-removing, open it
with &lt;code&gt;hexdump -C [Download FileName] | head&lt;/code&gt;. You should see it
starting with the string KpGrd The main watch firmware has two of
those KpGrd headers, but we only remove the first one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also bear in mind that there may be multiple firmware files to update,
e.g. the watch firmware itself, as well as language files and the ANT
firmware. And apparently &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; these need the header removing. Anyway,
you can search Garmin's site for e.g. "Forerunner 15 update" and see
what you find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What's the watch actually like?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've only started using it today, but it seems good at what it does. I
tracked a run and, at a glance, the data looked consistent with where
I'd been and how I'd run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a basic model, but capable. It's got what seems like a decent
battery, apparently eight hours in active GPS use. Anecdotally, I headed
out taking it straight from the box without charging and it was flashing
an empty battery warning for most of the run (an hour or so), but still
managed to record the entire distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also waterproof which was handy since I was caught up in a heavy
downpour while out. And it didn't feel noticeably less comfortable or
more cumbersome than the (near-weightless) Casio digital watch that I'm
usually wearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also activity tracker features available to count steps and
calories, though I'm less concerned about those. Recording a run for
later inspection, tracking my heart rate, distance travelled and time
elapsed while running, and keeping my best times are the features I
really want. And the FR15 does all of these things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FR15 was on offer when I bought it. Would I have paid the full
retail price? I don't know. At that price and adding on an optional
heart rate monitor bundled, it's very similar in price to higher-end
watches like Garmin's 225.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I did look into more expensive watches and all of
them, at least the Garmin watches, seemed to have drawbacks. There
wasn't an obvious candidate that stood out as the one to get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a starter watch, the FR15 seems like a good deal, especially as it
seems we're in a time where the technology's still improving. (Perhaps
indicative of that, Garmin, much to the chagrin of unlucky purchasers,
released a newer version of their FR225 only a few months after they
launched it.) There's also competition from the likes of Fitbit and
Jawbone which will probably push improvements to these devices in
future. Newer, more expensive watches are already switching over to
wrist monitoring of heart rate instead of using more traditional heart
rate bands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if this is technology that I use long term, then the next step would
be to a watch featuring wrist heart rate monitoring and cadence
measurement. Nonetheless, the expandability of the FR15 is a bonus: you
can use a separate ANT heart rate monitor (it optionally is bundled with
one), as well as a footpod. Excluding these extras keeps the price down,
but it's still possible to augment the device with these features in
future; I've already ordered a heart rate monitor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one downside of the design I've seen so far is that I think the
battery will be a chore to replace when it expires. It's not officially
user-replaceable. That drawback aside, it seems a decent choice.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Garmin"></category><category term="Forerunner"></category><category term="Linux"></category><category term="GPS"></category><category term="running"></category></entry><entry><title>Beatmatching to beat grid in Traktor</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/beatmatching-to-beat-grid-in-traktor" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-21T13:50:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-12-21:posts/beatmatching-to-beat-grid-in-traktor</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Tracks that beat Traktor's beat detection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traktor's not always perfect in automatic beat detection. I was trying to set
the correct beats per minute (bpm) value for a particular track and not having
a lot of luck with the tap function that Traktor provides. The estimated bpm
kept jumping around on each click.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're not familiar, a tap feature is common in music software for beat
detection: tap a button along to the beat of the music, and after a few clicks,
you should have a fairly good estimation of what the bpm is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another option you have is to manually adjust the beat grid to set the bpm; the
beat grid is a series of line markers that you want to mark the track's beats.
It acts as a visual guide for the user that shows whether the bpm is set
correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a chore as it requires fine adjustment. You'll end up clicking a lot to 
stretch or compress the grid and correct it. Also, if you're zoomed in to precisely
align this, you can't see if everything's still OK further along the track
without going back and forth, like Cameo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Beatmatching to find the bpm&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last time I was contemplating doing this I realised that if you can
beatmatch by ear, then to find an unknown track's bpm, you can simply beatmatch
to a track with a known good bpm. It's more fun too as you're actually
&lt;em&gt;listening&lt;/em&gt; to the music and DJing, rather than &lt;em&gt;click-click-clicking&lt;/em&gt; like
you're gold farming in some video game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you're happy that the tracks are beatmatched, if you have the current bpm
for the known good track displayed — you can change what's displayed in each
deck's heading in Preferences — then that should give you the correct bpm for
the track with unknown bpm. You can then type this in where the bpm is
displayed on the "Grid" panel for the deck playing the track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All that's left to do is seek to the first downbeat and add that as a beat grid
cue point (use the "Cue" panel for the deck) and the track should be ready for
beatmatching. Traktor usually does a decent job on finding that downbeat
though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That would be all, except you might only have a correct bpm for the particular
section you've been listening to: it's possible that the bpm fluctuates. If the
beat detection fails, this is quite a common problem, particularly for older
pieces of music which weren't created digitally and may drift slightly due to
human timing. A fix for this is to just work with a loop in the track which
does have a sufficiently steady bpm to mix. You can add loops in the "Cue"
panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I'm here, I should wistfully wish that Native Instruments would improve
the beat matching aspect. Using multiple beat markers, Ableton's capable of
adjusting — "warping" they call it — the track to fix it such that it has a
consistent tempo, something that Traktor lacks. So, I'm still saving for
Ableton.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Traktor"></category><category term="beatmatching"></category><category term="DJ"></category><category term="beat grid"></category></entry><entry><title>As easy as 123(-reg)</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/as-easy-as-123-reg" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-12-11T17:04:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-12-11:posts/as-easy-as-123-reg</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Two factor or not two factor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're living in the future right now: it's almost 2016. Almost as unbelievably,
123-reg &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; haven't implemented any kind of two factor authentication for
their site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From their own &lt;a href="https://www.123-reg.co.uk/blog/security-issues/how-to-create-a-strong-password-and-protect-your-online-life/"&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-factor authentication adds another layer of protection and you should use
it where it is available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, yeah, I would. If I could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's stupid for me to not be using a registrar that provides two factor
authentication. Get control of the domain and you could hijack my website or my
email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also stupid on their part not to implement this. It's a security feature I
expect as standard on important web services these days. And I'm sure that I'm
not the only person who's decided to leave or not use their service as a
result. Moreover, the implication of no two factor support does have me
questioning what else they can't be bothered to do security-wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this issue, I wouldn't say I'd be exactly content, but I'd have the
apathy towards transferring my domain out that many people have towards
switching bank accounts, rather than any more urgent impetus to leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I don't ever really use the 123-reg site itself, I don't really have a
problem with them not redesigning it in years. The only major outage I've
knowingly experienced in over 12 years(!) of being with them is that email was
&lt;a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2006/12/18/123_says_sorry/"&gt;hideously delayed&lt;/a&gt; a
few years back. However, when reading about domain transfer, I also learned of
some recent &lt;a href="http://www.mayne.net/123reg-domain-name-hostage"&gt;moneygrabbing
tricks&lt;/a&gt; they've
tried.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Searching around for other domain registrars, it seems there is no single
standout provider. You can find complaints about every one, so it's a bit of a
crapshoot in choosing one. Namecheap were, true to their branding, a name that
was reasonably cheap. And, they appeared to have no more complaints than any
other provider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as a prelude to committing to moving, I figured I'd buy some other domain
names with Namecheap and see what I made of the site. My first impressions were
that the initial signup and buying services from Namecheap was pretty easy.
Their dashboard also simple to navigate and fairly fresh looking. This is a
marked improvement on the 123-reg control panel that is well overdue for a
modern, clean redesign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thing to give me the confidence to start looking into domain transfer
was the quick response I received from Namecheap in resolving an issue when
extending my domain name expiry. So, I started delving into the murky waters of
domain transfers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;12(free)-reg&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you dive in, you find the depths are actually not as bad as they first
look. Certainly, the process isn't actually that complicated. The confusing
part is navigating around help pages that usually tell an incomplete story of
what you need to do to move your domain. Neither 123-reg nor Namecheap did a
great job here: I ended up reading several different pages to do something
that's, I imagine, a reasonably common procedure for their customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you an idea, I probably spent about five to ten minutes actually making
changes on the old and new domain registrar's sites, and probably spent ten
times that time reading around, and double and triple checking what I was
doing. I didn't want to bungle the whole thing and spend hours in dialogue with
support to resolve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Migrating .uk domains&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One important note is that .uk domains are handled a bit differently to others.
The stages you need to carry out and avoid downtime aren't much more than:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;set up new name servers on your new registrar, and copy over whichever
   existing DNS settings are needed from your current registrar to the new one;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;change name servers on your current registrar to those of the new registrar
   and wait for this to be updated everywhere;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;maybe&lt;/em&gt; you need to make WHOIS data public (not sure if this is absolutely
   necessary for UK domains);&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;change the Internet Provider Security (IPS) tag on your current registrar to
   that of the new registrar;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;request a transfer in at your new registrar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, all that matters for .uk domains is the IPS tag. Anything you read about
EPP authorisation code or lock status just doesn't apply at all for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also note by .uk domains, this is &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; .uk domain, i.e. this applies for
stevenmaude.co.uk, not just stevenmaude.uk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to move from 123-reg to Namecheap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, set up FreeDNS on Namecheap. Add your existing domain as detailed
   &lt;a href="https://www.namecheap.com/support/knowledgebase/article.aspx/536/51/how-do-i-set-my-domain-to-use-namecheaps-freedns-service"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
   If you want to potentially activate that more quickly, note that you can
   prompt for an activation email. This also means you don't need to change
   name servers before you activate should you wish. You'll receive a link to
   activate the FreeDNS service in that case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to Advanced DNS on Namecheap's dashboard and copy over entries from the
   123-reg Advanced DNS settings. There were a couple of 123-reg IP addresses
   in there which I didn't move as they were no longer needed. Everything else
   I just copied over by hand. MX records are added in Namecheap by selecting
   "Custom MX" in "Mail Settings" which is in the Advanced DNS dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optional&lt;/strong&gt;: if you were using web forwarding and want to preserve it, you
   can set this up on Namecheap's Manage options for the domain ("Redirect
   Domain") or go to Advanced DNS and add entries manually. See their
   &lt;a href="https://www.namecheap.com/support/knowledgebase/article.aspx/385/77/how-do-i-setup-url-forwarding-for-a-domain"&gt;help pages&lt;/a&gt;
   for more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to 123-reg's control panel and select the option to add name servers to
   your domain. I added two of Namecheap's FreeDNS servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possibly optional&lt;/strong&gt;: you may need to make the WHOIS contact details public
   for the domain if they're not already. Go to 123-reg's control panel and do
   this. You may wish to change the address first to one which you're happy
   with making publically accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the new name servers have been added and that they work. Windows, Linux
   and OS X all have a &lt;code&gt;whois&lt;/code&gt; command you can use to see if the name servers
   are at least visible on the DNS server you're accessing. You may see this
   change fairly quickly e.g. within a few seconds or minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My way of testing that the name servers were working as expected was to add
a temporary web forwarding rule on the new registrar which didn't exist on
the old one. Once I could confirm that redirect worked, I could remove the
rule. As I was confident things were working OK, I then removed the 123-reg
name servers from my domain, leaving only the FreeDNS ones there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can verify that everything is working OK, you should now wait
sometime for the settings to propagate everywhere. 123-reg currently
recommend &lt;a href="https://www.123-reg.co.uk/support/answers/Domains-Archive/Domain-Configuration/why-do-people-always-tell-me-that-my-dns-changes-take-24-48-hours-to-propagate-2653/"&gt;48 hours&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, make sure you've waited for the name server changes to
   propagate before continuing. Do something exciting in the meantime.
   Or just sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change the IPS tag on 123-reg to Namecheap's IPS tag as detailed in the
   &lt;a href="https://www.123-reg.co.uk/support/answers/Domain-Transfers/Transfers-Out/how-do-i-change-the-ips-tag-on-my-domain-name-1264/"&gt;123-reg help&lt;/a&gt;.
   Enter Namecheap's IPS tag which you can find
   &lt;a href="https://www.namecheap.com/support/knowledgebase/article.aspx/260/8/what-is-an-ips-tag"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
   If they've changed the link, a search for "IPS tag site:namecheap.com" will
   probably get you to the right place to find it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go through the Namecheap transfer, select your domain in the dashboard and
   select "Transfer in". You'll probably have to pay them some money. The
   process should hopefully begin and be complete within an hour or two.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; My
   transfer only took maybe half an hour or even less. You can see the status
   of your transfer in the Namecheap dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, check that the FreeDNS has changed to the normal DNS, and that
    all of your DNS records are still present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some reason, in the advanced DNS, the mail settings had changed from
"Custom MX" to "No Email Service". Email still appeared to work in the
meantime, and the records were all still there when I reselected "Custom
MX" which was odd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While here, you may also wish to set the public WHOIS to private if your
domain is for use by a "UK Individual".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn't charged for changing IPS tag; no idea if 123-reg changed their
  policy for everyone or it's because the domain was registered long ago.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a little disconcerting that all this happens without receiving any
  email to the domain contact to confirm the move. I'm not sure what
  procedure's in place to prevent someone else transferring your domain to
  the same registrar but under their control, once you've changed the IPS
  tag...&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="domain"></category><category term="Namecheap"></category><category term="registrar"></category><category term="transfer"></category></entry><entry><title>Getting an official Windows 10 disk image</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/getting-an-official-windows-10-disk-image" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-10-26T17:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-10-26:posts/getting-an-official-windows-10-disk-image</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Currently looking to test out installing Windows 10 and one stumbling block was
just getting hold of an official disk image. (I'm cautious these days and want
to see how setting up a dual boot encrypted Windows 10/Ubuntu goes on a spare
drive prior to actually committing to an upgrade.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Start me up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious searches for installing Windows 10 inevitably lead you to &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-gb/software-download/windows10"&gt;this
page&lt;/a&gt; where it
tells you to install the Media Creation tool and use that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critically, that's not an option if you don't have access to a current Windows
install. (Yes, it should be easy enough to find a Windows PC &lt;em&gt;somewhere&lt;/em&gt;
around, but there might not be one to hand.) The other drawback is that, as far
as I can see without testing, is that it only creates media for one particular
version of Windows, so you'd have to run through the process twice for Home and
Pro.  The actual ISO disk image is buried on the site under &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/software-download/techbench"&gt;"Tech
Bench"&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the filename differed, the 64-bit download from that page &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; match
the SHA1 as listed on the MSDN site as of 2015-10-23:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;File Name: en_windows_10_multiple_editions_x64_dvd_6846432.iso
Languages: English
SHA1: 60CCE9E9C6557335B4F7B18D02CFE2B438A8B3E2
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that there's a 90-day Win10 Enterprise
&lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/evalcenter/evaluate-windows-10-enterprise"&gt;trial&lt;/a&gt;,
but there was no checksum at all to verify that download, and you need a
Microsoft account just to get to the download. It also had the following
ambiguous information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use Windows 10 Enterprise, you must sign in to your PC with a
Microsoft account. The option to create a local account will be made available
at the time of the final release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which was unclear as to whether this still applies or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Clean installing Windows 10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other question I had was which version, Home or Pro, gets installed from
this single ISO. If it's a clean install, how is the version to install (Home
or Pro) determined? From what I remember reading, the answer should be that if
you skip entering a product key on request by the installer (which would
automatically install the appropriate version if you provide a key), the
installer prompts you to choose the version to install.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Windows"></category><category term="ISO"></category><category term="disk"></category></entry><entry><title>Thinking of using a static site generator for your blog?</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/thinking-of-using-a-static-site-generator-for-your-blog" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-19T00:37:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2015-07-18:posts/thinking-of-using-a-static-site-generator-for-your-blog</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I first thought about moving from Blogger to Pelican, it was
because I'd had more than enough of Blogger's drawbacks. What hadn't
crossed my mind, because I had no experience of using them, were the
problems that static site generators could have. At the time, my hunch
was that it wasn't possible for them to be worse than Blogger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, that was the case. But, they are not entirely perfect
and, going through this migration, I better understood what the
good and the bad of static site generators are. If you're thinking of
making a similar migration, these points might give you an idea of what
you might deal with in shifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I'm familiar with Pelican and Blogger, most of the points apply
generally so could still be informative for you if you're considering a
move from, say, Wordpress to Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Converting and writing content (Markdown)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Depending on what you used to create a blog previously, and how much
    content you had on your old blog, it may be time consuming to move
    content. Even armed with a &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican/pull/1390"&gt;fork of Pelican&lt;/a&gt; where
    someone helpful had added Blogger conversion, the output
    wasn't perfect and still had plenty of residual cruft that had to be
    fixed up by hand.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown's quick to write with, but only gives you a small subset of
    HTML and so doesn't handle every eventuality. There are dialects of
    Markdown which expand this with more layout options that may be
    available in your blog software of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Pelican at least, it's possible to use
&lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/"&gt;Pandoc&lt;/a&gt; via a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/liob/pandoc_reader"&gt;plugin&lt;/a&gt;. Pandoc is one of
the more versatile Markdown converters, but does introduces another
dependency. Pelican also offers reStructuredText support which has
support for more formatting options than vanilla Markdown, but just
isn't as nimble to write.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, I opted to occasionally allow fall back to raw HTML in
posts, mainly for handling images. This isn't ideal, but is a decent
compromise that's at least compatible with different Markdown
implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All my content is in fairly plain Markdown which I love writing in.
    It also means that I'm far less locked into Pelican than I was ever
    tied into Blogger. Should I wish to switch to another static site
    generator, only the metadata and Python-Markdown specific tweaks may
    need adjusting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adding content to the site and hosting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My git repositories are structured in a way that I like: blog HTML,
    the theme I use, my Pelican configuration, my Markdown posts, and
    the post images are all separate. However, for making small
    adjustments to posts, this is a nuisance: you need to edit the post
    and remember to push that, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; generate the HTML, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; move
    that into the HTML repository and finally push that to GitHub. I
    usually do this via branches too, which is more work too (though
    this is my choice). Improving this workflow is on my to-do list.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My blog's not trapped within Google's servers. Certainly, I'm wary
    of how much Google's hands are present in much of what I do on the
    web, whether through hardware devices I use, their search tools or
    through websites that use features like Google Analytics and Fonts
    (including mine). At least the blog's now hosted elsewhere and
    Analytics and Fonts that the site's using could, in the worst case,
    be removed entirely, or replaced with alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the blog's not really dependent on the whims of any service
    owner at all. If GitHub stop hosting, I can take the HTML and host
    it elsewhere. With Blogger, you're at Google's mercy: if they ever
    decided to drop Blogger, then you'd be forced to switch to a new
    blog platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the content is tracked within a git repository. This means it's
    version controlled, and there's no easy way to obliterate posts.
    With Blogger, at least once, I foolishly attempted to edit multiple
    posts in separate browser tabs and subsequently lost the content of
    one of them. Luckily, I had a window open with the web version of
    the post to recover it. Having only a single canonical copy of
    posts stored in Google's servers was clearly not a good thing.
    (Wordpress is better in that it's possible to store multiple
    revisions of posts.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have much more control of the post URLs; Blogger posts always
    have the year and date in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blog hosting using my own domain name on GitHub is free of charge.
    This is also free on Blogger. If you use wordpress.com, you'll need
    to pay; if you're using your own Wordpress installation, using your
    own domain is free, but it's likely you'll need to pay for hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Appearance and viewer experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With Pelican (probably much less so for Jekyll), there's not a huge
    range of themes. If you're fussy like me, you may need to spend some
    time tweaking, or creating your own. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My site now functions without the viewer needing JavaScript. With
    Blogger, you used to only see half the page content. If JavaScript
    is disabled now, the only issue is that the mobile menu doesn't
    open, which is far less of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's no awful separate mobile version of the site. On Blogger,
    the template I used had an unfriendly feature where swiping would
    navigate away from the page to the previous or next article. This
    could be triggered quite unintentionally by trying to pinch to zoom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often my posts are on programming. Having code snippets that look
    nice without me having to do anything is a great bonus. In Blogger,
    you'd need a JavaScript plugin for syntax highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Running the generator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static site generators are not for the impatient. For Pelican, being
    comfortable with Python is a big help, though not essential.
    Pelican — and I imagine this applies to Jekyll too — isn't difficult
    to get a basic blog up and running, but to get the result you want
    may take you considerable work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a very large number of posts, the time it takes to build
    your site may become an issue. With 61 posts and 1 page, my site
    takes 2 to 3 seconds on my Core i5 PC. If the site starts taking
    minutes to build, that may become a chore. This would be
    particularly frustrating if editing posts and wanting to quickly
    preview how the changes look since, with Pelican, the entire site is
    rebuilt when running the development server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican is nice to use, and I had very few problems in doing so.
    Most of my effort was spent on converting content and amending the
    theme to my liking. Though the community's relatively small, it does
    seem like there are more blog posts and activity compared with when
    I first looked into it last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pelican, and many other static site generators, are &lt;a href="http://opensource.org/"&gt;open source&lt;/a&gt; software. This means they are free
    to use, and free to modify (and share those modifications). The
    implication is that, as long as there are developers interested in
    it, it's likely that it will continue to be supported and developed.
    Even in the unlikely event that everyone else abandons it and you're
    the only user, you can still continue modifying it. (This also
    applies to Wordpress' source too incidentally.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Living with a static site&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When worrying about the limitations that static sites may have, think
about the actual minimum you need on a web site to share and present
written ideas and thoughts you have. It's really not very much; do you
&lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need everything that Wordpress offers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I'm pleased with the result. When I'd started thinking about
moving, I'd got fed up of using clunky old Blogger, which feels
distinctly unloved by Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to write directly in the format (Markdown) that the blog
actually uses is a real convenience. (Note that Wordpress offers this
option too.) Along with that, the blog looking fresher than it did is a
bonus. These features, more than perhaps anything else, actually makes
me want to add new content to my blog, which is more than I could say
that Blogger ever did for my inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see exactly how much work in the early commits
&lt;a href="https://github.com/StevenMaude/blog-content/commits/master"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Blogger"></category><category term="Pelican"></category><category term="Wordpress"></category><category term="static site"></category></entry></feed>