<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>stevenmaude.co.uk</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/</id><updated>2017-07-15T23:14:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Rinse FM's SoundCloud account takedown</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/rinse-fms-soundcloud-account-takedown" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-07-15T23:14:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-07-15T23:14:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-07-15:posts/rinse-fms-soundcloud-account-takedown</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="and-its-shutdown"&gt;And it's shutdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For many dance music lovers, the taking down of Rinse FM's SoundCloud
profile yesterday was a sad event. Along with their account, a huge
archive of shows they hosted on SoundCloud have all gone due to
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/geeneus/status/885984092449366021"&gt;copyright
infringement&lt;/a&gt;
complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's difficult to overstate Rinse's influence in dance music. The
station was heavily instrumental in pushing grime, and later dubstep in
the UK, and contributing to the massive spread of these genres outside
of these shores. While much of the UK radio broadcast frequency space is
pumped full of the same cloying pop music being endlessly
recirculated,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Rinse FM is a refreshing breath of fresh air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rinse FM started life as a pirate station, &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2012/sep/30/rinse-fm-former-pirate-station-18-birthday"&gt;broadcasting illicitly via
aerials perched on tower block
rooftops&lt;/a&gt;,
but more recently acquired a legal license. Peculiar then that they are
now legitimate under the traditional broadcasting regulations, but don't
have the same freedoms when distributing those same broadcasts via the
internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately Rinse has an established physical presence as an FM station
and a fanbase built long before the internet became popular for
distributing music. Rinse also has a sizable following on other social
networks, allowing them to communicate what's going on, and, probably as
important, a web site that lets them continue to put out their shows
uninterrupted, via live streaming and podcasts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without seeing their SoundCloud playback statistics or their web
analytics before and after this change, it's difficult to know how much
of an impact that has on the number of people listening to Rinse FM
online. But, given the news of SoundCloud's redundancies this week, it
may well be that &lt;em&gt;everyone's&lt;/em&gt; profiles are &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/07/12/soundshroud/"&gt;getting deleted from
SoundCloud sometime
soon&lt;/a&gt; like it or not.
Perhaps any impact on Rinse's future prospects may well be minimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, such an account deletion could be disastrous for the progress of a
smaller project, say a independent producer, or a niche podcast, who are
maybe start to make waves. All of a sudden their content evaporates
(easy to replace somewhere else) together with all of their following on
that site (perhaps more difficult to rebuild).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-can-we-take-away-from-this-takedown"&gt;What can we take away from this takedown?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="it-seems-a-backwards-step-for-the-music-industry"&gt;It seems a backwards step for the music industry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at &lt;a href="http://rinse.fm/podcasts/"&gt;the podcast&lt;/a&gt; page and, in any
given week, you'll see a diverse range of artists hosting shows, and
invariably a top line up. Today, you have a house legend, Masters At
Work's Kenny Dope, on only a couple of hours after alternative
electronic producer, &lt;a href="https://forestswords.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Forest
Swords&lt;/a&gt;. Whether old hands or not,
the hosts are often influential taste makers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of that, Rinse's audience no doubt overlaps with who the music
industry are targeting: young and early adopters of new music. Why then
does someone, somewhere presumably think it's a smart move to hinder
that?  These listeners likely form the dedicated audience that same
industry is crying out for: those that will go out and track down music,
share it with their friends, go to shows to see acts playing out, or
even become the next big DJs or producers of the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another thing: many of Rinse's shows are in a mix format. That's
because mixes are a natural way of presenting modern dance music. Maybe
I'm naive as to the machinations of the music industry, but both as a
listener, and as a (mediocre) DJ, it's difficult to see the logic behind
&lt;a href="http://djtechtools.com/2017/06/15/drake-hate-dj-mixes-soundcloud-copyright-strikes-vs-dj-mixes/"&gt;taking down DJ mixes at
all&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as creative expression and entertainment in their own right,
mixes can act as promotional tools. The featuring of tracks in mixes may
well encourage listeners to buy the tracks, or at least to head over to
a streaming service to hear it uninterrupted. Keep in mind that a track
in a mix isn't usually a substitute for hearing the track end-to-end:
they're different contexts. And DJs listening in may well decide to
shell out for the full track to play in their own sets. When there's so
much music, past and present competing for attention today, you'd think
that &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; that might nudge listeners to a given label's artists
would be welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="where-to-host-projects"&gt;Where to host projects?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you're starting with a project that you're serious about and you
want it to reach the audience you're aiming for, what do you do? What
this situation tells me is that it's vital to be cultivating a following
in multiple places. That way you're not back to square one should your
profile on a single site be taken down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I have an idea for a music-related project I'm intending to
put together. To keep things simple starting out, I'd considered just
having the project exist as a SoundCloud account, instead of creating a
blog to go with it. After this week with the Rinse FM takedown, coupled
with the possibility of SoundCloud disappearing, my thinking has shifted
entirely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owners of accounts on online services, as I've written before,&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; have
little real ownership of what happens with those accounts. If the site's
owners or moderators don't like what you're doing for whatever reason,
you're gone. Someone might complain about what you're doing on the
service, just as happened to Rinse FM, and likewise you're gone. For
what I'm planning, it's very unlikely that copyright claims would be an
issue, but the potential of having your account taken down for some
other reason, and perhaps outside your control, still stands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certainly, radio stations like Rinse and DJs could try their luck on
Mixcloud or other alternative sites, but there's nothing to say that the
same copyright issues might occur there in future, even if those sites
are relatively permissive now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's difficult. The big services are those where the users are. Creators
are often tied to publishing using those services if they want to get
people interested, as those services are where people are browsing,
searching and listening. But, over-reliance on a particular service
means that if it fails you, either destroying your account on a whim, or
because the site itself is shutdown, the knock-on impact for getting
visibility (or audibility) for creative projects can be a big blow.
Hedging your bets seems the only viable solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't get me wrong. I'm very much not against pop music. The
  "same" in that sentence is an important qualifier of why I
  dislike those stations so, so much. It's the lack of individuality
  and the repetition that gets me. If you flick through the
  commercial pop stations, could you be able to tell them apart?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When there's so much music that I know I'll never have enough time
  to discover and hear, it's such a pity that show producers and
  station bosses are often so unadventurous.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look &lt;a href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/what-happens-when-github-decides-youre-not-a-human"&gt;what happened to my GitHub account last year&lt;/a&gt;,
  for example.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="music"></category><category term="radio"></category><category term="Rinse FM"></category><category term="SoundCloud"></category></entry><entry><title>Do you even Liszt? Five months of learning piano</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/do-you-even-liszt-five-months-of-learning-piano" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-06-11T14:06:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-11T14:06:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-06-11:posts/do-you-even-liszt-five-months-of-learning-piano</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="why-learn-now"&gt;Why learn now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other posts on my blog highlight the small theme of me very, very slowly
trying to get better at making music. When you're a novice, it's natural
to ask what's the best way to improve? Some common advice I've found on
music production forums goes like this: focus on develop piano playing
skills first, and less on learning software or production itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that's for two big reasons. An analogy is that being unable to
touch type would be a hindrance for writing and coding. You can still do
these things regardless, but the lack of being able to express yourself
quickly does slow your progress. Likewise with music, yes, you can
painstakingly draw notes in software,&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but being able to play a
melody or chord progression means that you can transcribe something in
your head much more quickly and directly, as well as improvise
effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being able to play also gives you hard fought experience of both picking
up music theory as you learn and seeing it constantly applied. When
playing pieces of music that "work" while seeing how they are made, it's
surprising sometimes just how some melodies can be pleasing, whether in
spite of, or indeed, because of their simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that motivation in mind, I've been taking piano lessons since the
start of this year. And as I've just this week played a very small part
in a concert, albeit a very simple accompaniment, it seemed as good a
point as any to document how I've found this as an adult learner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="tuition-or-self-taught"&gt;Tuition or self-taught?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lessons can be expensive for what is a relatively short time with a
teacher, so why would you bother paying? You're doing most of the
learning by yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very true, but lessons have a lot to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It makes a commitment to sit down and learn something for the next week,
which is very important. Aside from the odd day when I've been ill or
away, I've usually managed to get in at least a daily half-hour practice
session. Having a scheduled lesson with a teacher really does act as a
promise to ensure you keep time aside for practice. At times, I'd have
the idea in my head that I'd not yet got enough done for the next
lesson. That's usually enough motivation for me to sit down and work on
piano. You have a deadline to meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teachers can provide guidance of specific pointers, on technique, on how
to play tricky sections, or on explaining notation. Particularly with
piano, at least to me, it doesn't always seem obvious whether what I'm
doing is "correct" or most efficient. If I was learning in isolation,
things I find difficult could well contribute to me giving up. Knowing I
can go and get advice at the next lesson is a really positive and
powerful resource to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having someone capable of competently observing and listening to you
play, assessing that and pointing out things you're doing wrong (even
when you think you've mastered something) is also a boon. Likewise, this
means you should be encouraged with reasonably good habits, e.g. posture
and finger positioning, instead of getting by for now, and struggling
later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A teacher can also tell you when you've got the most out of learning a
piece. You could spend a long time playing something to near perfection,
but is that practice time most usefully spent doing that? Importantly,
it's not just having that feedback from someone else, but one who has
taught others and knows what's reasonable to expect too. It also, again,
takes this decision out of your hands. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Removing some of the decision making of learning is another benefit.
Instead of having to figure out what books to get and which pieces to
try next — is this too difficult? too easy? — they can set tasks for
you. Again, a teacher should know what works well for other learners,
and it means you don't have to concern yourself with that at all. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, for me, lessons work best with a two-way involvement. As time
is short, I've found a good strategy is going in with a clear idea of
things I've been struggling with or don't quite understand, to discuss
and work on in the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disregarding all those benefits, could you teach yourself? It's not
impossible. There are musicians that have successfully done just that.
But, it requires a lot of discipline and the persistence to battle
through the tricky skills you'll need to learn. The only downside I can
think of taking lessons is their financial cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="starter-books"&gt;Starter books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first book I was using was The Classic Piano Course Book 1 by Carol
Barratt. Beginning from basics, it introduces new ideas throughout every
couple of pages, moving briskly, without being overwhelming. Progress
feels regular and positive. Certainly, except towards the last third or
so of the book, with a little practice each day, it was possible to get
most of the simple pieces to a decent standard in a week or so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going back to tuition versus being self-taught, you could use it for
self-teaching as it is mostly self-explanatory, although at times it's a
light on details. For instance, it provides an exercise on hand
extending and contracting, which, in the absence of helpful pictures, I
had to check with my teacher that I'd understood it correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From completing about three-quarters of that book, I've moved on to 2017
&amp;amp; 2018 ABRSM Grade 1 assessment pieces. Not necessarily with a view to
taking the exams, but to get to that standard. These are challenging,
probably taking me maybe a couple of weeks to be able to play through
from start to finish at all (i.e. stumbling through them with hands
together), with another week or two to refine them. Even then, I'm aware
of shortcomings that I could still improve on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Popular books, such as these, are a good choice. You'll easily find
competent performances on YouTube as a useful reference for what the
music you're playing should sound like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-is-learning"&gt;How is learning?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually enjoy practice. It can be frustrating, particularly when you
first start out on something and struggle, which can be demoralising.
What you have to do is retain the faith that you'll improve just like
you have on previous pieces when you first encountered them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you're a bit more comfortable that most new things you play could
be the most difficult that you have tackled, the process starts to feel
less daunting. Once you begin to get to grips with a piece, playing
becomes a lot more fun to work on as it comes together, and you make
fewer mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picking out the correct notes, adding the correct rhythm, introducing
dynamics and accents, and pedalling all feel almost like separate layers
of complexity. This can feel overwhelming at times, although focusing on
tackling a subset of these and adding the others on later does help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coordinating two hands is definitely a tricky aspect of piano. It takes
considerable practice to be able to play two different things with your
hands independently. That's very different from guitar (where I have a
little past experience),&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; where left and right hand perform very
different tasks, and it's easier to isolate their movements. That said,
as much as I find certain aspects of piano tricky, I found barre chords
on guitar a real barrier (sorry) to cross.&lt;sup id="fnref:3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:3" rel="footnote"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Piano feels difficult
generally, but I've not yet encountered any single thing that is a
comparable obstacle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the whole, learning piano been an enjoyable and rewarding experience.
To go from almost no experience to being able to stumble through Grade 1
pieces, which sound pleasant (if played well), and really feel like
you're playing piano, has been an interesting journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now feeling a bit more confident when I'm attempting to make music.
Knowing that my hands are likely in the correct position, or being able
to noodle around on the keyboard with a more decisive feeling of what
I'm doing as being musical, are some of the early benefits I've gained
from studying piano. Recalling little melodies or chord progressions
also seems a simpler task, since I'm more familiar with keyboard layout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a late starter, there's no way I'm going to be ever as good as if I'd
begun when much younger. I think it's important to keep your possible
achievements realistic, so as not to stretch too far and give up in
frustration. Nonetheless, for what I really want to do, create
music,&lt;sup id="fnref:4"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:4" rel="footnote"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the skills being developed are valuable, and, importantly,
I've found learning piano enjoyable enough in itself to continue with
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some take this to
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_MIDI"&gt;extremes&lt;/a&gt; too, treating a
musical score as a canvas that must be filled and painting in an
&lt;em&gt;inhuman&lt;/em&gt; number of notes.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One notable thing from learning guitar is that I only ever read
treble clef, but not bass clef (although I did see it and struggle
through with it a while back in a &lt;a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/edinburgh-music-theory"&gt;Coursera music theory
course&lt;/a&gt;). Because
of that, I'm much less comfortable reading the bass clef. The best way I
can describe this feeling is: imagine the confusion if you were reading
a book where a mischievous publisher had turned every second line upside
down.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've not picked up a guitar, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Barre_chord"&gt;barre
chords&lt;/a&gt; are difficult because
they require clamping some or all of the strings down at one fret
position, usually with the index finger. Here, you need to strengthen
and toughen up your finger to do this, as well as placing it correctly
so the strings ring cleanly, instead of with an unsatisfying dull thunk.
It can be tricky.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:4"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's certainly worthwhile and enjoyable to play other people's
music well. But I think there's something about the possibility of being
able to create something as an individual. There's no-one else that is
you, or can ever be you. Therefore it is possible to create something
that's really your own and couldn't be made by anyone else, even if
your technical prowess is a hindrance. And sometimes that lack of
competency, to a degree, can be a key part of what marks out what you
create as &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Outsider_music"&gt;distinct and
unique&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:4" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="learning"></category><category term="music"></category><category term="piano"></category></entry><entry><title>Looking at Ableton's Learning Music</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/looking-at-abletons-learning-music" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-21T20:09:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-05-21T20:09:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-05-21:posts/looking-at-abletons-learning-music</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Previously I &lt;a href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/book-and-talk-review-making-music-74-creative-strategies-for-electronic-music-producers"&gt;looked at Ableton's book of ideas for music
producers&lt;/a&gt; that came out
a while back, geared to people with some experience of making music
already. That did well in summarising suggestions for creativity into
short, easily digestible chapters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ableton have now followed on by developing a free tutorial site that
actually takes a step back. It's instead aimed at complete beginners who
might be interested in creating music which, in the spirit of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Does_exactly_what_it_says_on_the_tin"&gt;Ronseal&lt;/a&gt;,
Ableton have called it &lt;a href="https://learningmusic.ableton.com/"&gt;Learning
Music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the previously published book, this resource is accessible for
free. Is it worth your time to work through?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-does-the-site-work"&gt;How does the site work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always &lt;a href="https://learningmusic.ableton.com/"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt;
yourself, but, briefly, each page is a mixture of a small amount of
explanatory text with usually some interactive tool that mimics some
aspect of a digital audio workstation (DAW) (particularly Ableton Live).
Sometimes, there are music videos where some feature of that music is
then broken down on the page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where this DAW-lite interactivity works well is that it's stripped down
to the minimum framework of triggering samples or placing notes. Looking
at a lot of modern audio software, it's easy to be overwhelmed by
options, even as a seasoned user. This paring down was a sensible
decision so as not to deter the interested who might have little
experience of music theory, or digital music making. (And no doubt made
the site simpler to build too.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This functionality also provides an opportunity to practice and try
altering the examples, if someone doesn't yet have a digital audio
workstation installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These interactive tools often nicely assist the user, making it easy to
make something sounding pleasing. This can be by, for example,
restricting the permitted notes to ones within a scale, or, as on the
&lt;a href="https://learningmusic.ableton.com/index.html"&gt;first page&lt;/a&gt;, by carefully
creating patterns that the user can trigger and overlay each other
without any danger of the sounds clashing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the look and feel of the interactive sequencer widgets is
obviously influenced by Ableton Live, and could segue nicely into trying
out the Ableton Live demo, the ideas — much like the book — transcend
any particular piece of software. Like the book, even if you've no
interest in Ableton itself, and intend to use some other software (or
hardware) for making music, that shouldn't put you off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial does allow you to export sketches you make in the Learning
Music web app to Ableton Live, should you wish — a nice touch — albeit
one that's geared towards steering users towards Live (which is fair
enough).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other main feature of this tutorial is that context of the musical
ideas is given by reference to contemporary music, often well-known
electronic music. Some aspect of each is broken down. This can be quite
revealing if you haven't thought of music that way before: isolating one
part (percussion, bassline, chords, melodies, structure) and briefly
exploring what makes those aspects effective. It's nice that's it's
example led; it gives the reader something to quickly grab onto, and
provides possible inspirations too. Active listening in this way was
pushed throughout the earlier Making Music book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the creators of the site's material could have gone slightly
further. Maybe deconstructing one simple track throughout the course of
the tutorial would work well in addition to analysing different pieces
of music (which admittedly does help avoid boredom). Referring back to a
single piece of music and considering a different aspect each time might
provide two things: a sense of familiarity as the learner progresses
through the material, and a sense of achievement that they understand
how most of the main aspects of a particular track are put together,
once they've completed the tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="and-does-the-site-work"&gt;And does the site work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of material, if you've ever covered some basic music theory or
have reasonable proficiency on an instrument, then you'll probably have
encountered plenty of what is taught, and you won't get that much out of
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there were still a few things I learned about, for example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the Indonesian &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pelog"&gt;Pelog&lt;/a&gt; scale;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the opening notes of the melody from Kraftwerk's &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LTZyXlLhvxs"&gt;Tour de
  France&lt;/a&gt; are apparently
  taken from Paul Hindemith's &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vXb63qlNg5c"&gt;Heiter
  Bewegt&lt;/a&gt; from Sonata for
  Flute and Piano. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tutorials, then, only skirt the surface of each topic. Read the
wrong way, this might sound like a criticism. It's not. In teaching
aimed to give a survey of a topic, it's actually a positive: crucially,
it's just enough to get the main point across to the target audience,
make them aware of the ideas, and prompt the curious to go and learn
more elsewhere, without being so detailed as to feel like hard work. So,
for me, the site succeeds in its aims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're a relative newcomer to music theory or composition, have got a
spare hour or two and want to learn a little about creating music, or if
you just want to see breakdowns of how parts of some pieces of music
work — music that you may well have already heard and loved — it's more
than worth your time to work through the material Ableton are offering.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Ableton"></category><category term="music"></category><category term="music theory"></category></entry><entry><title>Trying to trim down static GTFS feeds</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/trying-to-trim-down-static-gtfs-feeds" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-05T11:15:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-05-05T11:15:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-05-05:posts/trying-to-trim-down-static-gtfs-feeds</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="whats-a-gtfs-feed"&gt;What's a GTFS feed?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week I've been attempting to reduce the size of a static GTFS feed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the uninitiated, GTFS is the &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/"&gt;General Transit Feed
Specification&lt;/a&gt;, a format
for public transport providers to distribute details of their services.
For example, a bus operator might want to share which routes they run
on, and the times at which they arrive at certain stops. It's not
restricted to buses. You might find GTFS feeds published for trains,
underground services, ferries and &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/reference/routes-file"&gt;even
gondolas&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The "static" distinguishes those feeds from realtime&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; feeds. Static
feeds are just zip files that contain a number of text files in a
comma-separated values (CSV) format, with a .txt filename extension.
These CSVs detail regular timetables that should remain valid for some
reasonable length of time, i.e. they change infrequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Realtime feeds (GTFS-RT) report, for example, live trip updates (e.g.
when a bus gets behind the published ideal schedule) or vehicle
locations. Realtime feeds are in Google's Protocol Buffers format, not
CSV. It's useful to be aware of the difference, but, beyond that, I
won't discuss GTFS-RT feeds further in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-problem"&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Colleagues on a project were attempt to load the data we'd found for a
particular country, and they were finding it far too large to be usable.
GTFS files come zipped, and the total unzipped content of this file
wasn't far off a gigabyte, and the import into their software was taking
too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were only interested in one geographic region, so maybe most
content can be filtered out either by location, or by transport agency.
Here's a rundown of what I found with the existing tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="onebusaway-gtfs-transformer"&gt;onebusaway GTFS transformer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, on seeing the &lt;a href="http://developer.onebusaway.org/modules/onebusaway-gtfs-modules/1.3.3/onebusaway-gtfs-transformer-cli.html"&gt;onebusaway GTFS
transformer&lt;/a&gt;,
it seemed like a dream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a Java program that lets you simply specify the agencies to retain
from the feed in a simple JSON format, and it's fairly comprehensive in
how you can do that. So, hey, let's write a simple transform JSON that
keeps the bus and train agency for the region of interest, and drop the
rest. Exactly what's needed, and a job well done, so now I can relax, and
take a well-earned rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, &lt;em&gt;opens eyes to the smell of a burning PC&lt;/em&gt;, it's time to wake up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation does provide a warning that this transformation may be
memory and CPU hungry with large GTFS feeds, and that's what I found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the transformer seemed to choke on this large GTFS file.
It ran for a long time (hours, across multiple CPUs), got stuck spinning
its wheels on the huge stop_times.txt file (millions of lines) and never
managed to escape that mud. As well as that, out of memory errors were a
problem. In the software's defence, the free memory on the instance I
was running on was fairly limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've simpler GTFS feeds to work with, it may do the trick, but, for
large ones, you'll need a beefy PC to possibly get anywhere with it.
That said, there's little status output while it's running, meaning it
was unclear whether the transformer was ever doing any useful work or
just getting stuck in some loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="gtfstidy"&gt;gtfstidy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, &lt;a href="https://github.com/patrickbr/gtfstidy/"&gt;gtfstidy&lt;/a&gt;. It can reduce
the size of static GTFS feeds by removing redundant content, simplifying
identifiers and doing clever things to optimise shape data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's written in Go, although there are no builds provided, so you'll
have to have Go to install or compile it yourself, which is easy enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, it took a long time to process; here, about five hours on my
2013 Core i5 laptop. Then, gtfstidy crashed right at the end of
processing the data &lt;a href="https://github.com/patrickbr/gtfstidy/issues/1"&gt;because as I later discovered, it expected the
output directory to
exist&lt;/a&gt; and just failed
to write the output otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then it took &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; few hours after I created said output
directory to run again and actually get the cleaned feed data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, gtfstidy reduced the total size of the GTFS files by about
150 MB, which is a considerable saving. My initial idea was maybe it
might clean the data up enough to make running the onebusaway
transformer a little bit quicker, but it didn't seem worth bothering
trying that again, as the data files overall were still large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="gtfssplit"&gt;gtfssplit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href="https://github.com/samuelmr/gtfssplit"&gt;gtfssplit&lt;/a&gt; is a PHP
tool that breaks apart a static GTFS feed into trips, shapes and stops.
Unlike the other two projects, this one hasn't been touched for a
while.&lt;sup id="fnref:2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:2" rel="footnote"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This took a fair time to run, although you can see it's at least doing
something some of the time, because, contrary to the relatively shy and
subdued onebusaway transformer, it displays a lot of warnings while
running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once these files are all on disk, maybe it's possible to write code to
recombine these back together into a GTFS feed, filtering out for
agencies that you're not interested in?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I observed is that the dates.txt files that the gtfssplit documentation
refers to in the output (that should be for a given service, i.e. to
tell you which dates the service applies) didn't seem to be present, so
it might be possible that it's losing data somewhere. Maybe that's
because the feed I was looking at has a &lt;a href="https://developers.google.com/transit/gtfs/reference/calendar_dates-file"&gt;calendar_dates.txt and no
calendar.txt
file&lt;/a&gt;,
and this case isn't handled. (It's valid, just not the recommended way
of putting together a feed.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, I'm not sure, and didn't spend any more time investigating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="journeys-end"&gt;Journey's end?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's as far I got to, which is a little anticlimactic. That is, I
haven't found a good existing solution for solving this for large feeds,
outside of the prospect of attempting to write code to do this myself.
However, the fact that all the existing software runs slowly, doesn't
exactly instil me with much hope of doing a better job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big difference is that what's actually needed here to solve the
problem is something relatively simple by comparison. The core issue is
that the stop_times.txt is too large. Maybe it's possible to filter that
down based on working through the various files, which is a much more
specific kind of tool than the generic transformer. Perhaps this could
work along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep rows from routes.txt that match the relatively few transport
   &lt;code&gt;agency_id&lt;/code&gt;s of interest giving a set of &lt;code&gt;route_id&lt;/code&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep rows from trips.txt that match those &lt;code&gt;route_id&lt;/code&gt;s from 1 in
   trips.txt, so now these give &lt;code&gt;trip_id&lt;/code&gt;s of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep rows in stop_times.txt if they match a &lt;code&gt;trip_id&lt;/code&gt; retained from
   2, meaning most of the rows disappear, assuming the agencies that are
   of interest make up only a small proportion of the total rows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could go further and then fix up the other files too to purge
anything that's now no longer relevant: for example, cleaning agency.txt
to remove agencies that are no longer present. But perhaps gtfstidy
might be enough to tidy up the remaining files and allow us to construct
a clean and valid feed from the files we've mangled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also ways of wrangling GTFS feeds into SQL databases — haven't
linked any as I haven't tried any and can't vouch for them, but they're
easy to find by searching "GTFS to SQL" — so importing and writing
queries to do this filtering, then exporting the result as CSV might be
an alternative option instead of coding something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all speculation for now; I haven't attempted any of this yet. If
I do and it's useful, I'll share what I learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would be nice is if feed providers offered feeds in smaller
regional chunks. Often, transport companies are providing GTFS feeds at
an agency level, so these should be relatively small. I suspect that the
sources of countrywide feeds are usually efforts of communities or
companies to compile the data, which is sometimes originally in a format
other than GTFS, into a standard feed. So it feels ungrateful to comment
that it would be nicer if they broke these feeds into smaller chunks for
data consumers to import into software without further work because
they're providing a free service and their efforts are appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, those making efforts to share this data may find more
users for their data if it's ready for import into other software
without needing fast PCs with lots of RAM, or without consumers having
to find ways to divide up the provided feed. For instance, applications
like OpenTripPlanner can, at time of writing, &lt;a href="https://github.com/opentripplanner/OpenTripPlanner/issues/2063"&gt;still struggle with large
GTFS
files&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The single word "realtime" is how the specification writes it.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't always the case, but looking at the activity of an open
  source project can be a portent of how useful it might be, if
  there are several competing bits of software that do the same
  thing and you're trying to narrow down to a few candidates to try
  out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How popular a project is, e.g. the number of GitHub stars, might
  be one indicator, although all projects will start out at zero on
  this, so it could well be a good project you've stumbled across
  that's just relatively new, or in a particular niche that means it
  will never become extremely popular. If there are multiple
  competing projects, you can compare them relatively, as opposed to
  comparing their number of stars to &lt;a href="https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap"&gt;something like
  Bootstrap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The age of the last commit is another. If a project has not been
  touched in a very long time, it could be so good that it hasn't
  needed any maintenance, or just be abandoned because it no longer
  works, or it never did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A project with comprehensive documentation, particularly if the
  documentation is good and still valid is another positive sign.
  Especially if you can get a software package or program to install
  and runs an example as described in the docs. There have been
  times I've found that this isn't the case; not a good start and
  I'm likely to give up at this point, if there are alternatives to
  still try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These aren't definite rules. And if projects are open source, then
  the only cost in trying them out is time, but these are some of
  the rules of thumb that I'd use when looking out for software I'm
  unfamiliar with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking for recommendations from others is another valuable
  resource that might speed up your search, instead of solely
  relying on your own judgement and web searching skills too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This footnote definitely turned out much longer than planned.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="GTFS"></category><category term="open data"></category><category term="transit"></category><category term="public transport"></category></entry><entry><title>Learning LaTeX: why and how</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/learning-latex-why-and-how" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-01T15:02:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-05-01T15:02:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-05-01:posts/learning-latex-why-and-how</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="sharelatex"&gt;ShareLaTeX&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I saw &lt;a href="https://www.sharelatex.com/learn/Learn_LaTeX_in_30_minutes"&gt;this
documentation&lt;/a&gt;
from ShareLaTeX linked on Hacker News and, as I haven't used LaTeX in a
while, thought I'd quickly skim through to see what I remembered. And I
started reminiscing about LaTeX which I'd been using semi-regularly
around a decade ago, eventually writing a circa 300 page thesis with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've never encountered it before, LaTeX is a free software project
that is described by the &lt;a href="https://www.latex-project.org"&gt;project's site&lt;/a&gt;
as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a high-quality typesetting system; it includes features designed for
the production of technical and scientific documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's nothing to stop you using it for other types of documents too;
those are just the areas where it's traditionally used, particularly in
academic circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to ShareLaTeX. First, the ShareLaTeX documentation looks pretty
good if you need something to get you started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't used ShareLaTeX recently although I think I tried it out a few
years back and it seemed fine enough. It's a web app that lets you
prepare LaTeX documents and, if you pay, collaborate on them. One big
advantage I can see of using a web app for LaTeX beginners is that it
removes one of the barriers of starting with LaTeX: installing
everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="installing-latex-on-windows"&gt;Installing LaTeX on Windows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've not had cause to use LaTeX much recently, so haven't tried
installing on Ubuntu; a lot of my writing is done via Markdown, whether
technical documentation or words like the ones you're reading now on my
blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Windows, it used to be reasonably simple to get a working system with
&lt;a href="http://www.texniccenter.org"&gt;TeXnicCenter&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="https://miktex.org"&gt;MikTeX&lt;/a&gt;, but you'd still have to get a PDF viewer,
like &lt;a href="https://www.sumatrapdfreader.org"&gt;SumatraPDF&lt;/a&gt; integrated into that
for previewing. This &lt;a href="https://tex.stackexchange.com/questions/116981/how-to-configure-texniccenter-2-0-with-sumatra-2013-2016-version"&gt;Stack Exchange
answer&lt;/a&gt;
may help with integrating the PDF preview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though that's still three different bits of software you have to get
working together, so not a trivial task by any means. From memory,
install MikTeX first, as TeXnicCenter can detect it during install and
configure its own settings to use your MikTeX installation without you
needing to set things up by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="starting-out"&gt;Starting out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ShareLaTeX documentation just starts out with creating a basic
document and has you working through following their example. That's
fine to see things piece by piece. Beyond that the single suggestion I'd
have for a new user to learn effectively is to take a completed document
you have written, representative of what you'd like to create using
LaTeX, and then &lt;strong&gt;struggle through recreating that existing document in
LaTeX&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it may well be a struggle, but this has a few benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's presumably a finished work, so you don't have any time pressure
  for completion. With a deadline to meet, as soon as you encounter
  issues with LaTeX, you'll likely fall back to whatever word processor
  or document creator you're comfortable with to get the job done, and
  then give up on learning LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a document similar to that you'd usually be writing, you'll
  encounter many of the issues in LaTeX that you'd hit doing so, and can
  solve these without the aforementioned time pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, it was graphics and, especially, table layouts
that caused the most problems, but you may have particular
typography requirements that require some package to be installed,
or some subtle override of the LaTeX defaults to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding these solutions is not always quick, but I imagine there are
more forum posts, &lt;a href="https://tex.stackexchange.com/"&gt;Stack Exchange&lt;/a&gt;
questions and blog posts around than there were when I started, so
it's likely someone's encountered and asked about the same issue
you're dealing with. The LaTeX Community forum was also a good
source of helpful solutions from knowledgable people even in its
early days ten years ago, and &lt;a href="http://latex.org/forum/"&gt;still lives on
today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A completed document gives you a reference for getting started in
  future.  You can use it as the basis for a new document, instead of
  starting from nothing, or you can just refer back to it and copy and
  paste appropriate bits of formatting markup you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="latex-versus-word"&gt;LaTeX versus Word&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="latex-installation"&gt;LaTeX installation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I saw it when learning back in 2007ish, LaTeX was more difficult to
get started with than the likes of conventional word processors: the
installation isn't trivial, and you need several things other than your
desired text in a LaTeX document before you can get that text to
display. In a word processor, you can just start typing. So there's some
level of competence you need just to make &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; old document, let alone
the one you actually want to make.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="word-woes"&gt;Word woes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Word is easy to get started with, but Word had, and maybe still has, its
own problems: again, going back to 2007, to when Word 2003 was still
popular, referencing support was limited, that you'd use external tools
for (e.g. EndNote or &lt;a href="https://www.zotero.org/"&gt;Zotero&lt;/a&gt;).  I'm not sure
how Word looks with respect to that now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back then, Word seemed to struggle and be sluggish with large documents
with lots of images, which was always fun. Again, maybe that's improved
in recent versions? When editing LaTeX, you're only editing the source
markup in whatever text editor you choose to use, and this source, even
for a lengthy document, will be relatively small; images for LaTeX are
stored entirely separately from the source. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue with Word is ensuring formatting styles are correctly and
consistently applied to text. You can create styles, but you then have
to apply them by hand, selecting the text. Sometimes you may delete
spacing between words and suddenly you have to reapply a styling, as the
text has changed to the style of its neighbours. In LaTeX, anything to
do with formatting is specified explicitly in the markup, making it easy
to see that the correct styling is applied to the text.  Furthermore,
the LaTeX defaults are usually decent, not always perfect, but decent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-good-and-bad-of-latex"&gt;The good and bad of LaTeX&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This explicitness and strictness of LaTeX is good and bad. It means that
you know what is intended for your text, but it also means that it's
possible for you to break your document sufficiently such that it cannot
be rendered correctly, or sometimes even at all, by LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've done programming and are used to finding and correcting your
inevitable mistakes, this isn't unusual. But the idea of having written
a document that you can't then display in the intended output format may
be an intimidating concept to new users. Likewise, the error messages
can be numerous and formal, and not much help to novice users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tricks known to programmers like a regular edit-compile cycle to ensure
you find issues as you create them, or commenting out markup to isolate
the specific parts of markup that are the cause of difficult to
understand problems are useful skills. (These ways of working are
perhaps a result of the creators of LaTeX — and TeX, which LaTeX is
built on — being computer scientists.) However, these concepts may not
be immediately obvious by users with little experience of coding who
just want to get on with writing, and don't want tools getting in the
way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, working just with the LaTeX source and focusing on
the text alone seems much more productive to me. You can concentrate on
content first, and fix up the presentation at the end. Otherwise, I find
that working alongside the printed document layout presents me with the
continuous distraction of making things look "right", fixing incorrect
formatting or alignments, even though the content in question could be
modified or removed entirely during later editing. This time might be
better spent just writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Talking of layout, in my opinion, a LaTeX document using defaults will
be much more pleasant to read than a Word document using defaults. To
some extent, in both cases, this can somewhat depend on templates that
you may choose to create your document, but a default LaTeX document has
more of the look of a professionally typeset book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, many useful additions to LaTeX come in the form of a huge range
of additional packages you can install to add new commands and features.
Again, this is a mixed blessing. First, you need to be aware that they
even exist — &lt;a href="https://tex.stackexchange.com/questions/553/what-packages-do-people-load-by-default-in-latex"&gt;lists like
this&lt;/a&gt;
can help: there may be a package perfect for what you're trying to do,
but you just haven't discovered it yet. Another hassle is that you can
have incompatibility issues between certain packages, or they may
require to be loaded in a certain order. Fixing problems like these is
time, again, spent on tools, not on writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do need to be careful of package updates. Mostly these should be
benign, but in one case I experienced, a package update suddenly broke
my document, and I had to spend time discovering the problem and
reverting the package version.  (My memory's hazy, but I think this was
complicated by MikTeX only having the latest package versions, so in the
end I think that I had to download from elsewhere and install by hand.)
This may be an issue for compiling documents if you return to them much
later in the future: if any of the packages have broken their backwards
compatibility, you may be stuck. There's also no easy way that I was
aware of to pin package versions, like you might in a &lt;a href="https://packaging.python.org/requirements/"&gt;Python
setup.py&lt;/a&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="do-you-still-need-to-learn-latex-these-days"&gt;Do you still need to learn LaTeX these days?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I learned LaTeX, software like &lt;a href="http://pandoc.org/"&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt; has
appeared and made it simple to write in other formats — for instance,
Markdown, reStructuredText, or HTML — and convert that to LaTeX.
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown"&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; in particular is very
simple, and easy to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For relatively straightforward documents, that's an alternative to give
you the benefit of nicely typeset output, without having to bother
writing LaTeX directly. This can give you a handy subset of LaTeX in
potentially a simpler markup, especially with Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, LaTeX remains flexible and powerful and, especially for
creating more complicated documents, it still retains popularity more
than thirty years after its first development. Furthermore, it's also
released under an open source license (the LaTeX Project Public License)
so these professional-level tools are available to everyone at no cost.
If you have the likes of long reports or a thesis to write, it's
certainly still worth a look.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="LaTeX"></category><category term="document preparation"></category><category term="word processor"></category></entry><entry><title>Building a music collection on a budget</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/building-a-music-collection-on-a-budget" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-04T13:55:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-04-04T13:55:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-04-04:posts/building-a-music-collection-on-a-budget</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of months back I wrote something on trying to find inexpensive music
for DJ sets for DJ TechTools which just &lt;a href="http://djtechtools.com/2017/04/02/dj-music-for-a-budget-beatmatcher/"&gt;got posted
there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's another two tips here that I didn't think to include there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="amazon-primes-no-rush-delivery"&gt;Amazon Prime's No-Rush delivery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least in the UK, if you have an Amazon Prime account, and you buy things
shipped from Amazon, currently you're probably eligible to opt for a &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=201910750"&gt;slower
delivery&lt;/a&gt;
with the benefit of a £1 digital credit applied to your account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This credit can be used for music purchases, and as individual MP3s on Amazon
are often just 99p or less, that usually means you can pick up a track for free
in addition to whatever you actually were ordering in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's possible to further benefit from this too. When you're planning an order
of multiple eligible items, breaking that one order up into orders of
individual items allows you to multiply the credit by the number of items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure you do use the credit though since they expire after some time. It's
maybe worth keeping a want list to ensure you know exactly what to spend your
next credit on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="compilations-can-be-competitively-priced"&gt;Compilations can be competitively priced&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With compilations, you'll often find that, versus buying individual tracks,
you'll get more value for money, and can be a quick way to build up a
collection, especially if you're looking for well-known hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are, say, five tracks that you're after on a compilation, and you get
another fifty or so bundled in for a few pounds more than buying the five
individual digital tracks, that's not a bad deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you get the case where the CD version of the compilation
contains mixes, whereas the digital version may have the mixes (which
you probably don't care about too much; there are more mixes around than
I'd ever have time to listen to) and the individual tracks (which you do
want).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to sound like I'm just advertising Amazon here, as it may
be that other digital music stores offer the same kind of deals,
although I've not investigated them. But, Amazon can be particularly
competitive, again when you "arbitrage" buying MP3s via lower priced CDs
which feature
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=201377450"&gt;AutoRip&lt;/a&gt;
bundled MP3s, as I mentioned in the &lt;a href="http://djtechtools.com/2017/04/02/dj-music-for-a-budget-beatmatcher/"&gt;original DJ TechTools
post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example: at the time of writing, &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/I-Love-Garage-Various-Artists/dp/B0163D5WEQ/"&gt;this
compilation&lt;/a&gt;
is £5 for the CD &lt;strong&gt;which has MP3s provided via AutoRip&lt;/strong&gt;, versus £9.99 for
the MP3 version. Seeing Roy Davis Jr's Gabriel on there, you might think
that £5 for just that track is worth paying, but there are another 65
tracks on there too.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Surprisingly, there's very little filler on
there, and while there are a few radio edits on there, most tracks are
the full length versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bonus here is that you also get instant digital delivery on the
bundled MP3s when buying the CD version too. The only differences are
that you've paid less and get a redundant bit of plastic through the
post a few days later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since it was such ridiculously good value, I just impulse bought that
  compilation.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="DJ"></category><category term="MP3"></category><category term="music"></category></entry><entry><title>Type:Rider: A Re:view</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/typerider-a-review" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-29T00:31:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-03-29T00:31:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-03-29:posts/typerider-a-review</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2 id="a-journey-through-history"&gt;A journey through history&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typography is ubiquitous and present in our daily lives, often without even
noticing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a quote from &lt;a href="http://typerider.arte.tv/"&gt;Type:Rider&lt;/a&gt;, what the
developers call a "game documentary" and what I'd call a slightly frustrating,
albeit compelling museum-style whistle stop tour through fonts and typography
across human civilisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the quote is spot on. Typography is everywhere, and though that's difficult
to imagine for us today — just take a look around — it wasn't always like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type:Rider goes on a journey from cave paintings, through to early writing
systems, such as cuneiform and hieroglyphics, then onwards to the spread of
printing across late medieval Europe, and the continued development of fonts,
typography, all the way to the current age where words being marked on media
has made way for being displayed on screen instead. So then, this is as much a
study of the spread of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only is it a journey through history for the player, but for the two dots
comprising a colon that the player controls. They roll along the level and can,
somewhat inexplicably, jump and wall jump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="typerider-is-no-nightsky"&gt;Type:Rider is no NightSky&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why two dots when, say, a full stop could have sufficed? Perhaps that's to
avoid accusations of being a clone of Nifflas' relaxing
&lt;a href="http://nifflas.ni2.se/?page=NightSky"&gt;NightSky&lt;/a&gt;. If anything, the extra dot is
a hindrance; it makes the clumsy platforming even clumsier, and doesn't really
add anything to the gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extra dot aside, it is reminiscent of NightSky (itself a game you should check
out) and I think the difficulty and the slightly sparse, often monochrome
foreground level layouts are why comparisons are drawn to Playdead's
&lt;a href="http://www.playdead.com/games/limbo/"&gt;Limbo&lt;/a&gt;. That, as well as the difficulty.
The difficulty is another reason that Type:Rider seems to get compared to
Trials, but this is a more loose association only. The Trials games are finely
balanced and tuned, so as to allow for mastery of very delicate, precise
controls. Type:Rider, unfortunately, is not. Quite often you'll end up bouncing
off uselessly from walls, or find your &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xfKhDiUNOG0"&gt;pitiful leaps are insufficient to jump
the chasms&lt;/a&gt; that you need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK. It's not actually that glitchy — it's definitely no &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3MWEHwvcnyM"&gt;Sonic the Hedgehog
2006&lt;/a&gt; — but the floatiness of how
the dots "jump" and move, mean that there are some sections that are
frustrating where you'll repeatedly bounce to your doom. With the addition of a
couple of cheap instant death sections which seem like they were thrown in as
attempts to add tension, it would have been just nicer to have a relaxing, easy
to progress through, game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the plus side, restarts are quick and the checkpoints frequent, so it's rare
that you find yourself repeating familiar ground. It does still break the flow
of what would be an otherwise relaxing experience, but this at least tempers
player frustration. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="but-typeriders-still-worth-a-look"&gt;But Type:Rider's still worth a look&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all a pity, because the actual atmosphere, that of something like a very
immersive museum exhibit is a pleasant one. The graphic designs of the levels,
and the integration of fonts into them, are well thought out, and thematically
cohesive in the ideas they're trying to portray and show imagination. The
historical background is provided via brief, but informative, texts that are
collected throughout the levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some peculiar issues, likely due to a quickly thrown together English
localisation. There is one notably particularly bad translation that recurs
throughout: the term &lt;em&gt;wheelbase&lt;/em&gt; peculiarly gets mentioned in the text several
times. The Steam discussion forum for the game actually answered this: it's a
&lt;a href="https://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/french-english/empattement"&gt;badly proofread
translation&lt;/a&gt;:
it should be &lt;em&gt;serif&lt;/em&gt;. Likewise, there are some weird text kerning issues in the
history text too, and it's likely that these too don't occur in the French
original. But that's an oversight considering that the game is dealing with
typography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scope of the game means that it is limited to telling a few stories, but as
an introduction to some of the big names in history and the technological
advances made, it does a good job. It is interesting just how important the
onset of widespread dissemination of information has been, and the impact that
has had since. We take the immediacy of that for granted now — you could well
be reading this text that I wrote seconds after I published it on this site,
wherever you are in the world — but the distribution of printed works on any
useful scale wasn't even a concept until the late medieval period, just a few
hundred years ago. It's difficult to comprehend that when information is so
central to society now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also interesting where Type:Rider leaves off, which is the development of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generalized_Markup_Language"&gt;markup languages&lt;/a&gt;,
and computer bitmap and vector fonts. A really big omission, perhaps because it
was made a few years ago, back in 2013, is emoji. (However, emoji were big
enough in 2013 to make it into the &lt;a href="http://public.oed.com/the-oed-today/recent-updates-to-the-oed/previous-updates/december-2013-update/new-words-katherine-martin/"&gt;Oxford English
Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;.)
Electronic communication saw the incorporation of emoticons, constructed from
text to hint at tone where plain text may be ambiguous. That's been followed by
the widespread use of emoji, where characters visually represent concepts or
objects, and so that nicely brings us full circle: modern day communication
harking back to how writing systems first began.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the idea of spending a couple of hours learning about typography is
something that sounds appealing, Type:Rider's worth spending the time with.
Just take the gameplay for what it is, which is occasionally relaxing,
sometimes frustrating, be prepared to work through the trickier sections. It's
certainly hard to dislike a work that even manages to make a valiant attempt of
painting &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2017/mar/28/how-we-made-font-comic-sans-typography"&gt;Comic Sans
MS&lt;/a&gt;
in a somewhat sympathetic light.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="game"></category><category term="review"></category></entry><entry><title>If you want my money, please state your payment processor clearly</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/if-you-want-my-money-please-state-your-payment-processor-clearly" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-06T23:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-06T23:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-03-06:posts/if-you-want-my-money-please-state-your-payment-processor-clearly</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I got a nice letter in the post informing me that my vehicle tax
was due. Wonderful news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, off I dutifully went to the appropriate &lt;a href="https://gov.uk"&gt;GOV.UK&lt;/a&gt;
site to pay the tax: it's not like it's an option if you want to keep
your car on the road legally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're not in the UK, or you are but haven't taxed a vehicle
recently, it's quite simple. They send you a paper reminder. This is
also a form that you can take into a Post Office and pay there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paying this online, you're asked for a reference number from the
reminder. There's a check made that your car has a valid &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOT_test"&gt;MOT
certificate&lt;/a&gt; (which establishes
your vehicle's roadworthiness) and then asks you for payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I'm using
&lt;a href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/taking-control-of-chromium-and-chrome"&gt;uMatrix&lt;/a&gt; in
my browser, I can spot which sites other than the one I'm directly
visiting have content which is supposed to be loaded into the current
page. The payment form didn't initially load and I noticed a blocked
site: "ephapay.net".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, I've never heard of them: let's check them out and make sure they're
someone I can trust. I didn't anticipate that the UK government's
website would be using someone dodgy, but best to check anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few searches via web search engines didn't reveal anything about this
domain. Even weirder, the WHOIS information is all hidden by a privacy
service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admin Name: PERFECT PRIVACY, LLC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely a legitimate payment processor wouldn't hide their details?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did reveal who was operating the site was right at the end of the
WHOIS information, in the name server details:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Name Server: NS1.THE-LOGIC-GROUP.COM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and turns out to be benign. They're a payment processor that got
acquired by Barclaycard in 2014. And I've heard of Barclaycard&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. And
the WHOIS information for the-logic-group.com actually points to their
business address. So, it seems that at least they're a established
company (since 1988, a Companies House search will tell you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I had to dig through to establish all that. It would have been much
easier if the GOV.UK vehicle tax site just stated clearly who the
payment processor is. I almost considered just reverting to paying the
tax in person when I first encountered the mysterious site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the UK government has going for them is that road users who want to
stay legal must pay this, so one way or another, online or offline,
they'll get your cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are other sites that have similar behaviour and don't have a
captive audience. There have been several cases where I'm interested in
paying for a product or service, and hit some anonymous looking page or
iframe pointing somewhere else, where it's down to my browser showing
details of blocked requests and content that reveal who's handling
payment (yes, of course, you could also search in the source too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, common culprits of having vague payment pages are sites that
handle ticket payments for small shows, or sites that let you book a
place at running events. I'm sure there are more. And it really does
deter me: if I'm not sure if my payment details are safe, I'd rather not
bother, especially if it's something I can live without.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're designing a website, bear this in mind: for the sake of
placing a small, clear explanation of how payment works, and why the
user should trust you and your payment processor, you can remove another
stumbling block that you're putting in the way of getting more paranoid
or technically savvy users to give you money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If nothing else, you have them to thank/blame for inspiring Rowan
Atkinson's Johnny English.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="security"></category><category term="UI"></category><category term="UX"></category></entry><entry><title>Fixing horrible wireless network pings in Ubuntu (2017 edition)</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/fixing-horrible-wireless-network-pings-in-ubuntu-2017-edition" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-03T16:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-03T16:44:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-03-03:posts/fixing-horrible-wireless-network-pings-in-ubuntu-2017-edition</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I was using my laptop on battery power and I remembered that I
hadn't disabled wifi power management since I reinstalled Ubuntu in
late 2016. With power management enabled for wifi, I find I get laggy
internet on battery power, and pings are noticeably higher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you suspect this is affecting you, it's easy to check:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ iwconfig 2&amp;gt; /dev/null &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; grep &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Power Management&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
Power Management:on
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the &lt;a href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/horrible-wireless-network-pings-in"&gt;method I wrote about
previously to disable wifi power
management&lt;/a&gt; no
longer works. My guess is that this is due to Ubuntu switching to
systemd in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, you need to use an alternative approach as &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/jcberthon/ea8cfe278998968ba7c5a95344bc8b55"&gt;suggested in this
post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, look at your existing configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ &lt;span class="nb"&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; /etc/NetworkManager/conf.d/
$ ls
default-wifi-powersave-on.conf
$ sudo cp default-wifi-powersave-on.conf wifi-powersave-off.conf
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The new .conf filename must follow any other files alphabetically, in
this case the filename must be one that's alphabetically later than
&lt;code&gt;default-wifi-powersave-on&lt;/code&gt;, so that it gets applied last, and your
modified setting overrides the default. If we named this file, e.g.
&lt;code&gt;a-wifi-powersave-off-config.conf&lt;/code&gt;, our new settings wouldn't apply
since the filename would then be ahead of
&lt;code&gt;default-wifi-powersave-on.conf&lt;/code&gt; alphabetically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, edit the new file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sudoedit wifi-powersave-off.conf
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Change what is likely a 3 in the &lt;code&gt;wifi.powersave&lt;/code&gt; line to 2. This
disables wireless power management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It likely will look like this when you've edited it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;[connection]
wifi.powersave = 2
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now, restart NetworkManager and you should see that this change is now
in effect. It should also persist across reboots. You can confirm this
again with &lt;code&gt;iwconfig&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;$ sudo systemctl restart NetworkManager
$ iwconfig 2&amp;gt; /dev/null &lt;span class="p"&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; grep &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;Power Management&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
Power Management:off
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="high"></category><category term="ping"></category><category term="latency"></category><category term="wireless"></category><category term="wifi"></category><category term="Ubuntu"></category></entry><entry><title>The dangers of long forgotten Bitbucket team accounts</title><link href="http://www.stevenmaude.co.uk/posts/the-dangers-of-long-forgotten-bitbucket-team-accounts" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-04T21:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-04T21:30:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Steven Maude</name></author><id>tag:www.stevenmaude.co.uk,2017-02-04:posts/the-dangers-of-long-forgotten-bitbucket-team-accounts</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last month, I'd been reviewing some of the shared accounts for online
services we have at work. Often, users have an individual login for
online services. Some services don't offer that feature and there's a
single account that's shared by everyone. While digging around, I found
details for a shared Bitbucket account. If everyone has their own
Bitbucket account, then what's this one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logging in worked, and allowed me access to an account for the team
itself; there was no user, as such. Not only could this team account
access the team, but with full permissions. Furthermore, this account
had no settings of its own. If you accessed the settings page, you got
the team's settings, not that of this team account, so it wasn't
possible to change any security settings for the account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With one of these "legacy" accounts lying around, it's possible that it
is sat there with only password authentication — Bitbucket &lt;a href="https://blog.bitbucket.org/2015/09/10/two-step-verification-is-here/"&gt;introduced
two-factor
authentication&lt;/a&gt;
late, in 2015 — an unchangeable (and maybe weak, depending on your
policies) password, and with full team access.&lt;sup id="fnref:1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:1" rel="footnote"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes this particularly insidious is that if you're not aware of
this account, you'll be blissfully unaware if you look at the list of
users on your team. Even if you manage the team as an administrator,
&lt;strong&gt;this team account didn't appear as an admin user&lt;/strong&gt;. I don't even think
it counts as a billed user. Someone who gains access presumably could
maintain that silently without you being able to do anything about it,
at least if they just sat there cloning your code. Mitigating that is
the audit log which would be a giveaway if anything noisy happened. By
that point though, someone malicious could still cause a lot of problems
for you by, let's say, booting out all other team members, or deleting
all your repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I had to contact support and request them to remove this
account, since there was no way I could fix this as a team
administrator. Therefore, this is definitely something worth auditing if
you think you might have such dormant accounts, even though, according
to Atlassian, this shouldn't be the case at all. They &lt;a href="https://blog.bitbucket.org/2014/01/14/important-changes-are-coming-to-teams/"&gt;earlier
stated&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting February 18, 2014, Bitbucket will remove the ability for
individuals to log into a team with a username/email and password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert your own &lt;a href="http://www.unicode.org/emoji/charts/emoji-list.html#1f937"&gt;Unicode shrug
character&lt;/a&gt;
here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating new repositories failed, but, for instance, creating a
repo using my account (as a team administrator), then logging in as the
"team account" and using the team account to delete the test repo was
successful. I didn't test removing team members, but don't see why this
would have failed.&amp;#160;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="Bitbucket"></category><category term="security"></category></entry></feed>